<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The grand question concerning the judicature of the House of Peers, stated and argued And the case of Thomas Skinner merchant, complaining of the East India Company, with the proceedings thereupon, which gave occasion to that question, faithfully related. By a true well-wisher to the peace and good government of the kingdom, and to the dignity and authority of parliaments.</title>
            <author>Holles, Denzil Holles, Baron, 1599-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 244 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 111 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86467</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2459</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202445</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895214</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895214</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152672</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86467)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152672)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2313:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The grand question concerning the judicature of the House of Peers, stated and argued And the case of Thomas Skinner merchant, complaining of the East India Company, with the proceedings thereupon, which gave occasion to that question, faithfully related. By a true well-wisher to the peace and good government of the kingdom, and to the dignity and authority of parliaments.</title>
                  <author>Holles, Denzil Holles, Baron, 1599-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 219, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Richard Chiswel, at the two Angels and Crown in Little Brittain,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A true well-wisher = Denzil Holles.</note>
                  <note>First leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The jurisdiction of the House of Peers asserted.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Skinner, Thomas --  East India merchant --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>East India Company --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament. --  House of Lords --  Jurisdiction --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152672:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GRAND QUESTION Concerning the <hi>IVDICATVRE</hi> Of the <hi>HOVSE of PEERS,</hi> Stated and Argued.</p>
            <p>And the Caſe of THOMAS SKINNER Merchant, complaining of the <hi>Eaſt India Company,</hi> with the proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings thereupon, which gave occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to that Queſtion, faithfully related.</p>
            <p>By a true Well-wiſher to the Peace and good Government of the Kingdom, and to the Dignity and Authority of <hi>Parliaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <add>by Denril Lord Hollis. who dyed Feb: 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1<hi rend="sup">0</hi> 1679/80</add>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Judicium Dominorum Spiritualium &amp; Temporaliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt Secundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſum &amp; Conſuetudinem Parlamenti.</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſus &amp; Conſuetudo Parlamenti eſt Lex Parlamenti.</l>
               <l>Lex Parlamenti eſt Lex Angliae,</l>
               <l>Lex Angliae eſt Lex Terrae,</l>
               <l>Lex Terrae eſt Secundum Magnam Chartam:</l>
               <l>Ergo, Judicium Dominorum Spiritualium &amp; Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralium eſt ſecundum Magnam Chartam.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Chiſwel,</hi> at the two <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in <hi>Little Brittain,</hi> 1669.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:152672:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152672:2"/>
            <head>THE JURISDIC-TION OF THE Houſe of Peers ASSERTED:</head>
            <p>THe Power of the Houſe of Peers in Point of their Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture having been lately called in queſtion, upon occaſion of a <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udgement given by them in a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar Caſe, which they conceived not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>yable elſewhere in the Ordinary Courſe of Law; It will not be amiſs, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or the removing of all prejudice out of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ens minds, to make a clear Narrative <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the matter of Fact, with ſome Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations upon it, and the Additions of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome Preſidents and Arguments: Such <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> may ſerve to evince and ſet forth the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152672:3"/>ancient way of Proceeding in that Houſe as to their Judicial Capacity; even the ſame which they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to practice in ſucceeding times, and ſo leave it to the Judgement and conſcience of every unbiaſſed indifferent man, to ſatisfie himſelf, If now there hath been any Innovation, any new In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crochment of Power, any Variation from the conſtant uſage and Priviledge of the Peerage in all times, Ancient and Moderne. The buſineſs was ſincerely thus.</p>
            <p>Soon after his Majeſties happy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration, one <hi>Thomas Skinner</hi> preferred a Petition to him in Council, purpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>great Oppreſſions and Spoils Suſtained by him in the Indies from the Eaſt-India Company, robbing him of a ſhip, and goods of a great value, diſpoſſeſſing him of a Plantation he had there, a dwelling Houſe &amp; ware-Houſe at</hi> Iamby, <hi>and an Iland called</hi> Barella <hi>(which he had bought of that King) aſſaulting his perſon to the danger of his life and ſeveral other Injuries done him; For which he prayed the Kings Juſtice, to appoint a Court, Conſtable and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152672:3"/>to Heare and Determine thoſe matters, they not being otherwiſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminable by the ordinary Courſe of Law, or to put it into any other way for Juſt Relief.</hi> After ſome years At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance and Sollicitation and ſeveral Petitions of this poor mans, the King at laſt referrs it to certain Lords <hi>viz.</hi> The Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the Lord Chancellor, the Lord Privy Seal and the Lord Aſhley, to call all Parties before them, and compoſe the matter if they could; The Order of Reference runs thus.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="document">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Whereas upon the Petition of Thomas Skin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Merchant, Setting forth his Sufferings under the barbarous oppreſſions of the Eaſt-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia Company, His Majesty was Gratiouſly pleaſed by Order of the</hi> 27. <hi>of Auguſt laſt, to deferre theclearing of the matter for erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Court to determine affaires of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture till the ſecond meeting of this Board at White-Hall, and in regard the ſaid Company have Slighted the Orders of this Board, and not complyed with any References or Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, deſigning to we are out the Petitioners Life in tedious Attendances; He did by his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152672:4"/>Petition this day read at the Board, humbly pray that the ſaid Court may be now Erected, to relieve the Petitioner according to Juſtice &amp; put a Period to his grievances; Whereupon his Majeſtie preſent in Council did Order. That his Grace the Lord Arch-Biſhop of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>the Lord Chancellor, Lord Privy Seal, and the Lord Aſhley do ſend for the Governor and ſome of the Members of the</hi> Eaſt-India <hi>Company, to treat with them, and to induce them to give the ſaid</hi> Mr. Skinner <hi>ſuch reaſonable ſatisfaction, as may in ſome meaſure be anſwerable to the loſs and damage he hath ſuffered under them.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Signed</hi> John Nicholas.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Theſe Lords Referrees met, took much pains in it, ſpent ſeveral dayes; Ordered <hi>Mr. Ayloff</hi> of Counſel with <hi>Skinner</hi> to give them under his Hand a true State of the buſineſs, whoſe report I will here ſet down in <hi>Terminis.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:152672:4"/>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="document">
                        <head>The Caſe of <hi>Thomas Skinner</hi> Merchant and his demands againſt the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company for damages done him in the year <hi>1659.</hi> in <hi>India.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>IN the year <hi>1657.</hi> was a general Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Trade into the <hi>Eaſt Indies;</hi> Then <hi>Thomas Skinner</hi> furniſhed and ſet forth his Ship called the <hi>Thomas</hi> from <hi>London</hi> on a trading voyage to the <hi>Indies,</hi> and arrived there, in <hi>1658.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Compan by their Letters the <hi>7<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Maij 1658,</hi> which arrived in <hi>India</hi> in <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> following, commanded their. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents to Seize all ſhips and goods of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh trading there, and diſpoſe half to the Common-wealth, and half to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
                        <p>The Agents of <hi>Bantam</hi> direct thoſe of <hi>Iamby</hi> to ſeize the Eſtate of <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick Skinner</hi> in the hands of <hi>Thomas;</hi> ſaying, <hi>Thomas</hi> had nothing there of his own; and that <hi>Thomas Leaver</hi> chiefe of <hi>Jamby,</hi> ſhould ſecure in his hands what Eſtate he had of <hi>Fredericks,</hi> for a Debt ſuggeſted owing by him to the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152672:5"/>Company; upon which pretences they ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed <hi>Thomas Skinners</hi> Ship and Goods, broke open his Ware-Houſe; aſſaulted him in his Houſe, and diſpoſſeſt him of his I ſtand <hi>Barella;</hi> for which Injuries he hopes ſatisfaction, and therefore in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar demands,</p>
                        <p>
                           <table>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>For <hi>128</hi> Peculls of Pepper, <hi>24</hi> Peculls of Nutmegs, and for Beef, ſtrong Waters, and other Proviſions and Merchandizes, taken out of his Ship by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents of <hi>Jamby</hi> and the Crew of the Ship Dragon, then in the Companies ſervice.</cell>
                                 <cell role="label">Ryals</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell> </cell>
                                 <cell>
                                    <hi>3355</hi>
                                 </cell>
                              </row>
                           </table>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Company agree the Value <hi>3160</hi> Ryalls brought to their Account, but it being proved, That the reſt was laden on Board <hi>Skinners</hi> Ship, this imbezlement or ſubduction by the Agents is juſt to lie upon the Company.</p>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:152672:5"/>
                        <p>
                           <table>
                              <row>
                                 <cell> </cell>
                                 <cell role="label">
                                    <hi>Ryals.</hi>
                                 </cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>For his Ship and Furniture, ſworn by two Witneſſes to be worth, when ſet out, five or ſix and twenty thouſand pounds ſterling, and that ſhe was worth as much or more in <hi>India</hi> when ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, yet abate a fiſt for ware and tare rests,</cell>
                                 <cell>
                                    <hi>8000.</hi>
                                 </cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>For eleven ſmall Copper Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and their Field Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, <hi>350</hi> Ryals, and two Quoyles of Ropes <hi>80</hi> Ryals, in all,</cell>
                                 <cell>
                                    <hi>0430.</hi>
                                 </cell>
                              </row>
                              <pb n="8" facs="tcp:152672:6"/>
                              <row>
                                 <cell> </cell>
                                 <cell role="label">Ryalls.</cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>For <hi>10</hi> Barrels of Engliſh Powder, at <hi>25</hi> Ryals <hi>per</hi> Barrel, and Sword Blades, Spectacles, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Glaſſes, Boxes, Knives, Ciſors, and other ſmall Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes, Iron Works, Nails, Piſtols, Pictures, &amp; Looking Glaſſes with Ebony Frames on board, &amp; Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planks, and other Wood on ſhore, and in the Ware-Houſe, valued by <hi>Marmaduke Grimſton,</hi> and <hi>Peter de Barrier</hi> Purſer of the Ship at</cell>
                                 <cell>
                                    <hi>1730.</hi>
                                 </cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>For Moneys owing by <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Leaver</hi> to <hi>Frederick Skin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> aſſigned to <hi>Thomas,</hi> and accepted by <hi>Leaver</hi> with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to pay, but detained by Order of the Company, who have in their hands a greater Summe of <hi>Leavers</hi> to indem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie them against this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</cell>
                                 <cell>
                                    <hi>1521.</hi>
                                 </cell>
                              </row>
                              <pb n="9" facs="tcp:152672:6"/>
                              <row>
                                 <cell>For his Charges at <hi>Jamby</hi> ſix Moneths under that trouble, and coming home over Land from <hi>India 19</hi> Moneths travel; the Companies Agents refuſing to give him paſſage in their Ships,</cell>
                                 <cell>
                                    <hi>1800.</hi>
                                 </cell>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                 <cell role="total">Totall</cell>
                                 <cell role="total">
                                    <hi>16836</hi> Ryalls.</cell>
                              </row>
                           </table>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Intereſt for 16836 Ryalls for ſix years.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Ryals are valued at <hi>Jamby 5</hi> 
                           <abbr>
                              <hi>s</hi>
                           </abbr> per Ryal: But what they produce here, being brought over in black Pepper to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany clear of all Charges, is expected, they will ingenouſly own.</p>
                        <p>For
<list>
                              <item>The Aſsault of his Perſon,</item>
                              <item>Loſs of ſix years Time,</item>
                              <item>Diſappointment of his Trade,</item>
                              <item>Attendance and Charge here,</item>
                              <item>Diſſeizin of his Iſland.</item>
                           </list>
Being valuable at more than all the other particulars, are humbly ſubmitted to your Lordſhips Diſcretion.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Signed <hi>Joſeph Ayloff.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:152672:7"/>
            <p>The Lords Referrees to this requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Anſwer of the Company, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this as follows.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="document">
                        <head>To the Right Honourable the Lords Referrees, concerning the Demands of <hi>Thomas Skinner</hi> upon the Eaſt India Company.</head>
                        <p>IN obedience to your Lordſhips Order and Direction, the Court of Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees of the ſaid Company have conſidered of the Matter propoſed by your Lordſhips, and do humbly offer to your Lordſhips; That for the Nutmegs, white Pepper, and other things, which were ſeized by the Juſtice of the place in part of a Debt due to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany from <hi>Frederick Skinner,</hi> which ſaid Goods were brought to the Companies Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts, though the ſame were afterwards loſt in the Ship <hi>Dragon;</hi> and in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the Accompts between the Company and <hi>Frederick</hi> are concluded, and the ſaid Goods not included therein; the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany have alwaies offered to pay for the ſaid Goods, and are now ready to pay <hi>3160</hi> Dollars for the ſame, which at <hi>4</hi> 
                           <abbr>
                              <hi>s</hi>
                           </abbr> 
                           <hi>9.</hi> 
                           <abbr>
                              <hi>d</hi>
                           </abbr>
                           <pb n="11" facs="tcp:152672:7"/>
                           <hi>per</hi> Dollar, amounts unto the ſumme of <hi>750</hi> 
                           <abbr>
                              <hi>l</hi>
                           </abbr> 
                           <hi>10</hi> 
                           <abbr>
                              <hi>s</hi>
                           </abbr> And concerning the <hi>1521</hi> Dollars demanded by <hi>Thomas Skinner,</hi> as a Debt due unto him from <hi>Thomas Leaver;</hi> they in complyance with your Lordſhips deſires will bè ready and willing to pay the ſaid fifteen hundred twenty one Dollars, amounting to <hi>361</hi> 
                           <abbr>
                              <hi>l</hi>
                           </abbr> 
                           <hi>4</hi> 
                           <abbr>
                              <hi>s</hi>
                           </abbr> 
                           <hi>9</hi> 
                           <abbr>d</abbr> to the ſaid <hi>Thomas Skinner,</hi> ſo as they may be diſcharged by the Adminiſtrator of the ſaid <hi>Thomas Leaver,</hi> to whom only they are liable, it being very reaſonable that the Company pay the Debt but once. But the Company do utterly diſavow, that the Company can by any Law or Equity be liable for their Factors Debts.</p>
                        <p>Concerning <hi>Skinners</hi> other Demands for his Ship and for other Goods pretended to be ſeized on ſhore, The Company do humbly offer to your Lordſhips; That the Company are not liable for the Debt or Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Factors, unleſs done by their Order; and if the Company ſhould be liable to every ones Clamors, and preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for wrongs done, or pretended to be done by their Factors (when if any ſuch thing were done, the ſame was not by their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152672:8"/>or Knowledge, nor appliable to their uſe and accompt) the ſame will neceſſarily impoveriſh and ruine the Company: And the Company gave no Order for the ſeizure of <hi>Thomas Skinners</hi> ſhip, nor nothing elſe of his; nor was the ſame brought to the Companies accompt, and the Agents at <hi>Bantam</hi> expreſly ordered the Factors at <hi>Jamby</hi> not to meddle with the ſaid <hi>Thomas Skinners</hi> ſhip, who acted accordingly: For it appears clearly, That Captain <hi>Allnut</hi> and his Mariners had his Proviſions and Stores for their Wages, and that the King of <hi>Jamby</hi> and <hi>Jehore</hi> ſeized and kept the ſhip; And his Goods on ſhore were ſeized on by Chinenſes, and other his Creditors; and therefore they hope that his continual clamours of oppreſſion ſhall not take any Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion in your Lordſhips great Judgments, the Company not being able to put a price up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an oppreſſion, where none was, at leaſt that they are concerned in: Yet for the procuring of their own peace and quiet, and to prevent all further trouble unto your Lordſhips and the Company, they do ſubmit unto your Lordſhips diſpoſal ſuch further ſumme as will make the whole amount to <hi>1500</hi> 
                           <abbr>l</abbr>
                           <pb n="13" facs="tcp:152672:8"/>which is more than his ſhip and Goods were ever worth, or valued at upon the Inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance at her going forth, ſo as the Company may have thereupon full and final Releaſes and Diſcharges from the ſaid <hi>Thomas Skinner</hi> and <hi>Frederick Skinner.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>September <hi>28. 1666.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>By Order of the ſaid Company. Signed</hi> Jo. Stanyon <hi>Secr.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>To which</hi> Skinner <hi>makes this Reply.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:152672:9"/>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="document">
                        <head>To the Right Honourable the Lords Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrees, concerning the Damages done to <hi>Thomas Skinner</hi> Merchant, by the East India Company.</head>
                        <head type="sub">The humble Reply of <hi>Thomas Skinner,</hi> to the Propoſals of the ſaid Company.</head>
                        <p>THat ſince the Rapine and Spoil of the Companies Agents by their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, took from me Nutmegs, white Pepper, Proviſions, &amp;c. Of <hi>3355</hi> Ryals value, if but <hi>3160</hi> Ryals came to their Accompt, yet are they anſwerable for the whole, which as the Juſtice of <hi>Jam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byes</hi> Atteſtation, That they took all with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Reaſon, moniſhes them of the duty of Reſtitution, ſo the periſhing thereof in and with the Companies Ship Dragon threatens them with the Improſperity of ill gotten goods; And then though Ryals Coſt put on Ship-board in <hi>England</hi> but <hi>4</hi> 
                           <abbr>
                              <hi>s</hi>
                           </abbr> 
                           <hi>9</hi> 
                           <abbr>
                              <hi>d</hi>
                           </abbr> or <hi>5</hi> 
                           <abbr>s</abbr> as they go for <hi>India,</hi> yet they come home at above <hi>15</hi> 
                           <abbr>
                              <hi>s</hi>
                           </abbr> clear, as by Oath of the Companies own Servants appears, that when Pepper was ſold at <hi>London</hi> but <hi>11</hi> 
                           <abbr>
                              <hi>d</hi>
                           </abbr>
                           <pb n="15" facs="tcp:152672:9"/>a pound, though the Company ſold ever ſince <hi>Anno 1660</hi> at <hi>11</hi> 
                           <abbr>
                              <hi>d</hi>
                           </abbr> 
                           <hi>13</hi> 
                           <abbr>
                              <hi>d</hi>
                           </abbr> 
                           <hi>14</hi> 
                           <abbr>
                              <hi>d</hi>
                           </abbr> 
                           <hi>½</hi> and upwards; therefore they are juſtly ſo demanded with Intereſt.</p>
                        <p>The <hi>1521</hi> Ryals owing formerly by <hi>Leaver</hi> is become the Companies Debt, not only becauſe he was their Servant and Agent, but becauſe it was ſeized for them, and they have ſo much in their hands for my ſatisfaction, and therefore are Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers thereof to my uſe, and may now pay it as ſafely, as they ought honeſtly to have paid it long ſince with Intereſt in manner as thoſe above mentioned.</p>
                        <p>Concerning, my ſhip and goods taken on ſhore, my Perſecution in <hi>Jamby</hi> and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Journey home, for which the Company offer payment by Fictions and Reproaches, the ſence which the King of <hi>Jamby</hi> (who would have made that Factory a Publick Example, had not my importunate Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions in Confidence to find Juſtice at home prevented it) had of the Agents Inhumani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; And which, as their own Letters wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt them, was by their Order, what ever pretended againſt <hi>Frederick,</hi> execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt my ſelf, and afterward owned by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152672:10"/>the Company, cannot but goade their private Conſciences, how Inſenſible ſoever the Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique Conſcience of a Corporation be, as it did <hi>Allnuts</hi> upon his death bed, (who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and repented ſorely, That he had been inticed and incited by the Agents unjuſtly againſt me, and had nothing of the depreda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;) With what modeſty do the Company then upbraid me with pretended debts, and calumniat the King and people of thoſe parts, and ſo much undervalue my Ship and Oppreſſion, when the contrary (to the Companies Knowledg) is ſo clearly manifeſt; Nor are they ignorant of the hopeful De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne in my Plantation and valuable Trade they have deſtroyed me of; (which, though it plainly appears) That my Ships intended Voyage for <hi>Maccaſſor,</hi> and freight thence, for which Conſideration above <hi>2000</hi> Ryalls is deducted from the Ships worth, and other particulars in a Schedule, would have rendred alone above <hi>20000</hi> 
                           <abbr>
                              <hi>l</hi>
                           </abbr> ſterling yearly: Yet I ſubmit that, and my whole Sufferings and Concerns, to your Lordſhips Determination, in hopes, That if I do not receive an adequate Recompence; yet I ſhall by his Majeſties Grace, and your Lordſhips
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152672:10"/>direction, be enabled, by the reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of my Iſland <hi>Barella</hi> in <hi>India,</hi> to reap a future benefit without the <hi>Eaſt India</hi> Companies further moleſtation or interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, His Majeſties late Charter granted the third of <hi>April 1661.</hi> prohibiting the Company expreſly to undertake any thing againſt any Chriſtian Colonie ſetled in <hi>India</hi> before the date thereof.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>
                                 <hi>October</hi> the <hi>6. 1666.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>Signed <hi>Thomas Skinner</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>THe Lords Referrees finding this vaſt diſproportion between the demands and Pretences of the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner, and the real loſs and damage which he had ſuſtained; and the Offers on the other Side of the Company for his Reparation and Satisfaction, and ſeeing no poſſibility of reconciling them, though much pains had been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in endeavouring it, at laſt reſolved to report it back to the King and Councel; and made their Report as followeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:152672:11"/>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="document">
                        <p>IN purſuance of his Majeſties Order in Councel dated the three and twentieth of <hi>March</hi> laſt; we have treated with the Governor and Company of <hi>Merchants</hi> trading into the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> and have heard the Councel both of the ſaid Company, and <hi>Thomas Skinner</hi> Complainant, in the diſquiſition whereof we found the ſaid <hi>Thomas Skinner</hi> to have ſuffered much wrong by the ſaid Company, and their Agents: and therefore endeavoured to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the ſaid Company to give ſatisfaction to the Petitioner: but there being a great difference between the Petitioners Demands of Reparation for Damages, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies Offer towards the ſame, our Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion proved ineffectual therein.</p>
                        <p>As to the Iſland of <hi>Barella</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi> claimed by the ſaid <hi>Thomas Skinner;</hi> We conceive that he ought to enjoy the ſame, and from thence to trade into any part of the world, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept into <hi>England.</hi> Given under Our Hands the ſixth day of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. 1666.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Signed</hi> Gilb. Cant. Clarendon C. J. Roberts. Aſhley.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:152672:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>HIs Majeſtie upon this finding the</hi> Eaſt-India <hi>Company would be brought to no reaſon, thought fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend the buſineſs to the Houſe of Peers, to do the Petitioner Juſtice according to the merits of his Cauſe, which Meſſage was brought to the Houſe the 19. of</hi> January <hi>1666 by the Lord Privy Seal, and all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in Councel tranſmitted thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and withall a Petition from</hi> Skinner <hi>himſelf was preſented to them ſetting forth the wrongs done to him by the</hi> Eaſt-India <hi>Company.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Houſe of Peers, thus poſſeſſed of this buſineſs, Order a Copy of</hi> Skinners <hi>Petition to be given to the Governor and Company, and they to bring in their Anſwer to it upon</hi> Friday <hi>the 28 of</hi> January: <hi>They accordingly bring in for Anſwer a Plea to the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of the Houſe of Lords, and ſay;</hi> That the Petition is in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of an Original complaint, not brought by way of Appeal, Bill of Review, or Writ of Error, nor intermixed with Priviledge of Parliament, nor having Reference to any
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152672:12"/>Judgement of that Court; therefore offer; If it will pleaſe to take any further Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of that Cauſe: <hi>And then plead over and ſay,</hi> That the Company was incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſeveral Charters in the Reignes of <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi> and <hi>King James,</hi> and likewiſe by a Charter from <hi>Oliver,</hi> which excluded all others not Members of the Corporation from trading in any part of the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi> within the limits of the ſaid Charter, and that therefore if any ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries were done, it was by vertue of the Charter, and whether Criminal or Civil they were for ever releaſed and diſcharged by the Act of <hi>Oblivion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lords upon debate of this Plea, well knowing their own Right to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain even Original cauſes, when ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with ſuch Circumſtances, as this then before them had; A poor man oppreſſed by potent Adverſaries, by a rich and numerous Society, where there was a Peer of the Realm, the</hi> Lord Berckley <hi>of Berckley, Gentlemen of great Eſtates, very many wealthy Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants incorporated in one body, dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving on a great trade in the</hi> Indies <hi>with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152672:12"/>one joynt ſtock, reſolved to imploy that whole ſtock for the deſtruction of any man, that ſhould preſume but to touch upon that trade without their leaves, which was this poor mans Caſe, &amp; in a time when he had been encouraged thereunto by a general Liberty then ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to trade in that Country; who after the ſpoyle of his goods and Plantation there, to ſave his life (they having beſet his paſſage by Sea) was glad to expoſe himſelf to the hazard and charge of a Journey of many thouſand Miles over Land, to return into</hi> England, <hi>that he might here endeavor to get ſome repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for all thoſe loſſes, which that Company with their great purſe and power oppoſed, and had already made him ſpend that little Eſtate he had left, and ſeven years attendance to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute that reparation without any fruite: So as to go to Law with them, and abide all the delayes and formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties even of the ordinary Proceedings at Law, much leſs what ſuch Adverſaries would have raiſed to him, he was no waies able; The Lords I ſay knowing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152672:13"/>all this, and that what was pretended of the Indemnity by the Act of Oblivion was of no validity, that Act not at all intended for things of this nature, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt party and party not relating to the Warr, made no difficulty to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule their Plea, and enter into the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition of the Fact, and to do the poor man Juſtice and give Releife if they found cauſe for it, as a work worthy of them, much conducing to the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the publick Juſtice of the Kingdome, and moſt agreable to the conſtant practice of that Houſe from the very beginning of Parliaments: Wherefore they appointed Tueſday the 24 of</hi> January <hi>for the Counſel of both ſides to be heard at the Barr. But ſuch art was uſed, ſo many delayes caſt in by the Company and their Counſel, as the cauſe could not be brought to hearing during all that Seſſion of Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>At the next meeting of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the year 1667.</hi> Skinner <hi>renued his ſuit and preſented a Petition the 30. day of</hi> October, <hi>In</hi> haec verba.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:152672:13"/>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE &amp;c.</head>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>The Humble Petition &amp;c.</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>THat in the year</hi> 1657. <hi>Private Trade being open in the</hi> Eaſt-Indies, <hi>the Petitioner ſet forth his ſhip</hi> Thomas <hi>on a trading voyage to the ſaid</hi> Indies, <hi>where being arrived in</hi> 1658 <hi>he poſſeſſed himſelf of a Ware-houſe on the River ſide of</hi> Jam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>on which his ſhip rode, wherein he put a great part of his goods, and alſo had a houſe at</hi> Jamby <hi>and goods therein, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed of the</hi> King <hi>of</hi> Jamby <hi>the Iſland of</hi> Barella, <hi>and built a houſe for habitation, and had contracted for planting of Pepper and other Commodities thereon. That in</hi> May 1659. <hi>the Agents of the Governour and the Company of Merchants of</hi> London <hi>trading into the</hi> Eaſt-Indies, <hi>by direction of the ſaid Governour and Company, and of</hi> Maurice Tompſon, <hi>and</hi> Sir. Andrew Riccard, <hi>ſeeing the Petitioners hopeful deſigne in his Plantation and way of trade with his Ship, did ſeize for and on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152672:14"/>of the ſaid Governour and Company his ſaid Ship, goods, houſes, Iſtands and</hi> 1521 <hi>Dollars of the Petitioners in the hands of</hi> Thomas Leaver <hi>the Companies Chief Agent at</hi> Jamby, <hi>which hath damag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him</hi> 17172 <abbr>
                              <hi>l</hi>
                           </abbr> 
                           <hi>Sterling, beſides the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment of his trade, diſſeizin of his ſaid Iſland, loſs of above ſix years time with attendance and vaſt charges here in endeavors for a juſt ſatisfaction &amp;c. being much more valuable then all the other da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages; And the ſaid Agents uſed many violences upon his perſon in the ſaid</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, <hi>notwithſtanding that the Petitioner proffered Bail and good Security there, to anſwer all their pretences; which inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane and unreaſonable dealing, forced the Petitioner through infinite hazards and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence to come moſt over Land for</hi> England, <hi>to ſeek redreſs.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>That in the year</hi> 1661 <hi>and continually ſince he hath humbly beſought his Majeſty for Juſtice againſt the ſaid Governour and Company, and perſons aforeſaid; and though his Majeſty hath been graciouſly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to convene the ſaid Company and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and to hear the ſaid Matters; and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152672:14"/>alſo to referre it divers times to ſeveral Lords of his Majeſties moſt Honourable Privy Councel, to hear them and mediate an End; yet they could not be reduced to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon nor Juſtice, albeit the Petitioners Wrongs and Damages were made to appear, as well by their own acknowledgement, as other evidence produced before the Lords Referrees; but endeavoured by the ſtrength of their Joynt-Purſe to bear down the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners Relief, though never ſo juſt, by wearying him from further Proſecution.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>That the Petitioners whole Caſe not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing remediable by the Courts below, he is conſtrained humbly to addreſs himſelf to your Lordſhips, his Majeſties great Councel and Supreme Judicature, whom the Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner most humbly petitioned the laſt Seſſions, and your Lordſhips were pleaſed to order their Attendance, but by their Dilatory Pleas and ſeveral non-attendances upon ſlight excuſes at the day appointed by your Lordſhips, they fruſtrated the Petitioner of obtaining your Lordſhips Juſtice that Seſſion.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <pb n="26" facs="tcp:152672:15"/>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Wherefore he moſt humbly prayes, That your Lordſhips will be pleaſed to cauſe the ſaid Governour and Company and perſons aforeſaid to anſwer the premiſſes before your Lordſhips by a ſhort day, and that he may receive from your Lordſhips ſuch Relief as ſhall be conſiſtent with Juſtice and Equity.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>And he ſhall pray, &amp;c. Signed <hi>Thomas Skinner.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>The Lords upon this, order the Company to put in their Anſwer in Writing upon Wedneſday the 6<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of <hi>November.</hi> They bring in a Plea as before; Firſt by way of Proteſtation, <hi>That all the Injuries ſuppoſed to be commited by them and their Factors are untrue;</hi> Then plead as formerly, <hi>That the Petition is in the Nature of an Original Complaint, not brought by way of appeal, &amp;c.</hi> as in their Plea of the laſt Seſſion: but add, <hi>And therefore theſe Reſpondents do humbly demand the Judgement of this honourable Court, whither it will pleaſe to take any
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152672:15"/>other or further Cognizance of the ſame; the rather, becauſe the matters of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint in the Petition are ſuch, for which remedy is ordinarily given in the Courts of</hi> Weſtminſter-Hall, <hi>wherein theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondents have Right to be tried, and ought not to be brought hither</hi> per ſaltum, <hi>nor drawn</hi> ad aliud examen: and ſo pray to be diſmiſſed.</p>
            <p>The Lords having received this Plea, to ſhew the clearneſs of their Intentions, and their tenderneſs of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing which might but carry a Semblance, That they deſired to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſs to themſelves the judging of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Cauſes, (when determinable elſewhere, and nothing extraordinary in the Caſe to induce their Lordſhips to take Cognizance of the Matter, which apparently was in this Caſe of <hi>Skinners,</hi> as hath been ſaid before) would have the Opinion of all the Judges, before they proceeded any further; And therefore made an Order, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the 2<hi rend="sup">d.</hi> of December, <hi>That it be referred to all the Judges to conſider of</hi> Skinners <hi>Petition, and to Report to the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152672:16"/>Houſe upon the Wedneſday following, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Petitioner were relievable upon the matters therein mentioned in Law or Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and if ſo, in what manner, upon the ſeveral parts of the Complaints of the ſaid Petition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The day appointed the Judges came, and the Lord Chief Juſtice of the Kings Bench, reported, <hi>That all the Judges had conſidered of the Matter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to them, and having met and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered thereof, were of Opinion; That the Matters touching the taking away of the Petitioners Ship and Goods, and aſſaulting of his Perſon, notwithſtanding the ſame were done beyond the Seas, might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined in his Majeſties Ordinary Courts at</hi> Weſtminſter; <hi>And as to the diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing him of his Houſe and Iſland, That be was not relievable in any ordinary Court of Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here then clearly by the Judges own Confeſſion, part of the Caſe was not within the Power of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Hall, and under favour of better Judgements, I think it will be but a venial Sin, if notwithſtanding this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152672:16"/>of our Sages in the Law, the Doubt do ſtill remain with us, if ſome of the other points alſo, as that of the taking of his Ship, a Robbery com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted <hi>ſuper altum mare,</hi> be puniſhable by the Law of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Hall; Nay! may not one be bold to affirm, That it is not? And may it not be doubted further, if any part of <hi>Skinners</hi> Caſe be tryable there, and if their Fiction in Law will reach any part of it? being all for Injuries and Violence againſt his Perſon and Eſtate in <hi>India:</hi> We know, that ſome Judges and Lawyers make it to extend to Contracts and Bonds made beyond the Sea, which they ground upon a Caſe in the Year Book of 48 <hi>E.</hi> 3. fol. 2. where Sir <hi>Ralph Pole</hi> brings his Action againſt Sir <hi>Richard Tocheſter,</hi> upon an Obligation bearing date at <hi>Harfleet</hi> in <hi>Kent, Lou de rei ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate Il fuſt fait en Normandie;</hi> the Book ſaith; and his Action was held good: And <hi>Brook</hi> (who makes it to be at <hi>Roan,</hi> not <hi>Harfleet</hi>) gives the reaſon in his Abridgement, <hi>Faits</hi> 98. <hi>le lieu n'eſt traverſable,</hi> the place is not tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſable
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152672:17"/>which is to be underſtood, when it is expreſſed in the Bond, for a man cannot traverſe the place againſt his own Act. But the Law was ever underſtood to be otherwiſe till then, that the Judges would <hi>ampliare Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictionem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And (to ſhew what the Law was before <hi>E.</hi> 3.) it was adjudged, <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaelmas</hi> 2 <hi>E.</hi> 2. That no Action would lie for a Bond made at <hi>Barwick</hi> (which did not then belong to <hi>England) ou ceſt Court nau' coniſans,</hi> where the Court hath not cogniſance, ſaith <hi>Fitzherbert,</hi> Obligation 15. And ſo <hi>Perkins, Faites</hi> 121. But both before and ſince the Courts of Law were ſo far from pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing Injuries and Treſpaſſes done beyond Sea, That even Treaſon was not tryable till the Statute of 26 <hi>H.</hi> 8. cap. 13. which ſaith, <hi>That if any of the Kings Subjects ſhall commit Treaſon, though out of the Limits of this Realm, it ſhall be tryed in any place that the King ſhall appoint by Commiſſion under the great Seal:</hi> So a ſpecial Commiſſion was to be iſſued for it: And ſeveral other Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152672:17"/>were afterwards made of the ſame Nature; But for Treſpaſſes, as this of the <hi>Eaſt India</hi> Company againſt <hi>Skinner,</hi> there is no Act of Parliament to authoriſe the Proſecution at Common Law, nor (I think) any Book Caſe to warrant the practice of it; Book Caſes againſt it there are many, even for Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes in the Iſle of <hi>Jerſey,</hi> though with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Kings Dominions, becauſe a <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire Facias</hi> could not go thither to ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon a Jury from thence, <hi>Mich.</hi> 42 (as Mr. <hi>Prin</hi> cites it, or 41. as Sir <hi>Edw. Cook) E.</hi> 3. <hi>Coram Rege, rot.</hi> 109. <hi>An Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant of</hi> Jerſey <hi>complains to the King and Councel of falſe Impriſonment and ſeveral Injuries done him in the Iſland: They ſend this Bill of Complaint to the Judges of the Kings Bench, and there the Bill is diſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, Quia compertum eſt</hi> (ſaith the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord) <hi>quod negotium praedictum in Curia hic terminari non poteſt, eò quod Jurato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res Inſulae praedictae hic venire non poſſunt, &amp;c.</hi> Other Caſes there are of the ſame nature. And if a Fiction could not help for <hi>Jerſey</hi> being part of the Kings Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, much leſs could it help for
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152672:18"/>Forein parts, where the King had no Authority at all. Yet the Houſe of Lords hath in all times exerciſed Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction upon Crimes done and committed in Forein parts, as well as thoſe within the Kingdome, both Treaſons and other Offences, <hi>As in the Caſes of the Lord</hi> Latimer <hi>for the loſs of St.</hi> Saviour <hi>in</hi> Normandy, <hi>and Oppreſſions done by him in</hi> Britany, 50. E. 3. n. 21. <hi>Of</hi> William de Weſton, <hi>for the ſurrender of</hi> Outherwick <hi>in</hi> Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, 1. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>n.</hi> 38. John de Gome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niz <hi>for</hi> Ardes, 1. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>n.</hi> 40. Pierce de Creſſingham <hi>and</hi> John Spickworth, <hi>for the Caſtle of</hi> Drinkham <hi>in</hi> Flanders, 7. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>n.</hi> 17. <hi>The Biſhop of</hi> Norwich, <hi>for not doing Service beyond Seas according to promiſe, and as he ought to have done, for delivering up</hi> Graveling <hi>to the French, not muſtering his Army at</hi> Calice, <hi>as he ſhould have done, and not having his Number compleat.</hi> n. 18. <hi>Sir</hi> William Elinſham, <hi>Sir</hi> Thomas Trevit, <hi>Sir</hi> Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Ferrers, <hi>Sir</hi> William de Hurnedon, <hi>and</hi> Robert Fitz-Ralph, <hi>for delivering ſtrong Holds and Fortreſſes for Money,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:152672:18"/>n. 24. John Hall <hi>a Servant to the Duke of</hi> Norfolk, <hi>for Murthering the Duke of</hi> Glouceſter <hi>at</hi> Calice, 1 <hi>H.</hi> 4. n. 11. <hi>Sir</hi> William Richill <hi>for but taking the Examination of the Duke of</hi> Glouceſter <hi>at</hi> Calice, 1 <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>n.</hi> 93. And multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of others, who could not have been tryed by the Common Law, were tryed by the Houſe of Lords: And in truth a man may ſay the whole Caſe of <hi>Skinner</hi> in every point of it was only cogniſable before them; However, it being out of all diſpute, even by the Confeſſion of the Judges, That ſome things in it are not tryable in <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> Hall, I hope it may be thought reaſonable, to leave as great an extent of Power to the Houſe of Peers, which is the ſupreme Judicature of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as to the Court of Chancery, where the ordinary practice is to retain a Cauſe, when there is Equity in any part of it. The Lords therefore Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the hearing of the Cauſe, ſpent ſeveral daies in it, and having with much patience heard all that could be ſaid on both ſides, appointed a day to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152672:19"/>conſider what was fit to be done <hi>ſuper totam materiam:</hi> Upon which day, after a ſolemn debate, they came to this Reſolution only in general, That <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Skinner</hi> was to be relieved by that Houſe: And referred it to a Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee to conſider what damages he had ſuſtained by the Governour and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany trading to the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> and to report their Opinions, what Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence was fit to be given him for the ſame.</p>
            <p>Whileſt the Buſineſs was under the conſideration of the Committee, and before the Houſe of Peers had made any Determination of it, a Petition was ſaid to be preſented by the <hi>Eaſt India</hi> Company, unto the Houſe of Commons; which I will ſet down word for word before I give it any Epithete, and upon reading it, I think every unprejudicate man will ſay, one cannot give it an Epithete bad enough; the Petition was thus,</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:152672:19"/>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>TO THE HONOURABLE, The Commons of <hi>ENGLAND</hi> in Parliament Aſſembled.</head>
                        <head type="sub">The Humble Petition of the Governour and Company of Merchants of <hi>London,</hi> trading to the <hi>Eaſt Indies.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>THat</hi> Thomas Skinner <hi>lately exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Petition to the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in Parliament aſſembled, againſt your Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners (many of which are and were Members of this Honourable Houſe, when the ſaid Petition was exhibited) for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries pretended to be done by your Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners Factors in the</hi> Eaſt Indies, <hi>in ſeiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Ship, Goods and Money, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſing him of a ſmall Iſland there; all which Matters (excepting what concerns the Iſland) are Matters clearly determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable in his Majeſties Ordinary Courts of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152672:20"/>Law, as by the Judges attending their Lordſhips, hath been reſolved and report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed And for the Iſland, the ſame is parcel of the Dominions of a Foreign Prince, and ſo the Right thereof only determinable by the Laws of that Prince. That though the Petitioners did humbly tender a Plea to their Lordſhips, for that the Petition was in Nature of an Original Complaint (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Commoners only) and not brought to their Lordſhips by Writ of Error, or Bill of Review, or any way of Appeal, and that the Matters therein were relievable in the Courts of</hi> Weſtminſter <hi>Hall; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon prayed the Judgement of that High Court, whether it would pleaſe to take fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cognizance thereof: Yet their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips have been pleaſed not only to give a hearing to all the Matters in the ſaid Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion contained, but have denied to gran<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> the Petitioners a Commiſſion, or ſo much a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> time to ſend for their Witneſſes now inhabit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the place, where the Injuries were pretended to be done, and without whoſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Teſtimony it was impoſſible for the Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to make their Defence.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>That upon the ſaid hearing, their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152672:20"/>were further pleaſed to appoint a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee to aſſeſs damages againſt your Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, which Committee is now proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereon accordingly, whereby ſeveral Members of this Honourable Houſe, who are of the ſaid Company as well as others your Petitioners, may be highly detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented. All which proceedings as your Petitioners humbly ſubmit to your Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Judgements, are againſt the Laws and Statutes of this Nation, and Cuſtome of Parliament. In tender Conſideration whereof, and for as much as theſe unuſual and extraordinary Proceedings of their Lorſhips are not only grievous to your Petitioners at preſent, but may alſo be a Preſident of ill Conſequence to all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of</hi> England <hi>hereafter, and for as much as your Petitioners have no way of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief in this Caſe otherwiſe than by making their humble Addreſſes to this Honourable Houſe, your Petitioners do therefore most humbly pray, That your Honours will be pleaſed to take the Premiſſes into your grave Conſiderations, and to interpoſe with their Lordſhips for your Petitioners Relief there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152672:21"/>in ſuch way and manner as to your great Wiſdoms ſhall ſeem meet.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>And your Petitioner as in duty bound, ſhall pray, &amp;c. Signed by the Order and in the Name of the ſaid Governour and Company.</hi> Robert Blackborne <hi>Secr.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Copies of this flew about, were in every mans Pocket, and in every mans mouth, That the Lords were even forced to take notice of it, yet ſcarce could believe the Houſe of Commons would receive ſuch a Petition againſt them, ſo ſcandalous and ſo falſe; nor did they in the whole debate ſo much as mention the Houſe of Commons, but looked upon it as a thing done without doors, thrown abroad, only to blaſt and aſperſe the Houſe of Lords, and to bring them into the ill opinion and diſ-eſteem of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; which after a ſerious conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and debate, their Lordſhips voted,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152672:21"/>
               <hi>To be a ſcandalous Libel againſt the Houſe of Peers.</hi> And certainly ſo it was, both in Matter and Manner, and had the Matter been true, yet the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was ſcandalous: For though all had been true which was ſuggeſted, if the Houſe of Lords had committed an Error, had done ſome thing grievous to the Petitioners, yet was it moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for private men to cenſure their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, declare them <hi>to be unuſual and extraordinary, to be againſt the Laws and Statutes of the Nation, and Coſtome of Parliament, grievous to the Petitioners at preſent, and of ill conſequence hereafter to all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of</hi> England. Can the tongue of man utter more reproachful and ſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing words againſt any man or ſociety of men? If this were true, do they deſerve to live who are guilty of ſuch things, to continue ſo much as Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of any State or Common-wealth, much leſs to have Power and Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in it? Certainly to revile in this manner, and throw dirt upon the Higheſt Judicatory of the Kingdome,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152672:22"/>was a moſt tranſcendent Preſumption, and of a moſt dangerous Conſequence to the whole Nation, even to thoſe Commons of <hi>England,</hi> whom theſe Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners pretend for ſo much, making themſelves as it were, their Patrons and Protectors, Tribunes of the people, and withall endeavouring to bring an Odium upon the whole Peerage. What is this but ſowing ſedition between the two Houſes of Parliament, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Peers and the Commons of <hi>England?</hi> And what can it tend to, but to the very diſſolution of the Frame of Government? The Scripture ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſpeak evil of the Rulers of thy People,</hi> and <hi>Elihu</hi> in <hi>Job</hi> moves this queſtion, <hi>Is it fit to ſay to a King, Thou art wicked, and to Princes, Ye are ungodly?</hi> Yet theſe <hi>Rabſhakehs</hi> dare heap up Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches againſt the Lords of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and bring railing Accuſations againſt the Higheſt Order of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy under the King in the Kingdom. And how little Cauſe was given them for this, the preceding Narrative of the proceedings of the Lords, is, I
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152672:22"/>think, an evident demonſtration. Their Lordſhips had proceeded with all the tenderneſs imaginable, nothing of heat, nothing of Precipitation had appeared in the whole Tranſaction; They were not come to a full Concluſion and Determination of the buſineſs, which theſe Merchants had no reaſon to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that it would be ſevere upon them; And they might at leaſt have ſtaid, till it had come what ever it had been, and not have prejudged a Court, before it had declared it ſelf, what Judgment it would give: All it had then done, was but what the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company it ſelf had, by their own offer of Repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for the wrong done, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be Juſt; For the Lords had only declared, <hi>That Skinner was fit to be relieved;</hi> But what relief, how much and in what ſort, the <hi>Quid</hi> and the <hi>Quomodo,</hi> they had not determined, that was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Conſideration of a Committee. They themſelves in their Anſwer to the Lords Referrees appointed by His Majeſty in Counſel, had offered to pay unto <hi>Skinner</hi> for Nutmegs, White
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152672:23"/>Pepper, and ſome other things, which had been unjuſtly taken from him by their Factors and had been brought to their account, 3160 Dollars; And 1521 Dollars more they offered, for ſo many taken from him in <hi>Specie:</hi> And by this they confeſs they had done him wrong, and were willing to give him ſome Reparation: So without condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning themſelves, they can not ſay the Lords had as yet done amiſs: and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this moderation and Circumſpection, that opprobrious rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Petition was preferred againſt them; and which beſides was full of untruths.</p>
            <p>For the main matter in it, and which in truth had carried a ſhew of Injuſtice had it been true, is abſolutely falſe; And that is, that the Lords denied them a Commiſſion, or time to ſend for Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes inhabiting upon the place, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whoſe teſtimony it was impoſſible for them to make their defence; Firſt it is not true, that the Lords denied them a Commiſſion or time to ſend for Witneſſes, for they never inſiſted upon
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152672:23"/>it, which muſt have brought on a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the houſe, and have been entred in the Clerks Book, which was not: Some ſuch thing was once ſaid by ſome of the Councel at Barr, but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves went off it, knowing it would have groſly manifeſted their intent to delay longer a Poor man, who had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſpent ſeven years in the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that ſuit; And as untrue is it, that they could not elſe make their defence, for multitudes of Witneſſes were produced by them, and all fully heard with Patience, and enough ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged even by their own Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes (and more by their own offer (formerly mentioned) of giving <hi>Skinner</hi> ſo many thouſand Dollars Reparation) which they had then declared, which was only. <hi>That Skinner ſhould be relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved:</hi> A ſecond untruth is; That they ſay all the matters complained of were clearly determinable in the ordinary Courts of Juſtice, excepting what concernes the Iland, whereas it appears there was likewiſe a dwelling houſe at
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152672:24"/>
               <hi>Jamby,</hi> and a Ware-houſe by the River<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, of which they diſpoſſeſſed him, which were not ſo determinable even by the report of the Judges in their Opinion (but in truth one may ſay no part of the Complaint was ſo determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable,) they ſay untruely then in ſaying there was only the Iland, that he could not be relieved in, and as untruely do they vouch the Opinion of the Judges for it, who expreſly mention the Houſe as well as the Iland. A third untruth is, to ſay the Iland was parcell of the Dominions of a Foreigne Prince, and the Right to it only determinable by the Laws of that Prince: Whereas that Prince had made an abſolute bargain and ſale, and a Totall Alienation of it from his Dominion, and ſo had put it out of the Protection of his Laws. A fourth (and which they had inſerted to be a Baite to draw on the Houſe of Commons to eſpouſe their Quarrel) is, that they ſuggeſt the complaint to be concerning Commoners onely, Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the <hi>Lord Berckley</hi> of Berckley a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Houſe of Peers is likewiſe of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152672:24"/>that Company, which intitles yet more particularly that Houſe to the Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of the whole buſineſs upon point of Priviledge, one of their Members being a party. All theſe untruths are in matter of Fact. Then for their Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence upon them, the Judgement they give againſt the Houſe of Lords, their cenſure of their Proceedings, <hi>to be againſt the Laws of the Land, and the Cuſtome of Parliament, to be unuſual and extraordinary, to be a Preſident of ill conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to all the Commons of</hi> England <hi>now and hereafter,</hi> this I hope no man will ſay to have truth in it, but to be a falſe Imputation and a Slander or (as the Lords themſelves tern it) a Scandalous Libell againſt the Houſe of Lords. And as untrue it is, what they ſay in the cloſe of their Petition, and withall moſt Injurious to the Houſe of Peers <hi>viz.</hi> That the Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners had no way of relief in this Caſe otherwiſe then by making their humble Addreſſes to the Houſe of Commons: Whereas ever ſince Parliaments have been in England, the conſtant practice
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152672:25"/>hath been, (and multitudes of Preſidents there are of it,) of Appealing to the next Parliament from any Judgment given by a former Parliament, which was grievous and unjuſt; And never in this world before was there any Appeal to the Houſe of Commons from a Judgment of the Houſe of Peers, much leſs to take a buſineſs out of their hands, or give a ſtop to their Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, before they were come to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion; Then which nothing can be a greater Violation of the Rights and Priviledges of either Houſe; Nor would the Houſe of Lords ever have endured, that any ſhould have uſed the Houſe of Commons ſo in any application unto their Lordſhips. Yet upon the examination it appeared that this Petition had been really preſented to the Houſe of Commons, and was there received.</p>
            <p>The Lords then fell upon the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the main buſineſs in queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion between Skinner and the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company, and making Reflexion upon what had been alleged on both ſides
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152672:25"/>and the proofs, gave this Judgment, <hi>That the Governour and Company ſhould pay unto</hi> Thomas Skinner, <hi>for his loſſes and damages ſuſtained, the Sum of</hi> 5000 <hi>pounds, one thouſand within two daies after the ſerving of this Judgment, two thouſand pounds in three moneths after, and two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds more in three months after that.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And they referred to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee for Priviledges to examine, who was the publiſher and diſperſer of that Scandalous Paper or Petition, which they had voted a Scandalous Libell, and to make Report thereof to the Houſe.</p>
            <p>In the diſquiſition of this buſineſs, which held many daies at the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee and in the Houſe, and where the Lords found much ſhuffling in the Perſons they examined, who were Servants and Officers to the Company, It appeared at laſt, that the Petition had really been preſented to the Houſe of Commons, and well received by that Houſe, that it had been prepared
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152672:26"/>by a Committee of the Company, that Sir <hi>Samuel Barnardiſton</hi> Deputy Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Company, Sir <hi>Andrew Riccard,</hi> Mr <hi>Rowland Winn,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Chriſtopher Boone,</hi> were of that Committee and Actors in it, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Sir <hi>Samuel Barnardiſton</hi> the moſt Active man, who gave no Satisfaction to their Lordſhips in his Anſwers, which the others did, and by their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion obtained favour, but the Lords adjudged him guilty of contriving that Scandalous Paper, and fined him 300 l. to the <hi>King,</hi> and to remain a Priſoner in the Cuſtody of the Black-Rod till he paid his Fine.</p>
            <p>And now the Houſe of Commons ownes the Cauſe, and ſeems not only to Juſtify theſe Actings of the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company, but to lay blame upon the Houſe of Lords, and paſſes certain votes to that purpoſe, which they brought up to the Lords and delivered at a Conference.</p>
            <p>And began with telling the Lords, That they had examined the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Companies Petition, and found the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legations
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152672:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>in it to be true, That ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings had been in the Houſe of Lords: And that the Lords had ſince adjudged them to pay 5000 <abbr>l</abbr> to <hi>Skinner,</hi> and that the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons thought theſe Proceedings to be of ſo very high Concernment to the Right of all His Majeſties Subjects, that they had paſſed thoſe Votes upon it.</p>
            <p>The Votes were theſe: 1. <hi>That the Houſe of Lords taking Cognizance of, and their Proceedings upon the matter ſet forth and contained in the Petition of</hi> Thomas Skinner <hi>Merchant againſt the Governour and Company of Merchants of</hi> London <hi>trading to the</hi> Eaſt-Indies, <hi>concerning the taking away of the Petitioners ſhip and goods, and aſſaulting his Perſon, and their Lordſhips over-ruling the Plea of the ſaid Governour and Company, the ſaid cauſe coming before that Houſe Originally, only upon the complaint of the ſaid</hi> Skinner, <hi>and being a common Plea, is not agreeable to the Laws of this Land, and tends to deprive the Subject of his Right, Eaſe and Benefit due to him by the ſaid Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That the Lords taking Cognizano
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:152672:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the Right and Title of the Iſland in the Petition mentioned, and giving damages thereupon againſt the ſaid Governour and Company, is not Warr anted by the ſaid Laws of this Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lords were much ſurpriſed with theſe Votes, which gave them cauſe to make a ſerious Reflection up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what had paſſed in the buſineſs of <hi>Skinner,</hi> and to take a due examination of all Circumſtances, The way that it came unto them at firſt, upon the <hi>Kings</hi> Recommendation, Their own Right to take Cognizance of, Judge and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and give redreſs in cauſes of that nature; Then the merits of this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar cauſe, A poor man oppreſſed by great Ones, very unable to conteſt with them at Law, and ſo very unlikely there to receive relief, and have any repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from them (admitting it had been in the power of the Law to have helped him, which it was not) and The manner of their Proceeding in the hearing, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining and determining of it, in which they had uſed all the moderation Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, going by ſteps and dgrees,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152672:27"/>taking firſt the Opinion of the Judges, to know if the man were relievable elſe where; who ſaid he was but in part, and not for all relievable in <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter-Hall,</hi> which made them under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take it; Then giving way to and bearing with many delayes of the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company, ſuffering the buſineſs upon ſeveral Pretences and excuſes of theirs to be put off many daies, when their Lordſhips were prepared to hear it, and had laid aſide other buſineſs for it, by which means a whole Seſſion was loſt to the poor man; And when at the next meeting of the Parliament it was heard, in which a great deal of time, and very many daies were ſpent, yet not preſently to come to a reſolution, but appoint a day for the debate of it, and when that day came, not to give a full Judgment, but only paſs a previous Vote, <hi>That ſome Relief was fit to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and take longer time to conſider What and How much, and referr it to the Conſideration of a Committee to prepare it for the Houſe; And that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152672:28"/>then, in that Interim of time, before any thing was determined, whileſt but in Agitation and under conſideration what ſhould be done, a Scandalous falſe railing Petition to be delivered to the Houſe of Commons againſt the Houſe of Peers contrary to all uſage, Right and Priviledge of Parliament, and what was expreſly forbidden 9. <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>N.</hi> 22. And this not withſtanding (not knowen upon what miſtake, for a miſtake it muſt have been) to be received with appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation by the Houſe of Commons, and ſeconded and confirmed by thoſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Votes, which were brough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> up to the Lords, and declared unto them at a Publick Conference: A<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> theſe things conſidered, made the Lord very ſenſible, who thought, if there ha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> been failings, that a gentler application had yet been more convenient; but conſcious to themſelves of none, and very confident that what they had don<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was moſt Juſtifiable by the conſtan<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> courſe and practice of their Houſe, and in it ſelf moſt Juſt and Equitable, they conceived it abſolutely neceſſary for th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:152672:28"/>Vindication of themſelves and the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting of their Rights, to paſs likewiſe two votes in Anſwer to the two of the Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>That the Houſe of Commons entertaining the Scandalous Petition of the</hi> Eaſt India <hi>Company againſt the Lords Houſe of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and their Proceedings, Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations and Votes thereupon had and made, are a Breach of the Priviledges of the Houſe of Peers, and contrary to the faire cor-reſpondency which ought to be betweene the two Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and unexampled in former times.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>That the Houſe of Peers taking Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance of the Cauſe of</hi> Thomas Skinner <hi>Merchant, a Perſon highly oppreſſed and injured in</hi> Eaſt India <hi>by the Governour and Company of Merchants of</hi> London <hi>trading thither, and over-ruling the Plea of the ſaid Company, and adjudging</hi> 5000 <abbr>
                     <hi>l</hi>
                  </abbr> 
                  <hi>damages thereupon againſt the ſaid Governour and Company, is agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Laws of the Land, and well warranted by the Law and Cuſtome of Parliament, and Juſtified by many Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Preſidents Ancient and modern.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:152672:29"/>
            <p>Two Conferences paſt between the Houſes upon this occaſion: One asked by the Houſe of Commons, the other by the Lords, and what paſt at both, the objections of the one ſide, and the others Anſwers, What was ſaid by the Commons againſt the Proceedings of the Lords, and what by the Lords to maintaine what they had done; the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of all that was ſaid on both ſides, I ſhall here ſet downe as briefly as can, as I find them entred in the Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Book of the Houſe of Lords, where they are now a Publick Record.</p>
            <p>The Gentlemen of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, that managed the Conference on their parts, endeavored to maintain their votes by ſhewing the reaſons of them.</p>
            <p>They ſaid, that Pleas being of two na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Common Pleas and Pleas of the Crown, in this Caſe they ſaid they did not meddle with any part of their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Judicature concerning Pleas on the Crown, this being of the Firſt ſort, and thoſe being of two natures Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, or Real actions, and in both all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings muſt be by the Kings Original
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152672:29"/>Writ. And this being a Caſe between Perſon and Perſon, and ſo a common Plea, ought to be proceeded in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary way by the Kings Original Wri<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: Preſidents were brought for this, vſhered in with a Preamble <hi>That where the party never pleades to the Juriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Court, it is ordinary for Courts to proceed, though in Caſes not within their Juriſdiction.</hi> The Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents cited were out of the <hi>Placita Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentaria,</hi> four in <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. time.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Preſident. 18. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>Johannes de In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſula againſt the Biſhop of</hi> Winton <hi>fol.</hi> 33. <hi>John de Inſula proſecutes for the King, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains that the Biſhop had diſpoſed of an Hoſpitall which belonged to Queen</hi> Eleenor <hi>the Kings Mother, and ejected her Tenant, the Biſhop Pleads, that he found his Church ſeiſed of that advowſon, &amp; petit Judicium</hi> ſi debeat ſine Brevi Domini Regis inde reſpondere; The Judgement is, <hi>Et quia praedictus Epiſcopus invenit Eccleſiam ſuam ſeiſitam de praedicta advocatione tempore Creationis ſuae, Ideo ipſe quoad hoc eat inde fine die ad praeſens, &amp; Dominus Rex habeat Breve verſus ipſum Epiſcopum, quod reddat
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152672:30"/>ei Advocationem &amp;c. &amp; quoad Ejectionem inquiratur veritas per Patriam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Preſident, in the ſame Parliament 18. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>The Caſe of Hugh de Louther and the Heirs of</hi> Henry de Edelynthorp, <hi>F.</hi> 43 Where it was much inſiſted upon theſe words, <hi>Nec eſt Juri conſonum vel hactenus in Curia iſta vſitatum, quod ali quis ſine Lege Communi &amp; Brevi de Cancellaria de Libero Tenemento ſuo reſpondeat, Et maxime in Caſu vbi Breve de Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellaria locum habere poteſt,</hi> There fore, <hi>dictum eſt praedicto Adae, quod ſibi perquirat per Breve de Cancellaria, ſi ſibi viderit expedire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The Caſe of</hi> William de Valentia <hi>Earl of</hi> Pembrook, Jone <hi>his</hi> Wife <hi>and</hi> Iſabell le Mareſchal 18. <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 44. Iſabell <hi>Complaines of the Earl for aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Juriſdiction in the Commote or Hundred of</hi> Eſterlow, (<hi>which is in the Kings County of</hi> Kermerdyn, <hi>and not in</hi> Pembrook-ſhire <hi>which belongs to the Earl,</hi>) <hi>and ejecting her; He pleads that he is ſeiſed of it in the Right of his Wife, and they crave Judgement, ſi ſine Brevi Domini Regis inde debent reſpondere;
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152672:30"/>The Judgment is</hi> Quia praedicti Williel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus &amp; Johanna ſunt in Seiſina de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicta Juriſdictione per diſcenſum haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditarium, &amp; non per Uſurpationem ſeu Purpreſturam, quod eant inde ſine die ad praeſens, &amp; Dominus Rex habeat Breve ſi voluerit. The Gentlemen of the Houſe of Commons obſerved upon this, <hi>That if there had been a Crime, as Uſurpation or Purpreſture, ſuch Caſes had uſually been tryed in the Lords Houſe,</hi> But then added, <hi>That if that had been the Caſe, much might be ſaid now, how the Conſtitution of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment hath been altered ſince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> 4 th. <hi>Preſident in the</hi> 18. <hi>of</hi> E. 1. F. 51. <hi>was the Caſe of</hi> Roger de Somer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton <hi>and the Prior of</hi> Buttele; Somerton <hi>followes for the King, and by Petition Complaines, that the Prior unjuſtly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held from the King the mannor of</hi> Somer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton: <hi>The Prior Anſwers, that he holds it in the Right of his Church of</hi> Buttele, &amp; petit Judicium ſi debeat inde ſine Brevi Domini Regis reſpondere; <hi>The Judgment is,</hi> Ideo praedictus Prior quoad hoc eat inde ſine die ad praeſens, &amp; Dominus Rex habeat Breve &amp;c.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152672:31"/>
               <hi>And this though the King was concerned,</hi> as was obſerved by them.</p>
            <p>By theſe Preſidents they ſaid it did appear, <hi>that in Caſes of Free-hold there is no Proceeding without an original Writ, and then neceſſarily and Demonſtratively it muſt follow; That the Lords can not Judge in theſe Caſes, for there was never any Writt Returnable</hi> Coram Dominis Spiritualibus &amp; Temporalibus, <hi>none ſuch is found in the Regiſter or</hi> Fitzher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts Natura Brevium: <hi>And the reaſon they ſaid was the ſame for Perſonal Actions, as thoſe that concern Free-hold, that</hi> Magna Charta <hi>and ſeveral Statutes made in</hi> Ed. 3. <hi>time provide for our Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all by our Peers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some other Preſidents they mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out of the Roll of Petitions anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the Parliament of 14. <hi>E</hi> 2. as that of <hi>William le Rous F.</hi> 408. Complaining of the Kings Bayliffs, who had twice diſpoſſeſſed him of a houſe in <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> and praying remedy; the anſwer was; <hi>Habeat Breve novae diſſeiſinae in ſuo caſu.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then that of the Biſhop of <hi>Winton</hi> Elect in the ſame page, Complaining
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152672:31"/>that the Kings Officers had cut down the woods of the Biſhoprick during the vacancy and praying remedy; The Anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer is, <hi>Habeat Breve de Tranſgeſs. in Canc.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next of <hi>Joane</hi> the widdow of <hi>John Fouks</hi> p. 409. by Petition Complaining of a waſt committed in the Mannor of <hi>Radewynter;</hi> The anſwer is, <hi>ſequatur ad Legem Communem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Preſident of <hi>Mariote</hi> the wife of <hi>Robert de Carle</hi> in the ſame page, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing remedy for a breach of the Peace by the Parſon of <hi>Wormele</hi> and others, the Anſwer is, <hi>Adeat Cancel. &amp; habeat ibi Breve in ſuo Caſu.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to a Petition of <hi>Robert le Sauſſer p.</hi> 410 for a debt due to him, Anſwered, <hi>habeat in Cancell. Breve de debito.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt Preſident cited was <hi>p.</hi> 411. <hi>Ralph de Draiton</hi> Parſon of <hi>Luffenham</hi> complaining againſt <hi>Robert de Vere</hi> and others for impriſoning him, till he reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his living, taking away his goods, and committing other violences, for which he had a Commiſſion of inquiry in the Country of <hi>York,</hi> and now prayed,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152672:32"/>remedy, The anſwer is, <hi>quoad Reſignationem nonpertinet ad Regem, &amp; quoad Commiſſionem habendam, oſtendat in Cancellaria primam commiſſionem &amp; ibi reſpondeatur. Et ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat ſimiliter in Cancell. Brevia de Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſionibus ſibi factis contra pacem &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this firſt part of that Conference, the Lords when they came to theirs, gave for Anſwer in the firſt place, That they could not but obſerve ſome thing unuſual in the very title of the Petition, differing from the ancient Stile of thoſe preſented to the Houſe of Commons; Then that they were much ſurpriſed, reading the Petition to find ſo many fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, and yet to heare the Gentlemen that managed for the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſay, that their Houſe had exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it, and found all the Allegations in it to be true; Whereas in truth there were in it almoſt as many Falſhoods as Lines; thoſe Falſhoods have been mentioned before, ſo as it is not need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full again to repeat them. The Lords took notice after, of the unuſual Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of the Houſe of Commons, to take Cognizance of any matter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:152672:32"/>in their Houſe, before their Lordſhips had given any Judgment therein, or communicated the ſame unto them; And to examine, proceed upon, and cenſure by vote the Proceeding of the Houſe of Peers, which they ſaid the Houſe of Commons could not Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally do, becauſe they were not a Court of Judicature in any caſe, much leſs of the Houſe of Peers, which is the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Iudicature: And that in truth they had not means to come to the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth, whereby to found a Right Judgment, becauſe they have not power to give an Oath; Nor in this particular had they heard any more then one ſide, having not heard <hi>Skinner</hi> at all: Nor yet had they conferred with the Lords, by which meanes they might have come to the knowledge of the grounds and reaſons, upon which their Lordſhips had proceeded; So as the Lords could not but wonder at this Judgement, which had been paſt upon them.</p>
            <p>Then they came to that Aſſertion concerning Common Pleas, <hi>That they
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:152672:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>muſt be proceeded in by the Kings Original writ, and conſequently not before the Lords,</hi> for which the Houſe of Commons brought ſome Preſidents, to prove that <hi>Free-holds were never examined in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment but alwaies left to the remedy at Law;</hi> And in the next place the Lords took into Conſideration how they began their Preſidents with this Preamble; <hi>That where the party never Pleads to the Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of the Court, it is ordinary for Courts to proceed though in Caſes not within their Juriſdiction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which the Lords ſaid in the firſt place, as to the Aſſertion viz. <hi>That all Common Pleas muſt be proceeded in by Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Writ and Conſequently not before the Lords,</hi> That it was as eaſy for them to aſſert the contrary, and upon better grounds; Being able to ſhew Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents all along from the firſt and the moſt ancient Records we have, down to the lateſt and moſt moderne ones of the Proceedings of Parliaments, even within the memory and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of every yong man, that the Houſe of Peers have ſtill exerciſed
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:152672:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>this Juriſdiction, even in particular Caſes of <hi>Meum &amp; Tuum,</hi> between man and man, when they have thought good, (though that but rarely) and when moved to it by ſome thing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary in the Caſe; and that no Houſe of Peers hath done it leſs, and been more tender of entertaining ſuch buſineſſes, and more unwilling to be troubled with them, then this preſent Houſe of Peers, upon which ſo much blame is laid, and which is the only Houſe of Peers that ever Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Perſons (found guilty and cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by it for foul Oppreſſions) did preſume in that manner to accuſe and impeach to any Court or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel or Company of men, no not to the King himſelf; Or that ever were cenſured, and ſuch votes paſſed upon before. But we ſhall hereafter in its due place examine the matter of this Aſſertion, and ſhall ſhew that it holds not true even in the ordinary Courts of <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> whither of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, or Equity, where Caſes of mens Free-holds are tryed every day
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:152672:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>without any original Writt, and much leſs in Parliament. In the mean time we will take things in order as they were delivered.</p>
            <p>And to the Preamble which uſherd in the Preſidents, <hi>That where the Party never pleads to the Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, it is ordinary for Courts to proceed, though in Caſes not within their Iuriſdiction,</hi> upon which the Inference muſt be, that Preſidents then ſignify nothing to prove a Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction though never ſo many, though a conſtant Series of them in all times be made appear, except there be ſtill a pleading to the Juriſdiction, and that Plea overruled; The Lords thought this a ſtrange Argumentation, and took the force of the Argument to lye rather the other way, That it is a clearer Proofe of a Juriſdiction, to have it never or ſeldome queſtioned, and be ſtill exerciſed and ſubmitted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, then if it be ſome times oppoſed, though it be made good and maintained againſt that Oppoſition: And they thought, that in this particular Caſe,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:152672:34"/>they had good Warrant for their Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, finding it ſo ſeldome op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, even by the Houſe of Commons own ſhewing, who could bring but four Preſidents, where any had pleaded to their Juriſdiction, and the Plea ſeemingly admitted, (for it is but ſeemingly, as will be ſhewed upon the Examination of the Preſidents them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves:) Whereas multitudes were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced of the exerciſe of their Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, and ſome, Where the parties had deſired a try all at common Law, and the Lords would not grant it, as that of <hi>William Paynell</hi> and <hi>Margaret</hi> his Wife in the <hi>Placita Parliamentaria</hi> of the 30 of <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 231. The Caſe was this; Margaret <hi>had been formerly the Wife of</hi> John Cameys, <hi>and he yet living bad left him, (as ſhe alledged) with his conſent, and lived with</hi> Paynell <hi>as his Wife, and was married to him:</hi> Cameys <hi>dying,</hi> Paynell <hi>and ſhe ſue for the Thirds of the Mannor of</hi> Torpell <hi>which had been the Land of</hi> Cameys. <hi>It was objected on the other ſide, That ſhe lived in Adultery with</hi> Paynell <hi>in</hi> Cameys <hi>life time, and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:152672:35"/>ſo had forfeited her Dower. They upon that deſire to be tryed by their Country, if Adultery or no; What ſay the Houſe of Peers? Do they ſend them into the Country as is deſired? No,</hi> Videtur Curiae quod non eſt neceſſe contra tantas tamque mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtas Evidentias, Praeſumptiones, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bationes &amp;c. ad aliquam Inquiſitionem Patriae Capiendam procedere &amp;c. Et ideo conſideratum eſt quod prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicti Willielmus &amp; Margareta nihil Capiant per Petitionem ſuam, ſed ſint in Miſericordia pro falſo Clamore &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This ſhewes that the Lords ſome times would retain Cauſes, though ſometimes they did diſmiſſe them, not for want of Juriſdiction, but as it ſeemed to them convenient, and their Occaſions would give leave, &amp; as they had or had not leaſure for it from the greater Affaires of the Kingdome, or that ſome Circumſtances in the merits of a Cauſemade it more or leſs worthy of their Conſideration. As if one of the parties was powerfull in his Country, and ſuſpected to have an Influence
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:152672:35"/>upon the Juries, the Lords would then ſome times retain a buſineſs, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine it themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As in</hi> 3 <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>N.</hi> 24. <hi>The Caſe of</hi> John <hi>Earl of</hi> Pembro<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k <hi>and</hi> William le Zouch <hi>Complaining that they were ſued for certain Lands in</hi> York-ſhire <hi>by</hi> Thomas <hi>the Sonne of Sir</hi> Robert Roos of Ingmanthorp, <hi>and alledge, That the ſaid</hi> Thomas <hi>ſought to come to a tryall in the Country, which he had gained and corrupted. And therefore pray for redreſs, and a tryall by Parliament, giving this reaſon for it,</hi> Que Ils par tels Malveis Compaſſemens, et Procuremens en pais ne ſoient deſheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tez. <hi>That they may not loſe their inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance by ſuch wicked contrivances and practiſes in the Country.</hi> Do the Lords then ſuffer it to go on to tryall in the Country? No, They take the matter into their own hands, appoint <hi>John Knevet,</hi> and <hi>John Cavendiſh</hi> Chief Juſtice, and <hi>John Belknap</hi> Chief Juſtice of the Common Pleas to examine it and make Report to them, which they did.</p>
            <p>And ſo likewiſe in the Caſe of <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyngdon</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:152672:36"/>and <hi>Courtney</hi> 4 <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>N.</hi> 21. Sir Phillip Courtney <hi>a great man in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try oppreſſes</hi> Pontyngdon, <hi>diſpoſſeſſes him of his Land by force, he comes to the Lords,</hi> praies Pur Dieu Et en oeuure de Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite d'ordeigner remedies en cell Cas; <hi>For Gods ſake and as a work of charity that they would give remedy in this caſe. Setts forth in his Petition, that he had before in a Parliament held at</hi> Wincheſter <hi>made his complaint, at which time Sir</hi> Phillip <hi>laid the Baſtardy of his Father as a Barr, and that the Lords Anſwer then was, That he ſhould have right done him, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the buſineſs to the Arch-Biſhop of</hi> Canterbury <hi>to take care of it; That before the Arch-Biſhop, Sir</hi> Phillip <hi>and he agreed to go to a tryall upon that Iſſue, and that there ſhould be a ſufficient Jury of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Knights and Eſquires of the Country, But that Sir</hi> Phillip <hi>had named ſome of thoſe principal men, and withall poor men of leſs ſufficiency, to the intent, that the great men making default, the poor ſhould ſtand, and that theſe poor men durſt not againſt Sir</hi> Phillip, <hi>maintain the truth</hi> (les queux poures hommes n'oiſent
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:152672:36"/>envers le dit Sir <hi>Phillip</hi> la verite dire) <hi>That thereupon he Petitioned again the Lords in the next Parliament ſitting at</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>and informed them of all theſe Particulars, whereupon they Ordered a Writ to go to the Judges of Aſſize of that Country, commanding them to admit none to be of the Jury, but ſuch as had</hi> 40 <abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> 
               <hi>a year Land, and thoſe to be choſen out of the whole Country notwithſtanding any uſage or Challenge to the Contrary; But that now Sir</hi> Phillip <hi>finding that the charge of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtardy would not hold, contriving ſtill the wrongful diſinheriſon of the Petitioner, had ſtarted a releaſe unduely gotten from one</hi> Thomas Pontyngdon <hi>a Parſon, whoſe heirethe Petitioner is, And the Petitioner is thereby like to be ruined</hi> ſi il neit voſtre tres Hautiſſime et tres excellent ſecours et aide) <hi>if the Lords would not afford him their moſt High and excellent ſuccour and help.</hi> This was the effect of the Petition. <hi>The Lords upon this make an Order to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the tryall, the Point in Iſſue to be the Baſtardy, that the Releaſe ſhould be laid aſide as null and void, that if the Baſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy be proved,</hi> Pontyngdon <hi>ſhall be for ever
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:152672:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>barred to ſue hereafter, and if not proved, but that his Father was Mulier, he ſhould then recover the Land with Coſts and da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages; And they further Order a Writ to the Sheriff to Impannell none of the Jury, that had not</hi> 40 <abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> 
               <hi>per annum Land.</hi> So then three ſeveral times, in three ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Parliaments did the Lords take Cognizance of this Cauſe, being a Common Plea for a mans Free-hold, and that Originally in the firſt Inſtance, not upon an appeal, or Writ of Error, or any of thoſe waies to which the Houſe of Commons would now limit them; They direct the tryall, the Iſſue, the Condition and Qualification of the Jury, and the Judgment: and if this be not taking Cognizance of a Cauſe, I know not what is: And well was it for that poor Gentleman, That the Lords had that Juriſdiction, that they could take Cognizance of his Cauſe, to give him relief then: As now it was well for <hi>Skinner,</hi> That the Lords took Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance of his: Otherwiſe this power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Company had trampled him in the dirt and ruined him, as that violent
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:152672:37"/>man Sir <hi>Phillip Courtney</hi> (for ſo he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to have been by ſeveral Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints againſt him in the Parliaments of thoſe times) had ſerved <hi>Pontyngdon:</hi> And well will it ſtill be for many a poor man to have ſuch an Aſylum, ſuch a City of refuge to fly unto, to ſave himſelf from the violence and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of power and greatneſs. And perhaps ſome of thoſe who now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to lay low the Houſe of Peers, who would make it to be of no ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, to have no power, no Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon the Kingdome, be as ſalt that hath loſt its Savor, only <hi>Magni Nominis Umbra,</hi> a Name of Peerage without ability to help themſelves or any body elſe; perhaps I ſay, even ſome of them, ſhould they prevail now, may hereafter repent it, and wiſh they had not remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved an Ancient Land Mark, which heretofore was in Veneration, and looked upon, as that which bounds both power and Liberty, and is a guard to both by keeping both with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their due limits, and hath ever been held moſt neceſſary to the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:152672:38"/>the Government of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome for the Preſervation of it, and as ſervicable to Monarchy for the keeping up of Regal Dignity and Authority, as uſefull to the ſubject for the maintaining of his juſt Liberty and Freedome.</p>
            <p>But let us go on with the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and ſee what was ſaid by the Lords to the Preſidents cited by the Commons.</p>
            <p>To the firſt of <hi>John de Inſula</hi> againſt the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> the Lords ſaid, it was no diſmiſſion of the Biſhop for want of Juriſdiction, for then it would not have been ſaid, <hi>Eat inde ad praeſens,</hi> but rather <hi>ad perpetuum;</hi> This is but a Temporary diſmiſſion, no more but as if they had ſaid, Well, the Biſhop ſaith, he was ſeiſed of that advowſon in Right of his Church; Let the King (for whom <hi>John de Inſula</hi> proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes) take his Writ out of the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery, and try for that; And for the Ejection Complained of, let that be tryed by a Jury of the Country, and ſee if things can be ſo ended; If not, come
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:152672:38"/>again then, and we will hear you; But for the Preſent we diſmiſs you. So the Lords concluded, That this Preſident made nothing againſt their Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</p>
            <p>To the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> of <hi>Hugh de Louther</hi> and the Heire of <hi>Edelyngthorp,</hi> upon which the Commons did ſo much inſiſt, and particularly upon the expreſſion, <hi>Nec eſt Juri Conſonum, nec hactenus in iſta Curia uſitatum &amp;c.</hi> The Lords ſaid, That neither this Preſident well exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined would make much againſt them; For that <hi>Adam</hi> concerning whom and upon whoſe occaſion that was ſaid, was not at all before the Lords, as a Partie in the Cauſe before them, but came in of himſelf, unſent for, unlooked for, layes in a claime which the Lords of that Parliament had not heard of before, nor did at all then queſtion; So as it cannot be ſaid that there was any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of him or of his buſineſs; But the Lords ſay, Let him purſue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover his Land by a Writ out of the Chancery if he will, and that he ſees it convenient for him <hi>(ſi ſibi Viderit ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedire)</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:152672:39"/>and they go on to determine the buſineſs, which was before them; The Caſe was thus, <hi>Thomas de Normanvil an Eſcheator had order concerning</hi> Hugh de Louther <hi>for certain Lands then in his Poſſeſſion which had been ſeiſed into the Kings hands, as held of him in Capite formerly by</hi> Henry de Edelyngthorp, <hi>to whom one</hi> Eſton <hi>had granted them and to the Heirs of his body lawfully begotten, and having none to returne to</hi> Eſton, <hi>under whom now</hi> Louther <hi>claimed. The order was, That</hi> Louther <hi>ſhould give Pledge to come and Anſwer at that Parliament for the profits of thoſe Lands to the King:</hi> Louther <hi>comes as he was bound, and at the ſame time one</hi> Adam <hi>comes alſo, pretends him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be Son and Heire to</hi> Edelyngthorp, <hi>and demands the Land,</hi> Louther <hi>ſaid, he is a Baſtard, and the Lands belong not to him: And the Lords they ſay, they have nothing to do with him, let him ſue for his Land where he thinks beſt, and ſo ſend him away, But</hi> Louther <hi>they adjudge to do his homage, and to be Anſwerable to the King for the Rent; And for the Title of the Land, What do they? do they let it alone,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:152672:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>and meddle no more with it, as a thing not at all within their Cognizance or Juriſdistion? Nothing leſs; They Command the Eſcheator</hi> Normanvil <hi>to make enquiry upon Oath; if</hi> Edelyngthorp <hi>had any Heire lawfully begotten, who he was, and upon what Title he claimed, and to give on account of it at the next Parliament,</hi> Ita quod idem Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caetor ad proximum Parlamentum poſt Feſtum Sancti Michaelis Domino Regi diſtinctè et apertè inde reſpondeat. <hi>So as the Lords then were farr from thinking they muſt not meddle with ſuch things:</hi> And for that expreſſion of <hi>Non eſt conſonum &amp;c.</hi> rendred as the ground of that Judgment of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; Firſt it is anſwered, it was no Judgment at all, not only of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, for <hi>Adam</hi> was no party in the Cauſe; Then it is no part of the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if there were a Judgment, but precedes it; The Judgment ſuch as it is, or rather the Anſwer to <hi>Adams</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, followes in theſe words, <hi>Dictum eſt praedicto Adae quod ſibi perquirat per Breve de Cancellaria ſi ſibi viderit expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dire,</hi> So as the preceding words, may
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:152672:40"/>perhaps have been but inſerted by the Clerk that entred the Order; But take it at the ſtrongeſt, Admit that the Lords then preſent in the Houſe had inſerted thoſe words, as their ſence at that time, Is that binding to the Houſe, that it may not be of an other opinion at an other time? In that very Parliament of 18 <hi>E.</hi> 1. How many times have they been of an other mind? How many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples are there of Particular Cauſes Judged and determined by them? And ſhall one Swallow make a Summer, one ſingle Preſident overballance multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of Preſidents to the Contrary?.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place it was ſaid, That this Preſident did not <hi>Quadrare,</hi> ſure with this preſent Caſe of <hi>Skinners,</hi> fort at was meerely concerning a <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berum Tenementum</hi> and within the Realm where the Law had free Courſe, here is Rapine, Oppreſſion, Spoiling of goods, diſpoſſeſſing one of an Iſland in Fortein parts, <hi>extra poteſtatem Legis,</hi> aſſaulting the Perſon of a fellow Subject, a violent Interruption of the trade and commerce of the Nation; Which concernes the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:152672:40"/>Government of the Kingdome, is a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of State, and highly entrenches upon the Authority of the King, which will ſuffer much, if he ſuffer one ſubject to exerciſe a Tyrannicall Dominion over an other, though in an other Country: And is againſt the profit of the King, which is much concerned, That no violence be uſed in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of trade, to bring a Scandal upon the Nation, make it ſtinke in Forrein parts, that none will have to do with us, which muſt needs become the ruine of our trade and ſo of all His Cuſtomes.</p>
            <p>If one Merchant do that which is prejudicial to an other, or to a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, let them Complain of him to the King, who will command him home and puniſh him: And if he will not come (for that may be objected) being ſo farr off, out of reach, then the King will give them leave that are wronged and grieved by him to right them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. But that they ſhould do it of themſelves and in their own Caſe be Judges, Witneſſes and Executioners,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:152672:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>againſt all reaſon and Juſtice. So the Lords were not at all convinced with this Preſident neither, but ſtill thought, they had done very well in Cenſuring the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company for their Miſdemeanors and wrongs done to <hi>Skinner,</hi> and in adjudging them to give <hi>Skinner</hi> Reparation for it.</p>
            <p>The 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Preſident was that of <hi>william de Valentia</hi> and <hi>Iſabell de Mareſchal,</hi> in which the Lords obſerved the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to have been only <hi>ad proeſens;</hi> But withall obſerved, that the bare rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Caſe in the Book will ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy one of the Juriſdiction of the Peers, to retaine ſuch Cauſes: It ſayes, <hi>That William de Valentia had at the fore going Parliament been</hi> Ad querelas Iſabellae le Mareſchall allocutus et ad rationem poſitus, <hi>impleaded and put to Anſwer, by what right he aſſumed ſuch an Office and ſuch Power in the Hundred of Hoſterelegh, and that he then alleged he did it in the Right of his Wife, and that it being his Wifes Inheritance he ought not to be put to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere without her,</hi> Ita quod datus fuit dies ei ad hunc diem ad Parlamentum
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:152672:41"/>Domini Regis <hi>viz.</hi> a die Paſchae in ires Septimanas. <hi>And then his Wife and he appeared by their Atturney, and after pleadings, The Judgment is,</hi> Quia prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicti Willielmus Et Johanna ſunt in ſeiſina de praedicta Juriſdictione et de Haeredicate ipſius Johannae per deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſum haereditarium et non per Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pationem ſeu Purpreſturam &amp;c. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideratum eſt, quod eant inde ſine die quoad praeſens; Et Dominus Rex ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat Breve ſi voluerit &amp;c. The Lords knew they had Juriſdiction, elſe they would have diſmiſſed the Cauſe the Parliament before, and not have adjour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it to the next Parliament upon that ground to make the Wife a Party, as we ſee they did: And whereas the Commons had upon this Preſident ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that if there had been Crime in the Caſe, as Uſurpation or Purpreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, then they acknowledged that in ſuch Caſes the Houſe of Lords did uſually proceed and try them, but withall added, That if that were the queſtion, much might be ſaid how the Conſtitution of Government hath been
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:152672:42"/>ſince altered: So as they ſoon retracted their admittance of but ſo much of the Lords Right, and what they had given with their right hand, they would ſoon take again with their left.</p>
            <p>But firſt, for their Conceſſion of Judging Crime, the Lords ſay, that ſuffices for their Jndemnity, as to what they have done in this particular Caſe of the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company and <hi>Skinner,</hi> for here is Crime ſufficient, and Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation and Purpreſture, taking them in the larger ſence for invading any other mans Right, and not only where the King is concerned, as thoſe termes are taken ſome times: And then for the Qualification of their Gift upon the Change and alteration of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, The Lords Anſwer, That when they ſhew the Time, when that altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was made, and the Perſons by whom, and the Manner how (if Legally done) they ſhal then believe &amp; ſubmit, and not till then: But they never heard of any thing, that till now ſo much as looked that way, except that Vote of the Aſſembly called the Rump, <hi>which
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:152672:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>declared the Houſe of Lords uſeleſs and dangerous and therefore to be aboliſhed and taken away;</hi> and by a Clubb Law they did take it away. But even they that paſſed that Vote, and did make that Clubb Law, thought the Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature neceſſary and fit to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, for they immediatly aſſumed it to themſelves, and fairely voted themſelves into that Power by the Name of the Commons of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, the very ſame Title that the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company do now make uſe of in their Petition to the Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>To the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Roger de Somerion</hi> proſecuting for the King, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of the Prior of Buttele, for unjuſtly withholding from the King the mannor of Somerton; And the Judgment upon it, <hi>Ideo praedictus</hi> Priot <hi>quo ad hoc eat inde ſine die ad praeſens:</hi> The Lords ſay, it is but a Temporary diſmiſſion as the others were, and ſignifies nothing as to the point of Juriſdiction: And they wiſh
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:152672:43"/>the Commons would have pleaſed to caſt their eye upon the enſuing Caſe in the ſame leafe, of <hi>William de Valentia</hi> again, and of him upon the ſame occaſion (concerning his Wifes Inheritance as formerly,) where there is not a Diſmiſſion of the Cauſe as formerly, but a determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, and that determination again referred unto and confirmed by a ſuceeding Parliament, to ſhew that the Houſe of Lords ſometimes would, and ſometimes would not Judge and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine ſuch cauſes as were brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them: That Caſe was thus, <hi>William de Valentia Complaines of the Lords of the Counſel for admitting, during the Kings ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence beyond the Seas, one</hi> Dioniſia <hi>a preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Daughter of</hi> William de Monte Caniſo <hi>Tenant to the King of Lands held in Capite and formerly enjoyed by her Father in his life time, Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as his Wife was true Heire to that</hi> William, <hi>and the Land belonging to her; The Lords of the Councel juſtifie what they have done, ſay that</hi> Dioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia <hi>was notoriouſly known to be the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:152672:43"/>true Daughter of that</hi> William, <hi>and that the Biſhop of</hi> Wincheſter, <hi>in whoſe Dioceſs ſhe was born, teſtified it,</hi> The Judgment is, <hi>Ideo videtur domino Regi quod praedictus Comes, Theſaurar. &amp; Alij de Conſilio bene et rité proceſſerunt</hi> It is not now <hi>ſibi perquirat per Breve de Cancel.</hi> They do not referr him to the Chancery, as they did in the other Caſe. This was in 18 <hi>E.</hi> 1. In 20 <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 103. he comes again to Parliament, and renues his Complaint, and that Judgment given before is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed; the words are theſe, <hi>et de alijs Petitionibus ſuis viz. De hoereditate</hi> Willielmi de Monte Caniſo <hi>petenda, et etiam quod procedatur juxta Bullam quam jidem</hi> Williemus <hi>et</hi> Johanna <hi>impetrarunt ad inficiendum Proceſſum, perquod</hi> Dioniſia <hi>filia proedicti</hi> Willielmi <hi>Legitima cenſeba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, alias eis reſponſum fuit viz. in Parliamento poſt Natale Domini Anno</hi> 18. <hi>ut patet in Rotulis ejuſdem Parliamenti, Ad quam Reſponſionem ſe teneant &amp;c.</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be clearer then the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual practice of this Juriſdiction in the Houſe of Lords, whenſoever they pleaſed.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:152672:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>Not that it hath alwaies pleaſed them to trouble themſelves with exerciſing this Juriſdiction, their time having been ſo taken up ſome times with buſineſſes of a higher Nature, that they could not attend it, ſo as many times they have tyed up themſelvesby an Order of the Houſe, not to receive any private buſineſs: As in the Cloſe Roll 18 <hi>E.</hi> 1. There is a memorable Order to that purpoſe; I will ſet it down at length in the very words, which are theſe, <hi>Pur ces Ke la gent Ke venent al Parle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment le Roy ſunt ſovent deſtaez et deſtour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bez a grant grevance de eux e de la Curt par la multitudine des Peticions Ke ſunt botez devant le Roy, de quevx le plus porreient eſtre eſpleytez par Chanceler et par Juſtices, purveu eſt, Ke tutes les Petitions Ke tuchent le ſel vegnent primes al Chanceler, e ceux Ke tuchent Juſtices v ley veynent a Juſtices, e ceux Ke tuchent Juerie veynent a Juſtices de le Juerie. Et ſi les beſoings ſeent ſi grans v ſi de graces, Ke le Chanceler e ces autres ne le puſſent fere ſans le Rey, dunk Ils les porterunt par lur meins
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:152672:44"/>de meine devant le Roy pur ſaver ent ſa volentè. Enſique nulle Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion ne veigne devant le Roy e ſon Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeil fors par les majns des avaunt ditz Chanceler e les autres Chef Miniſtres. Enſike le Rey e ſun Conſail puſſent Sanz charge de autre buſoignes entendre a groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes buſoignes de ſun Reaume e de ſes Forei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Terres.</hi> Thus in Engliſh, <hi>In regard the People who come to the Kings Parliament, are oft delayed and diſturbed to the great grievance of themſelves and of the Court, by the multitude of Petitions exhibited before the King, of which moſt could be diſpatched by the Chancellor and Juſtices; It is provided, That all Petitions, that concerne the Seal ſhall come firſt to the Chancellor, and thoſe that concerne the Exchequer to the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, and thoſe that concerne the Juſtices or the Law ſhall come to the Juſtices, and thoſe that concerne the Jewes to the Juſtices appointed for the Jewes; And if the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes be ſo great, or ſo of Grace, as the Chancellor and the reſt can not end them without the King, then they ſhall with their own hands bring them before the King to know his pleaſure therein; So as no Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:152672:45"/>ſhall come to the King and his Counſel, but brought by the Chancellor and thoſe Chiefe Miniſters: that ſo the King and his Counſel may without the trouble of other bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines attend the great buſineſſes of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and of his forrein Dominions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the Order, in which two rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are expreſſed, for their not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving particular Petitions, one in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning the other in the end, Firſt the eaſe of the Petitioners, and of the Houſe it ſelf, which for their multitudes could not give every one his diſpatch; and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that freed of them it might at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Publick buſineſs of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; Not for want of Juriſdiction. And yet be all manner of buſineſſes ſo put by? No! Great ones, and ſuch as need grace and favor are ſtill reſerved: But take it at the ſtrongeſt, admit they had put all out of their own power, yet it will be granted, they had power, till they did in this manner diveſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of it; It appears they had by the Order it ſelf, which mentions ſuch multitudes of Petitions; I then aske, if ſuch reſolution of the Houſe at that
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:152672:45"/>time could be binding to perpetuity? The Houſes of Parliament we know are maſters of their own Orders, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves when they pleaſe alter the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders they have made; much leſs then be they binding to ſucceeding Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And it is obvious to every man, who will either look into the Records of Ancient Parliaments or will but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collect his Memory and call to mind what hath paſſed in our late Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that in all times the Houſe of Peers hath acted contrary to this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; Taking Cognizanceeven of ſmaller matters, which the ordinary Courts of Juſtice do every day diſpatch: And no Houſe of Peers did ever do it leſs then this, which in truth hath not done it at all, though it be now ſo quarrelled with for having relieved one poor man from the oppreſſion of the mighty, when no inferior Court could do it: And this too the only Cauſe of this Nature, that they have medled with during this whole Parliament, which hath laſted ſo many years, and hath had ſo many Seſſions; And a Cauſe particularly
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:152672:46"/>recommended unto them by the King (who is the Fountaine of all Juſtice;) not one taken up by themſelves, which makes not their Caſe the worſe, as it may well be hoped.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe there had been no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation at all in that Order of 8 <hi>E.</hi> 1. of any Cauſe or any buſineſs, but that the King and Lords had at that time bound up themſelves abſolutely from medling with any of thoſe Petitioners Caſes, and for the Preſent waved the exerciſe of their Juriſdiction in all ſuch matters, had this been a Renouncing of their Juriſdiction and quitting it for ever? No Court but may upon ſome particular occaſion ſuſpende and wave it's Juriſdiction, it doth not therefore follow that it muſt never make uſe of it again. The Court of Chancery doth ſometimes appoint a Tryall at Law of points in a Cauſe, which it might have determined it ſelf, if it had pleaſed: And at an other time it will determine things of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, The Houſe of Peers may do the ſame and wave their Juriſdiction when
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:152672:46"/>they pleaſe. It did it 13 <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>N.</hi> 10. <hi>in Changeours</hi> Caſe. Adam Changeour (<hi>So is his Name in the Record though the Exact Abridgement call him</hi> John) <hi>peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions the King and Lords againſt Sir</hi> Robert Knolls, <hi>Setts forth, how owing</hi> 2000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l</hi>
               </abbr> 
               <hi>to Sir</hi> Robert <hi>and his Wife</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, <hi>he had let him have Lands to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Rent till he was Satisfied his debt; That Sir</hi> Robert <hi>had received more then his money due, yet kept the Land, ſo prayes remedy.</hi> The Anſwer is indorſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Petition, <hi>Let a Writ be directed to Sir</hi> Robert Knolls <hi>to appear in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Friday after</hi> Candlemas <hi>next, to Anſwer the things contained in the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition. Upon hearing the buſineſs the Lords leave it to be tryed at the Common Law.</hi> This ſeemes a ſtronger Preſident for trying all at Law and not in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then any which the Gentlemen of the Houſe of Commons urged at the Conference; For here was an abſolute diſmiſſion of the Cauſe, and not <hi>ad prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens</hi> only, as was in their Preſidents. But I believe ſuch wiſe and knowing men could not but ſee, that this Preſident
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:152672:47"/>would not ſo much have helpt one way, as done prejudice to their Caſe an other way. The Prejudice, it would have done, had been this, that them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by their own ſhewing had over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown one of their maine Arguments, which was, That all Proceedings in caſes of Freehold ſhould be by the Kings Writ, and that no Writ was ever made Returnble <hi>Coram Dominis Spiritualibus et Temporalibus;</hi> Whereas here had been in their own Preſident mention of a Writ returnable in Parliament, which is <hi>Tant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amount,</hi> and ſignifies the ſame thing: But I have in this Diſcourſe given Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of ſeveral others in the ſame kind, where Writs are iſſued by Order of Parliament returnable in Parliament: and many more there are, if it were neceſſary and worth the trouble to ſet them down. And then, what had they gotten by telling us, That the Lords once would not retaine a Cauſe, which was tryable at Law, and would for once wave their Juriſdiction in ſuch Matters? When it was ſhewed to them by multitudes of Preſidents,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:152672:47"/>That the Lords had moſt frequently done otherwiſe at other times in Caſes of the ſame Nature.</p>
            <p>And Preſidents in the Affirmative are thoſe that prove a juriſdiction, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially when many in number are produced, and ſome of all times and in every Kings Reign (of which the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords can be had,) which ſhewes a Continuance of, and ſo an unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Right to ſuch a power. One, or two, or twenty then in the Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive (that the Lords did not do ſo in ſuch and ſuch Caſes) Nay I ſay more, were the Number equall, as many in the Negative as in the Affirmative, yet it could not diſprove their Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction; It would only ſhew, that their Lordſhips were free Agents, to do it, or not do it, as they ſaw Cauſe; But their Juriſdict on remained ſtill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure to do it, whenſoever they would.</p>
            <p>And when all is done, I may ſay, all this is <hi>Nihil ad rem,</hi> and concernes not the point in queſtion, which is, If the Lords have done well or ill in relieving <hi>Skinner</hi> againſt the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:152672:48"/>Company, for he was not relievable a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Common Law (as hath been ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed:) And if he had not been relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, there had been a failer of Juſtice: So as there was a neceſſity of their Lordſhips acting in that particular, to keep up the publick Juſtice of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. And all Preſidents, and all that can be ſaid and urged, to ſhew that the Houſe of Peers ought not to meddle with matters determinable at Law, are in truth out of doors, and can not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne this Houſe of Peers, which never did it, but the contrary; For whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it appeared, that any buſineſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them was proper to be tryed at Law, they preſently diſmiſſed it: Yet ſince their Right is queſtioned, they muſt defend it, though they gave no Occaſion for it, having not at all put that Right in execution, nor (as it may well be preſumed by their proceeding hereto) ever intending it.</p>
            <p>As to the 6 other Preſidents, o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Petitions Anſwered in the Parliament of the 14 of <hi>E.</hi> 2. which the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Houſe of Commons them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:152672:48"/>ſeemed not to lay ſo much weight upon; The Lords thought they did wiſely in it, for they were not ſuch as would bear weight to build upon; The Lords of that Parliament, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſeveral natures of the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes Petitioned for, diſmiſſed the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners with ſeveral directions; Which ſhewes they took Cognizance of thoſe matters; One was directed to take out his Writ <hi>novaediſſeiſinae;</hi> and an other to bring his action of Treſpaſs; the third they ſend to the Common Law; the fourth into the Chancery; the fifth they Order to bring his action of debt; the ſixth who complained of ſeveral things, to him they gave particular Anſwers, and particular Directions to every point; One of which (they ſaid) pertained not to the King, that is, to his Laws, ſo they could give no Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in it; it was concerning the Reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of a living, which was to be tryed by the Laws of the Church; For the other points, they diſpoſed them into their proper Channells. Was this to be done by a Court, that had
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:152672:49"/>no Juriſdiction in theſe matters? No rational man can think ſo.</p>
            <p>But it would be conſidered, that in this Caſe of <hi>Skinners</hi> the Lords could give none of thoſe Anſwers, neither <hi>ſibi perquir at per Breve de Cancellaria</hi> not <hi>Sequatur ad Legem Communem,</hi> or tobring this or the other Action. For neither Law nor Equity in the Ordinary way of the Inferior Courts could relieve him for the loſs of his real Eſtate in the <hi>Indies:</hi> the Judges ſaid, he was not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievable for his Houſe and Iſland: So as none of thoſe Preſidents are applicable to the point in queſtion. Not that the Law, even in the ordinary execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, provides not for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all Crimes: It declares againſt and condemns the Fact, but can not reach the perſon to puniſh him, when he hath committed that Fact in a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein Country, <hi>Ubi lex Angliae non currit.</hi> And the Houſe of Peers hath but helpt the Law to inflict ſuch pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment upon Offenders, as by the Law was due to them, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they had eſcaped. And were it
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:152672:49"/>but this, it ſufficiently juſtifies the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the Lords in that particular Caſe. Then as to the Juriſdiction of that Houſe in the generall it will be made as apparent as the Sun at Noone, how they have in all times exerciſed it to the relief of all perſons, who ſtood in need of their relief, even for things done within the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Where the Law had provided a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, they applyed it; Some times themſelves would take the pains, in Caſes that deſerved it, where there was ſome thing extraordinary to move them to it, and when they were at lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure from the more weighty and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Affaires of the Kingdom, Some times they would ſend it down to the Inferior Courts to do it for them, and give them Authority for it, (which they could not have done, if they had not had it themſelves, for <hi>Nemo dat id quod non habet</hi>) as in the Caſe of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Rioters 11 <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>N.</hi> 38. in the Exact Abridgement, <hi>Whom they turned over to the Kings Bench, and gave thoſe Judges Authority to the end the buſines.</hi>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:152672:50"/>where the Law had not provided, there they would not meddle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and declared it ſo, That none elſe neither ſhould preſume to meddle: As upon the Petition of <hi>Martin Chamberlain</hi> in that 14 <hi>E.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 409. <hi>Who upon the ſuppreſſion of the Knights</hi> Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers <hi>deſired to be put into the poſſeſſion of a mannor, which the</hi> Templers <hi>(whileſt they ſtood) had held of him,</hi> The Anſwer is, <hi>Quod non eſt Lex ordinata, there was no Law ordained in the Caſe;</hi> And becauſe the Law had not determined, how thoſe Lands ſhould be diſpoſed of, the Lords would ſay nothing to it.</p>
            <p>But will it not be ſaid, that this makes good what the Commons ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, againſt the Lords retaining this Cauſe of <hi>Skinners,</hi> becauſe ſome parts of it were not determinable in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall;</hi> Whereas, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no Law concerning thoſe points, till there had been one made, their Lordſhips ſhould not have meddled with them? As the Lords in that Parliament of <hi>E.</hi> 2. would do nothing
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:152672:50"/>in <hi>Chamberlains</hi> Caſe, becauſe the Law had not provided for it; And as in thoſe two Caſes mentioned by the Houſe of Commons, <hi>That of an Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix Forfeiting by her husbands default, where (as the Statute of</hi> Weſtminſter <hi>the ſecond expreſſed it) a</hi> Durum eſt <hi>was in the Caſe; And that of the Hoſpitall of St.</hi> Leonards 2 <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>N.</hi> 37. <hi>which had a clear Right to a Corn Rent, Yet the Lords could not relieve them, but both were faine to have Acts of Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This receives a twofold Anſwer; One, That there are other Motives in this Caſe to make the Lords retain it, and give <hi>Skinner</hi> Relief; Here is a poor man oppreſſed by a rich Company, with whom he was no waies able to wage Law: And that Conſideration hath in all times prevailed with that Houſe, which is compoſed of Perſons of generous and noble Spirits, who can not ſee poor men oppreſſed without feeling in their hearts an Inclination and a deſire to relieve them: But ſecondly we muſt diſtinguiſh between a Fact not being a Crime in the eye of the Law, which
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:152672:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>is neither <hi>Malum in ſe</hi> nor <hi>Malum prohibitum,</hi> and when the Fact it ſelf being odious and puniſhable by all Laws of God and Man, only a Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, as the Place where it was Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte, dputs it out of the Power of the ordinary Courts of Juſtice to take Cognizance of it, which are kept to formes, and may not trangreſſe them; In the firſt Caſe, the Houſe of Lords can not puniſh that for a Crime which the Law doth not make a a Crime, but in the ſecond Caſe God forbid there ſhould be ſuch a failer of Juſtice in a Kingdome, that fellow ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ſhould robb and worry and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy one an other (though in Forrein parts) and there ſhould be no puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the wrong doer, nor Relief for the party wronged, when they come home; For then the King might be deprived of many a good ſubject, the Land looſe many of her people, Trading receive much prejudice, and ſo King and Kingdome ſuffer great loſs, and all without remedy.</p>
            <p>But then ſay the Houſe of Commons,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:152672:51"/>
               <hi>Where the Law hath provided, and there is an ordinary remedy, an extraordinary ought not to be tryed:</hi> to this the Lords Anſwer, that their Houſe is not an extraordinary remedy, but the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary remedy in extraordinary Caſes, and this of <hi>Skinners</hi> was ſo, both in point of difficulty, and point of Compaſſion.</p>
            <p>And to what is ſaid, <hi>That it is the Intereſt of all men in England to be tryed by Juries, and there is remedy againſt willful Juries by Attaint, but here is no remedy nor no Appeal,</hi> It is Anſwered, That the Court of Chancery diſpoſeth of mens Eſtates without a Jury, Every Court of Juſtice, Every Judge in his Circuit ſets Fines on mens heads upon ſeveral occaſions without a Jury; Many are tryed for their lives and their Liberties (which is more then Eſtate) in the Houſe of Peers upon an impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Houſe of Commons, who are not a Jury, nor are ſworn; therefore that Aſſertion holds not, <hi>That all men in all caſes are tryed by Juries:</hi> And for matters of Appeal, there doth lye one to the next Parliament, or the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:152672:52"/>next Seſſion; But it will be ſaid, That is to the ſame Perſons; And what hopes of any remedy? For they wil make good their own Act; To this is Anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wered, It is what the Law of the Land hath eſtabliſhed; We muſt not be wiſer then the Law; It is what our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors thought ſufficient, what hath been the practice of all time; And if we leave Poſterity in as good a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition as our Anceſtors left us, they will have no Cauſe to Complain. Then we muſt preſume, that Courts of Juſtice will do Juſtice, and will do Right; that upon better reaſon ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Appeal, they will alter their minds, and give an other Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: They have done ſo heretofore; How many Judgements of Parliament have been reverſed by ſucceeding Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments? And where there is Cauſe for it, we muſt hope, they will do ſo again.</p>
            <p>Then where as it is ſaid, <hi>That the greatneſs of the Charge and the Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies of attending Cauſes in the Lords Houſe is an Argument againſt their Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> They Anſwer, That it is not the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:152672:52"/>Houſe of Lords, that appoints ſuch great Fees to Counſel; it being left to their Conſciences that take them, and to the will and diſcretion of their Clients who give them, and who (without an Act of Parliament to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine it) may give what they will, or rather what they muſt: However The Lords ſay, that the charge in Chancery is greater, there having been ſome times forty, fifty Orders made in one Cauſe; and the delay much grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſo as ſome Cauſes have laſted there very many years: And even at the Common Law, how many Verdicts have been given in one Cauſe, contrary Verdicts, one for the Plaintiff, an other for the Defendant? Contrary Rules of Court, the Judges give a Rule one day, and three daies after give an other clean contrary? As an Inſtance of it can be given but of laſt Trinity Term in the Kings Bench. Theſe are Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences, that lye not in the Houſe of Peers. But admit there were Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences: Many Laws are found incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, which yet are put in execution,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:152672:53"/>and all obedience given to them, whileſt they ſtand unrepealed. And the Queſtion is not now of Convenient or Inconvenient, but matter of Right. Is it the Right of the Houſe of Peers? hath it ſtill been the Cuſtome and Uſage of Parliaments, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Law of Parliament, that they ſhould exerciſe ſuch a Power of Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature? If it be ſo (as it is and will be ſufficiently proved) then the point of Conveniency or Inconveniency is out of doors; Well may it be a motive to alter it by the Law. But we will play with them at their own Weapon, and joyn Iſſue upon that point, that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniency is but imaginary, and ſo farr from an Inconvenience, that it is the great advantage of the ſubject that it ſhould be ſo: As well to give relief in Caſes otherwiſe unrelievable, as to aſſiſt and help on the adminiſtration of Juſtice, when ſometimes the greatneſs and power of ſome perſons would elſe bear down, or much obſtruct and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Proceedings of Inferior Courts.</p>
            <p>An objection alſo was raiſed, <hi>How
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:152672:53"/>ſhall the Lords Judgements be executed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Riſing of the Parliament? For ſo the ſubject may be deceived: And when he thinks, that with much Charge he hath made an end of his buſineſs, he is never the nearer;</hi> And it is Anſwered, that the Houſe of Peers is not as the Houſe of Commons, whoſe Orders are only of force, whileſt they are ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, they have power ſufficient to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire Obedience to their Judgements; Nor hath it been knowen, that ever any Judgement of the Houſe of Peers was not ſubmitted unto and obeyed, till now in this Caſe of <hi>Skinners,</hi> that the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company ſtands out in defiance, and refuſeth all Obedience to it. <hi>In</hi> 15 <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>N.</hi> 17. <hi>in the Caſe of the Abbot of St</hi> Oſeches <hi>complaining againſt</hi> John Rokell <hi>for divers Embrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and for not obeying an Order of the Duke of</hi> Lancaſters <hi>made therein, the Lords Confirme that Order; and charge the Lord Chancellor to ſee</hi> Rokell <hi>perform it.</hi> Why may not the Lords do the ſame ſtill, if they doubt of Obedience to their Orders? But there was never queſtion made of it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore:
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:152672:54"/>And there are many Preſidents of Orders given to perſons to act ſome thing in the Intervalls of Parliaments, &amp; to give an account of it to the Lords at the next enſueing Parliament, which ſhewes, that their Authority ſtil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues, to empower thoſe perſons to act and to execute their Orders even when the Parliament is riſen; 15 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>N.</hi> 48. <hi>The Biſhops of</hi> Dureſme <hi>and Saliſbury, the Earl of</hi> Northamton, Warwick, Arundell <hi>and</hi> Saliſbury <hi>are appointed to take the Anſwer of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>and to report it to the next Parliament: And</hi> 51 E. 3. N. 96. <hi>It is there ſpecified, How in the Parliament before, one</hi> Hugh Staffolk <hi>had been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of divers Extortions, and that a Commiſſion was then granted to the Earl of</hi> Suffolk <hi>and Sir</hi> John Cavendiſh <hi>to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into it, who ſo had done, and had found him guiltleſs by</hi> 18 <hi>Enqueſts, which Sir</hi> John Cavendiſh <hi>did in that preſent Parliament witneſs to be true:</hi> By all this it appears, that the Authority of the Houſe of Peers ends not with the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, but their Judgements ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in full force and power; And
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:152672:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>they may appoint Perſons to ſee them executed if they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons <hi>doth not deny them a power of Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature upon Writs of Error and upon Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peales,</hi> Will not the ſame objection lye as well againſt their Judgements in thoſe Caſes? For ſeldome that they be put in execution before the Parliament riſe, ſo it takes away their whole Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature, as in truth all the other ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections would do, could they be made good.</p>
            <p>And whereas it was ſaid, <hi>That none of the Kings Courts can give remedy, where the Kings Writ can not run; And where his Majeſties Soveraignty doth not come, the Juriſdiction of the Peers can have no place;</hi> It was Anſwered, that there Chiefly the Power of the Houſe of Peers is to give remedy, becauſe it only can: As for Treaſons (till the Statutes of 26 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>C.</hi> 13.32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>C.</hi> 2. and 5 <hi>E.</hi> 6. <hi>C.</hi> 11. which have made them tryable within the Realm) and all Miſdemeanors committed in Forrein parts, which never were, nor
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:152672:55"/>yet are, tryable at the Common Law: Of this there are multitudes of Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, <hi>Gomeniz, Weſton, Segrave, Hall, Richill &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here within the Kingdome the the Kings Writ doth not originally run in all places, as for example, in the Counties Palatine, yet no man will deny the Authotity of the Lords in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament taking place there; 9 <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>N.</hi> 13. <hi>The Duke of</hi> Lancaſter <hi>Complaines of Sir</hi> John Stanley <hi>for not ſuing out his Livery for the Mannor of</hi> Latham <hi>in the Dukes Court of Chancery, and yet entring upon it; They declare his Entry unlawful, and Order him to ſue out his livery in the Dukes Court.</hi> The Kings Writ did not run there, but the Authority of the Lords did.</p>
            <p>Another Objection was, <hi>That all Proceedings ought to be in Latin, and n<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Record to be in Engliſh:</hi> But the Lords had thought, That none had ever yet doubted, but the Houſe of Peers had been a Court of Record, where all the Proceedings &amp; Orders &amp; Judgements have been in Engliſh ever ſince <hi>H.</hi> 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:152672:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>time. All Acts of Parliament in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh. All impeachments, even thoſe brought up by the Houſe of Commons, the Proceedings, and the Sentence, all in Engliſh. The Ancient Records were in French, and the Pleadings likewiſe, till the Statute of 36 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Which appoints Pleadings to be in Engliſh, and to be entred and enrolled in Latin (ſo the Print ſaith, but in Sir</hi> Robert Cottons <hi>Abridgement of the Records it is obſerved that the Record it ſelf warrants no ſuch thing:</hi>) Then the Chancery Proceedings are all in Engliſh, The Pleadings, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and Decrees: Yet it will not be denied but that is a Court of Record: Sir <hi>Edward Coke,</hi> who alone is of an other Opinion concerning the Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and upon that ground, becauſe the Proceeding is in Engliſh, yet makes the Houſe of Commons it ſelf a Court of Record, where every body knowes all is in Engliſh; <hi>Jnſt.</hi> 4. part <hi>p.</hi> 23. ſo he doth not <hi>ſibi conſtare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt Objection and indeed the the Chief one (if true) was, <hi>That it deprives the Subject of the benefit of</hi>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:152672:56"/>Magna Charta, <hi>which will have all men to be tryed by their Peers, or by the Law of the Land; And the</hi> 25 <hi>of</hi> Ed. 3. C. 4. <hi>that none ſhall be apprehended upon Petition to the King or Counſel,</hi> (and Counſel here they interpreted to be the Houſe of Lords) <hi>but upon inditement or preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or by Writ Original; And the</hi> 42. <hi>of</hi> E. 3. <hi>which is to the ſame purpoſe; It was urged further that no Writ was ever made returnable</hi> Coram Dominis Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualibus et Temporalibus; <hi>And it was ſaid in Regard of the Iſland, being in a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein Princes Juriſdiction, that it ought to have been done by Act of Parliament, for that no Court of his Majeſtie can give re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, where his Majeſties Writ can not run, nor can the Juriſdiction of the Houſe of Peers have place there:</hi> An other ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation they had upon <hi>Lex Terrae</hi> in <hi>Magna Charta, That in the Arguments of the Kings learned Counſel</hi> 3. Car. <hi>They made</hi> Lex Terrae <hi>to be the pleaſure of the King, And the Lords were deſired to conſider upon this, if by arguing that the Proceedings of their Houſe were maintained to be</hi> Secundum Legem Terrae, <hi>it may
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:152672:56"/>not as well be ſaid that</hi> Magna Charta <hi>will have men to be tryed</hi> Per Judicium Parium aut per Legem Terrae, <hi>That is, by the will of the Lords.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the ſubſtance of what was moſt materially urged againſt the Lords at that Conference. Some other things were ſaid, rather to entertain the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanders, then for any thing elſe; as the queſtion asked <hi>How the Lords ſhould ſee further beyond ſea then other men;</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Lords thought they might ſee as farr as other men, and as farr as the Court of Chancery or any other Court, but never undertook to ſee further: But they think, if ſome may have their wills, they may be laid ſo low, that they ſhall then ſee but a very little way; but that is not yet.</p>
            <p>And another pretty Dilemma was made, which was this, <hi>Are the Lords bound to recieve all Petitions or not? if bound, they may refuſe none, for</hi> Magna Charta <hi>ſaith</hi> Nulli negabimus, <hi>and the King is</hi> Debitor Juſtitiae <hi>to all his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; If they be not bound, then they muſt be partial, to receive ſome and diſmiſs others:</hi>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:152672:57"/>But this <hi>Argumentum bicorne</hi> hurts with neither horne; For the Lords in theſe very Preſidents brought by the Houſe of Commons in <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. time did not deny Juſtice, when they ſent the Petitioners unto thoſe ſeveral Courts, where they ſhould receive it, one to the Chancery, an other to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, and directed one to bring ſuch an Action, another a differing one, according to their ſeveral Caſes: And in thoſe multitudes of Preſidents brought by the Lords where Cauſes have been retained and determined in that Houſe, they can not juſtly be charged with Partiality, when they are moved thereunto by ſome thing extraordinary in thoſe Caſes, which requires their Relief, and that it can not be had elſe where; And a Queſtion may be put on the other ſide, whither it can be believed, that Partiality was imputed to all the Parliaments hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, which at their firſt ſitting appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Committees, Tryers of Petitions for <hi>England,</hi> for <hi>Ireland,</hi> for <hi>Gaſcony,</hi> nay for <hi>Flanders</hi> (where the King had no Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion)
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:152672:57"/>and ſometimes in general, for all places beyond the Seas, to examine which were fit to be received, which not; And thoſe Parliaments that the <hi>Modus Parliamenti</hi> ſpeakes of, when a little before the riſing of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Proclamation was made in Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick places, to know if any had buſineſs to the Parliament, if any had Petitioned the Parliament &amp; their Petition had not been anſwered; Certainly thoſe Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments then did not apprehend to be reproached either with Partiality or deniall of Juſtice. And I would aske this further, If they can think that ſuch a Committee of Tryers would have rejected <hi>Skinners</hi> Petition, and have ſaid The Lords can take no Cognizance of your buſineſs, becauſe it is concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning things done beyond Sea, when themſelves were a Committee appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted only for ſuch buſineſſes.</p>
            <p>But to let theſe <hi>Sarcaſmes</hi> paſs, and ſee rather what was ſaid and may be ſaid to the more ſolid objections, concerning <hi>Magna Charta</hi> and thoſe other Statutes, which they will have to condemne the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:152672:58"/>Proceedings of the Lords. Firſt it may be obſerved as a thing very ſtrange, that in above 400 years ſince <hi>Magna Charta</hi> was firſt made a Law, it was never till now found out, that the Lords had bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that Law by the exerciſe of this Juriſdiction, nor were they ever char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with it before. But beſides, do they by this any more break it, then the Court of Chancery, which by a Decree diſpoſes of a mans Lands, or the Court of the Conſtable and Marſhall, which takes away a mans life, or any other Court where the Judge for a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt preſently ſends a man to Priſon or claps a Fine on his head, ſo takes both perſon and Eſtate, or the ſame Houſe of Lords, when it Commits a man upon an Impeachment of the Houſe of Commons, Judges, and Condemnes him; Here is no <hi>Judicium Parium</hi> (that is moſt certain) nor <hi>Lex Terrae,</hi> if you take it for an Original Writ; And yet no man will ſay, any of this is contrary to <hi>Magna Charta:</hi> Why then may not the Proceedings of the Houſe of Peers, when it puniſheth a man for robbing
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:152672:58"/>and aſſaulting his fellow ſubject in as ſtrange Country, which puts the buſineſ out of the Cognizance of the ordinary Courts of Juſtice, receive as favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Conſtruction? It can not be ſaid, that the Houſe of Commons, by their taking Cognizance of a Fact, &amp; by their previous examination of it, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration upon it, giving it the Denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Treaſon or of any other leſſer Crime, can create a Juriſdiction in the Houſe of Peers, which it had not before, and give it new power and Authority to paſs a condemnation upon the guilty Perſon, yet is it the Ordinary practice of the Houſe of Commons (who have a Grand Committee of Grievances for that purpoſe) to impeach men ſo before the Lords.</p>
            <p>They could receive not long ſince a Petition of one <hi>Taylor</hi> complaining againſt the Lord <hi>Mordant</hi> for oppreſſion and falſs impriſonment, and the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious taking away of an Office from him at <hi>Windſor:</hi> All which were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly tryable in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> yet they could bring this up to the Lords,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:152672:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>and crave Reparations and Damages in the Name of the Commons of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> And the Lords muſt not, though at the Kings recommendation, receive a Petition from <hi>Skinner,</hi> and give him relief for his whole Eſtate by violence and with a ſtrong hand taken from him, part at Sea, part upon Land, in a ſtrange Country, in neither of which the Courts of <hi>Weſtminiſter</hi> can afford him any help; For this muſt be againſt <hi>Magna Charta;</hi> So rather then the Lords ſhall do it, this muſt be a Fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of Juſtice in the Land, the King ſhall not be able to protect his ſubjects, the oppreſſor ſhall go free, and the cry of the oppreſſed ſhall go up to heaven for Judgment upon the Land, becauſe he finds not Juſtice in it for his Relief.</p>
            <p>But I remember what the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Houſe of Commons ſaid at the Conference, <hi>That therefore the Lords ſhould not have given Relief in this Caſe, becauſe there was no remedy at all at Law;</hi> This Objection hath been already anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wered, therefore I ſhall not repeat it here; only uſe one Argument more <hi>ad
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:152672:59"/>hominum,</hi> that they forget what them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have done this very Parliament, entertaining a Complaint of one <hi>Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> againſt the Lord <hi>Willoughby</hi> (who is ſince dead) for diſpoſſeſſing him of his Eſtate, and other wrongs done him in the <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> which could not be tryed in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> which yet they were preparing to bring up to the Lords, by way of Impeachment, if the Lord <hi>Willoughby</hi> had not dyed; And there is reaſon to believe, that if <hi>Skinner</hi> had in the like manner applied himſelf to them, there had been no breach of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> nor no excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions taken at the great charge of the Subject appealing to the Houſe of Commons and proſecution there (though the charge be every whit as great and becomes much greater to the party that proſecutes, for when he hath done there, then he muſt begin again in the Houſe of Lords, ſo the charge is double,) and the Judgement when it comes is never a whit more in Latin to make it a Record, then if the buſineſs had begun firſt in the Lords Houſe, &amp; as
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:152672:60"/>much is it without Jury or Appeal, and no leſs danger of the non-execution of the Judgement after the riſing of the Parliament: In Fine all that is ſaid againſt the Lords Proceedings now, might as well be ſaid againſt them then; And to ſay the truth, if it be well conſidered, it wil be found, that the conſequence of this oppoſition (ſhould it work it's effect, and prevail) would be the overturning of the very foundation of all Authority of Parliament; that it might then well be ſaid of the whole Parliament, that it did ſit only to make Laws and give Subſidies.</p>
            <p>But all this proves not the exerciſe of the Lords Judicature to be warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> it only ſaith, that other Courts, and the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons it ſelf do as bad: Which is no Juſtification of the Lords; For to erre with Company is not to be free from fault. Let us then ſee, what may be ſaid to clear them all, but principally and Chiefly this Judicature of the Houſe of Peers, which is the mark ſhot at.</p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:152672:60"/>
            <p>And to do this, we muſt examine the Disjunctive propoſition in <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> which ſaith, that every man ſhal be tryed <hi>Per Legale Judicium Parium ſuorum, vel per Legem Terrae;</hi> For if the Lords judge by either of theſe, they are well enough: And Sir <hi>Ed. Coke</hi> ſhall determine the queſtion, whom no man can ſuſpect of partiality for the Houſe of Lords: He tells us in his 2. <hi>Inſt. F.</hi> 51. That <hi>Lex Terrae</hi> is <hi>Lex Angliae,</hi> not <hi>Voluntas Regis</hi> as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſaid the Kings Counſel would have it to be 3 <hi>Car.</hi> And leſs <hi>voluntas Dominorum;</hi> Fot it is not in an arbitrary way the Lords proceed, but according to the Law of the Land; to puniſh nothing but what the Law makes puniſhable, and Judge every thing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Right, <hi>ſecundum aequum et bonum.</hi> So then <hi>Per Legem Terrae</hi> is all one with <hi>Per Legem Angliae,</hi> or <hi>ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Legem et Conſuetudinem Angliae,</hi> and what ever is done <hi>ſecundum Legem Ang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liae</hi> is done <hi>Per Legem Terrae;</hi> And in his 1 <hi>Inſt. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. He tells us what <hi>Lex Angliae</hi> is, he ſaith there are divers
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:152672:61"/>Laws within the Realme of <hi>England,</hi> and reckons them up, <hi>Lex et Conſuetudo Parliamenti</hi> is in the front of them; He names many more, the Civil Law by which the Court of Conſtable and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall, and the Court of Admiralty and Eccleſiaſtical Courts do act, the Law of War for the Court Martiall to act by, the Law of Merchants, the law of Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neries, Particular Cuſtomes in ſeveral places of the Kingdome, Statute Lawes eſtabliſhed by Authority of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Whoever and whatever is tryed by any of theſe Laws be it for life, Lands, or goods, it (is ſtill accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Magna Charta</hi> and though not <hi>Per Judicium Parium, yet Per Legem Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae.</hi> The Law and Cuſtome of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is one of theſe, and the Lords now acting agreeably to that, act agreably to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and that they have acted ſo, is I think ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved all ready, and will be further hereafter, when we ſhew you Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents for it, from the beginning of Parliaments.</p>
            <p>So for the other Statutes of the 25
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:152672:61"/>of <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4. and the 42. <hi>c.</hi> 3. They do not at all concerne the Houſe of Peers, and were made only to prevent Vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Petitions and falſe accuſations before the King and his Privy Counſel, as appeares by the Preambles of thoſe Statutes. Though the Gentlemen of the Houſe of Commons who managed the Conference were pleaſed to give them an other Interpretation, and to ſay, that the Petitions and ſuggeſtions to the King or his Counſel, which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by thoſe Statutes, are to be underſtood of thoſe brought to the King and Houſe of Lords; But can it be rationally believed, That the Houſe of Peers of thoſe times ſhould themſelves make ſo many Lawes, paſs ſo many Acts of Parliament (five in the ſpace of 17 years the 25 of <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4. the 28 <hi>c.</hi> 3. the 37 <hi>c.</hi> 18. the 38 <hi>c.</hi> 9. the 42 <hi>c.</hi> 3. all of them prohibiting that any man ſhould be apprehended, impriſoned or diſinherited upon an accuſation or ſuggeſtion to the King or his Counſel, and enjoyning all Proceedings, to be by Original Writ, or by Inditement, or
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:152672:62"/>by Preſentment of good and lawfull People of the Neighbourhood;) And they know themſelves to be intended by thoſe Acts, and yet ſtill ſhould act contrary to them, judge and determine ſo many Cauſes both Criminal and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, as they did from time to time.</p>
            <p>Nay can it be believed, That the Houſe of Commons in thoſe daies would bring up Impeachments againſt men to have them tryed at the Lords Barr, if they did then conceive that thoſe Acts of Parliament did forbid the Lords to meddle; For though the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Houſe are ſometimes called the Grand Inqueſt of the Kingdome to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the Grievances thereof, it is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed they will not ſay, that their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment is the Preſentment intended by thoſe Statutes; For the Preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment mentioned there is the very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription and true Character of your Country Juries: The words of the Statute are; <hi>The Preſentment of good and lawful people of the ſame neighbourhood, where ſuch Deeds be done; And can</hi> any man think, that this is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:152672:62"/>of the Houſe of Commons? No certainly; What then is it that makes the Lords Proceedings upon the Impeachments of the Commons to be Legal and not contrary to thoſe Acts of Parliament; Since there is neither Writ nor Inditement nor Preſentment, and yet men are brought to tryal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and executed by their Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? but only this, that it is the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law of the Land, being the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, unqueſtioned, and undoubted Law and Uſage of Parliaments. And thereby is there a clear demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the true meaning of thoſe Statutes, that it was the Regulation of the Kings Privy Counſel they aimed at, and not of the Houſe of Lords; that Counſel, of which Sir <hi>John Lee</hi> was one in that 42 <hi>of E.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 23. <hi>who was tryed and cenſured by that very Parliament, in which that Act was made: One of the Articles againſt him was, That being of the Kings Counſel, and Steward of his Houſe be cauſed ſundry men to be attached and and brought before him, and made them anſwer ſingly to him, as if it had been to the body of the Counſel; He was fined for
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:152672:63"/>it, and committed to the Tower.</hi> The Lords <hi>John Nevil</hi> was likewiſe of this Counſel, <hi>&amp; for miſbehaving himſelf in it, Judgment of Impriſonment, and loſs of Lands, goods, and Office was given upon him,</hi> 50 E. 3 n. 34. <hi>And in the ſame Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> n. 18. <hi>The Lord</hi> Latimer <hi>was accuſed for divers miſcarriages being a Counſellor, and for them he was by the Biſhops and Lords committed to the keeping of the Marſhall of</hi> England; <hi>and adjudged to make Fine and Ranſome at the Kings pleaſure, It is true he was enlarged preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the Earl Marſhall, one Arch-Biſhop, three Biſhops, the Prior of St. John, three Earls, fifteen Barons; and thirteen Knights being his Manucaptors, but the Commons deſired further, that he might be no longer of the Kings Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel which was granted;;</hi> And this was not to put him out of the Lords Houſe, for he continued ſtill a Member there, and had his Writ of Summons to come to the next Parliament in the 51<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> year of that King. There is nothing more clear, then that thoſe Statutes are all to be underſtood to mean the Privy Counſel; and ſo did the two Houſes of
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:152672:63"/>Parliament interpret them 3 <hi>Car.</hi> in their Petition of Right, where the expreſſion is, That againſt the tenor of thoſe Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes divers were detained by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties ſpecial command certified by the Lords of the Privy Counſel; and one may bodly affirme that never any Statute, or Act of Parliament did term the Houſe of Lords the Kings Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel.</p>
            <p>So that Article of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged likewiſe at the Conference, <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munia Placita non ſequantur noſtram Curiam,</hi> concernes not them neither; It was to fix the Court of Common Pleas, which (as all other Courts) was before that Ambulatory, and followed the King where ever he was, if he was in the Kingdome; and the Writs were made returnable <hi>Coram nobis ubicunque fuerimus,</hi> which was a great Grievance to the ſubject, and cauſe of many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continuances in ſutes; The following words clear it, <hi>Sed teneantur</hi> in <hi>aliquo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to loco;</hi> Now the place of the meeting of the Parliament was alwaies certainly known, being expreſſed in the Writ of
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:152672:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>Summons, which ſhewes, it was not meant for them.</p>
            <p>And whereas it was ſaid, <hi>That in Caſes of Freehold there is no Proceeding without an Original Writ;</hi> Scarſe any that walkes <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall</hi> but knows the contrary, and the Courſe of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding to be ſo fart otherwiſe, as that not one Tryal for Land of forty comes on upon ſuch a Writ; But by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery only of a Declaration of Treſpaſs and Ejectment, any mans Inheritance of never ſo much value may be queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and brought to Tryal if it ſhall continue his or no; Nay, There is an Act of Parliament 18 <hi>El. c.</hi> 14. which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides expreſly, <hi>That after a verdict given, the want of an Original Writ ſhall be no Cauſe of Error to be pleaded in Arreſt of Judgement, but that Judgement and Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall follow;</hi> So farr is it from being true, that no Freehold can be judged without an Original Writ. And faine would I aske, what Original Writ they uſe in Chancery to ſue men there for their Freehold? Is it any more, then for the Complainant to put in his Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionary
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:152672:64"/>Bill of Complaint, then take out a Writ of <hi>Subpoena</hi> for the Defendant to come in and anſwer by ſuch a day? juſt what was heretofore uſed in the Houſe of Lords, the Plaintiff put in his Petition, and the Houſe ordered a Writ of Summons to Iſſue out to call in the Defendant; But in later times that Houſe (as is uſuall for all Courts to alter their Method of Proceeding, and find out ſome more compendious and eaſy way both for themſelves, and for Suitors) ſo have they inſtead of a Writ as formerly, (which asked more time and charge to take out) made it now, that an Order of the Houſe ſhall be ſufficient for that purpoſe, but they may returne to their Writs of Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons again when they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>And as to Original Writs, ow un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable is it and ggainſt all reaſon, to make it now an Objection againſt the Judicature of the Houſe of Peers, <hi>That the Proceedings there not being upon thoſe Writs, they ought not to meddle with mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Freehold,</hi> Since the Practice of the Law is now ſo changed, that even In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:152672:65"/>Courts have left off the uſe of them: whereas heretofore, when all other Courts were by the Law and the practiſe of thoſe times tyed to thoſe Forms, the Houſe of Lords was not, but exerciſed ſtill their Judicature in their own Parliamentary way without Original Writs; yet no ſuch exception was then taken, but all their Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were ſtill allowed of, approved and obeyed, and punctually executed.</p>
            <p>And the other Aſſertion doth not operate much neither, viz. <hi>That it was never heard of a Writ Returnable Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram Dominis Spiritualibus et Temporali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</hi> For if it be meant of Original VVrits, what doth that ſignifie, ſeeing they are not at all neceſſary, no not uſed now for Commencing of ſuites even in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> much leſs in Parliament, where the uſe hath ever been otherwiſe? And if meant of other VVrits, it is a foul-miſtake: For it hath been the Common practice of the Houſe of Peers, eſpecially in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times, upon any Complaint made to them by Petition, to Order a VVrit
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:152672:65"/>to Iſſue out with the Petition annexed, or containing the matter of it, directed ſometimes to the party himſelf petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt, commanding him to appear, ſometimes to the Sheriff of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, commanding him to ſummon the party, to appear before them at a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine day, and the Writ withall to be then returned, ſo to enter into the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of the buſines, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards proceed to Judgement: Ancient Preſidents of this are <hi>ſans nombre:</hi> 25 <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>m.</hi> 14. <hi>Upon Complaint of the Arch-Biſhop of</hi> York, <hi>That the Advouſon of the Rectory of</hi> Bridgeford <hi>was detained from him by</hi> Boniface de Salucijs, <hi>a Writ re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing the matter complained of is ordered to be ſent unto him, requiring him to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in Parliament the morrow after St.</hi> Gregory <hi>the</hi> Pope <hi>at</hi> Carlile, <hi>and ſhew cauſe</hi> Quare ad finalem expeditionem praedictorum negotiorum minime fuerit procedendum, <hi>why the Houſe ſhould not proceed to a final diſpatch of the buſines; and be was enjoyned to bring the Writ with him,</hi> habeas ibi tunc hoc Breve <hi>is the Cloſe of the Writ. The Printed Book of
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:152672:66"/>the</hi> Placita Parliamentaria <hi>in</hi> Ed. 1. time, is full of Preſidents of this Nature, &amp; I have in this diſcourſe cited very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny both out of that Book &amp; other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of Parliament under the other Kings: I ſhal not therefore heap uy any number here, though it were eaſie to do: I will only give a ſhort account of one, which ſeemes to me a memorable one out of that Book of the Pacita Parliamentaria <hi>p.</hi> 1.57. <hi>the</hi> 21 <hi>of</hi> E. 1. Magdulphus <hi>ſonne of</hi> Malcolin <hi>Earl of</hi> Fife <hi>in</hi> Scotland <hi>complaines in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to King</hi> Edward, <hi>That</hi> John <hi>King of</hi> Scotland <hi>had wrongfully diſpoſſeſſed him of certain Lands in</hi> Scotland <hi>called</hi> Reyes <hi>and</hi> Crey, <hi>Whereupon King</hi> Edward <hi>directs his Writ to the Sheriff of</hi> Northumberland, <hi>commanding him to go into</hi> Scotland, <hi>(taking perſons with him to teſtifie it) and there deliver a Writ of Summons to the King of</hi> Scotland <hi>to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before him ſuch a day,</hi> ad reſponden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum praedicto Magdulpho ſuper prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſis et ad faciendum et recipiendum ulterius, quod Juſtitia requireret: <hi>Which was by the Sheriff performed at</hi> Striveling <hi>the morrow after St.</hi> Peter
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:152672:66"/>ad vincula, <hi>who made his returne accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly to the Parliament: And the King of</hi> Scotland <hi>appeared at his day, and was asked, if the Kings Writ had been delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to him by the ſaid Sheriff, which he acknowledged, and ſaid further</hi> Quod ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per paratus eſt et erit Brevia et manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Regis ut Domini ſui admittere: <hi>Then be was bid to deliver in the Writ, and he ſaid he had delivered it to his Chancellor, and the Chancellor examined ſaid he had it not there: But yet upon the Kings acknowledgement that he had received ſuch a Writ, his appearance was admitted, and be was willed to Anſwer to the matter of complaint put in by</hi> Magdulphus. His Anſwer was, <hi>That he was King of</hi> Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>and could not, without the Counſel and Advice of the good men of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſpeak to any thing that concerned it. This was judged by the Parliament to be</hi> Contempt us manifeſlus et Inobedientia expreſſa, <hi>and it was further Ordered that three of the Principal Caſtles of</hi> Scotland <hi>ſhould be ſeiſed into the Kings hands, and ſo remain</hi> Quo-uſque de contemptu et
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:152672:67"/>Inobedientia praedicta cidem Domino Regi ſatisfecerit. <hi>But the King of</hi> Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>came before the pronouncing of the ſentence</hi> Coram Rege et Conſilio ſuo, et fecit Domino Regi quandam Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationem ore ſuo proprio per verba ſubſcripta, <hi>which words were theſe,</hi> Sire Ieo ſuy voſtre home du Royaulme d'Eſcoce, et vous prie que de ceo que vous me avez mis adevant que touche les gents de mon Royalme auſſy come a moy, voillez mettre en ſoeffrance, jeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques a taunt que ieo ay a eux parle, que ieo ne ſey ſuppris per defaute de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeil, deſicum les gens que cy ſont oue moy ne moy voillent ne oſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeiller ſauns autre du Royaulme; et quand ieo me averay a eux conſaile, ieo vous reſpondray a voſtre primer Parliament apres Paſch le Conſeil qil moy averont donnez, et fray envers vous ceque fere deveray. Sir <hi>I am your liege man for the Kingdome of</hi> Scotland, <hi>and do pray, that as to what you have propoſed unto me, which concernes the People of my Kingdome as well as my ſelf, you will have patience till I can ſpeak with them, that I be
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:152672:67"/>not ſurpriſed for want of Counſel, ſeeing thoſe who are here with me, will not nor dare not give me their advice without the reſt of the Kingdome: And when I ſhall have advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with them, I ſhall give you for Anſwer at your firſt Parliament after</hi> Eaſter <hi>that which they ſhall counſel me, and ſhall do unto you that which I ought to do. This requeſt of his did King</hi> Edward <hi>grant, the Record ſaith,</hi> Et Dominus Rex habito ſuper hoc Conſilio ad Rogatum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictum praedicti Regis Scotiae, et etiam ad Inſtantiam Procerum et Magnatum de Conſilio ſuo, et Gratia ſua ſpeciali, et ſimiliter de Conſenſu praedicti Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulphi, conceſſit ipſi Regi Scotiae ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicationem ſuam, et diem ei dedit ad Parliamentum ſuum poſt Paſcha <hi>viz.</hi> in Craſtino Sanctae Trinitatis &amp;c, in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus in eodem ſtatu quo nunc, Idem dies datus eſt praefato Magdulpho. Et per ipſum dominum Regem dictum eſt praefato Regi Scotiae, et injunctum, quod habeat ad praefatum terminum praedicta Brevia, quae cognovit ſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepiſſe ut ſupra dictum eſt: <hi>He muſt not forget to bring the Writs with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="132" facs="tcp:152672:68"/>
            <p>1 R. 2. <hi>n.</hi> 29. A Scire facias <hi>is awarded againſt the Earl of</hi> March <hi>to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before the Lords at the next Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to abide further Order: And</hi> 2 R. 2. <hi>n.</hi> 33. <hi>the Sheriff of</hi> Shropſhire <hi>makes his return, that the ſame Earl was not found in his Bayliwick, it ſeemes he was dead, for there was then an other</hi> Scire facias <hi>ordered to warne his Son, who was then Earl, to be and Anſwer at the next Parliament after.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>13 R. 2. <hi>n.</hi> 12. <hi>Upon a complaint of the Biſhop and Dean and Chapter of</hi> Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne <hi>againſt the Mayor and Towneſmen for ſome wrongs done them in Execution of their Charter, by order of Parliament a Writ was directed to the Mayor and Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffs of the Town, to appear at a certain day before the Lords, with Authority from their commonalty, for abiding their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips determination; they appear, but not coming with full Power, they are adjudged in Contempt. By the ſame Parliament ſuch a Writ is directed likewiſe to the Mayor and Bayliffs of</hi> Cambridge <hi>upon <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Petition and Complaint from the Vice-Chancellor
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:152672:68"/>and Scholars, and they run the like fortune, to be adjudged in Contempt for the like cauſe. So then there are Writs made returnable in Parliament.</hi> And many other examples may be given and ſome more will be given in this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and Preſidents cited upon other occaſions where Writs have been Iſſued ſo returnable; Which ſhall be obſerved as we go along: And theſe few ſhall in this place ſuffice to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove that Aſſertion; Nor indeed was there any thing ſaid on that ſide, that did not receive a full and ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Anſwer.</p>
            <p>For what was ſaid of an Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to give <hi>Skinner</hi> relief for his Iſland, doth in truth deſerve no Anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, for it were ridiculous to think an Act of Parliament, or any thing elſe but an Army, could put him into Poſſeſſion of his Iſland again; And it would be altogether uſeleſs unto him could he ſo obtaine it, his Plantation there being utterly deſtroyed, and all
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:152672:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>his goods ſpoiled and loſt both there and at <hi>Jamby,</hi> ſo as it would be impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for him to carry on his trade to any advantage; Therefore it is Repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and Satisfaction for his Damage, which he muſt have: And that is not the work of an Act of Parliament, but of a Court of Judicature. That advice then is not to be followed, and ſo we will leave it.</p>
            <p>It now remaines but to ſet forth the Preſidents, which the Lords did on their part alledge, with ſome few more Antient ones, which ſhall be added for the Vindicating and Aſſerting of their Right unto this (never before controverted) point of their Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in all Caſes of what nature ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, when ſome thing extraordinary in thoſe Caſes did induce them to exerciſe it; Of which they were the ſole Judges, that being a Truſt lodged in them by the very Frame and conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Government.</p>
            <pb n="135" facs="tcp:152672:69"/>
            <p>
               <hi>In the black Book in the</hi> Tower, <hi>which is Printed by the Name of</hi> Placita Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentaria, 30 E 1. F. 231. <hi>is the Caſe of Sir</hi> VVilliam Paynell <hi>and</hi> Margaret <hi>his Wife ſuing for Dower upon the Lands of</hi> John Cameys, <hi>who had been</hi> Margarets <hi>former Husband, and whom ſhe had left he yet living; And they now deſiring tobe tryed by their Country upon the point of Adultery, and the Lords not allowing of it; This hath been at large expreſſed before, therefore I only mention it now.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the ſame Book p.</hi> 266.33. Ed. 1. <hi>The Caſe of</hi> Nicholas Segrave, <hi>who was tryed in Parliament for leaving the Kings Army then in</hi> Scotland, <hi>and goeing over into</hi> France <hi>to fight with one</hi> John de Crumbwell <hi>upon a fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling out between them, they being toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Kings Army: This was a caſe not tryable in</hi> VVeſtminſter-Hall, <hi>nor puniſhable in any ordinary Court of Juſtice by the Common Law of</hi> England, <hi>yet the Houſe of Lords could try him, and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:152672:70"/>adjudge him worthy of death: And one thing more is obſervable in that Record, That a Writ is Iſſued to the Sheriff of the County to take foure Knights with him and in their preſence to Summon</hi> Segrave, Quod eſſet Coram Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino Rege in proximo Parliamento ſuo apud VVeſtm. ad audiendum voluntatem ipſius Regis, et ad facien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum et recipiendum ulterius quod Curia Domini Regis conſideraret <hi>in</hi> Praemiſſis: <hi>So here is a Writ re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnable in Parliament, and the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff did accordingly make his returne, that he had Summoned and charged him,</hi> Quod eſſet coram Domino Rege in iſto Parliamento nunc juxta formam et Tenorem Mandati praedicti &amp;c. It was therefore a groſs miſtake to ſay That never any Writ was made returnable in Parliament, as it was likewiſe one to ſay, That the Houſe of Peers could give no remedy, where there was not remedy at Law, this Preſident proving the Contrary to both.</p>
            <pb n="137" facs="tcp:152672:70"/>
            <p>21. Ed. 1. p. 135, 136, <hi>&amp;c. The Arch-biſhop of</hi> York <hi>is queſtioned in Parliament for excommunicating the Biſhop of</hi> Dureſme: <hi>The ground of the Excommunication was, For that the Biſhop of</hi> Dureſme <hi>had impriſoned two Perſons employed by the Arch Biſhop to cite the Biſhop to appear before him. The Arch Biſhop appeals,</hi> Et dicit quod de ſententia a Canone lata, &amp; per ipſum declarata, in Curia Domini Regis non debet reſpondere. <hi>The Houſe of Lords goes on; The other ſide alleadging, That the Biſhop in his Temporal Capacity, as Count Palatin, had committed thoſe men, and it pertained to the King, and not to the Arch-Biſhop, to take cogniſance of the Impriſonment, if or no it was law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; The Judgement is,</hi> Videtur Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino Regi in pleno Parlamento, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictis Comitibus, Baronibus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Quod praedictus Archiepiſcopus quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum in ipſo fuit, nitebatur uſurpare ſuper Coronam &amp; Dignitatem Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Propter quod per Comites, Barones &amp; Juſticiarios &amp; omnes alios de Conſilio ipſius Domini Regis una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimiter
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:152672:71"/>concordatum eſt, quod prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictus Archiepiſcopus committatur Priſonae pro Offenſa &amp; Tranſgreſſione praedictis. Et ſuper hoc ante Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um pronunciatum, (licet unanimiter de Conſilio praedict. Magnatum &amp; aliorum concordatum fuiſſet tenen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum in hoc Caſu &amp; ſimiliter in Caſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus conſimilibus in perpetuum) prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictus Archiepiſcopus Magnates &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lios de Conſilio ipſius Domini Regis rogavit, quod pro eo Dominum Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem requirerent, ut ante pronunciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem Judicii ipſum ad gratiam ſuam admitteret &amp; voluntatem ſuam. <hi>They interceded for him, and he made Fine to the King of</hi> 4000 <hi>Marks, and was received to favour.</hi> They did not only give a Judgment in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Caſe, (which being <hi>Contra Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam &amp; Dignitatem,</hi> was tryable in <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter-hall</hi>) but they declare it to be a Standing Rule for the Judging of all Caſes of like nature; which ſhews the abſoluteneſs of that Power of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature, which is lodged in that Houſe.</p>
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:152672:71"/>
            <p>It was ſaid, <hi>That the Lords could not take a Cauſe to themſelves</hi> per Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, <hi>and before it had paſſed all the formalities below; That a Writ of Error did not lie from the Common Pleas to the Lords Houſe, but muſt firſt be brought to the Kings Bench;</hi> And <hi>the Caſe of the Biſhop of</hi> Norwich <hi>was urged,</hi> 50. Ed. 3. And it is acknowledged, The Lords would not receive that Biſhops Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, but ſent him away with that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, nor could they give him any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: For Writs of Error have their Walk, and their gradual Proceeding chalked out, and ſetled by ſeveral Statutes, and by the Common Law of the Land; But what doth that ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie againſt the Judicature of the Houſe of Peers? No man, ſaith the Lords, can either take Cogniſance of Cauſes, or judge Cauſes againſt the Law of the Land, and take them <hi>per ſaltum,</hi> when the Law prohibits it: But they do ſay and affirm, That by all the Examples and Preſidents of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times, it hath been the uſage of that Houſe to receive Complaints, and
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:152672:72"/>give remedy in all Caſes, where the Law hath not expreſly otherwiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined; and if there be any thing in the Caſe which merits, or requires, and needs ſomething above the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Power and Proceeding of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior Courts of Juſtice, to adminiſter that Relief which is juſt and due. As in Caſes of difficulty where a Court cannot, or of delay where it will not proceed, the Lords, who have a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral inſpection into the Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Juſtice of the Kingdom, and into the Proceedings of all other Courts, have ever, upon Application made to them, aſſumed to themſelves the Cogniſance of ſuch Cauſes. 14. Ed. 3. <hi>Sir</hi> John Stanton, <hi>and his Wife, had paſſed a Fine of certain Lands to</hi> Thomas Cranthorn, <hi>who reverts them back, and by that means ſetled them upon the Wife; Sir</hi> Jeffry Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, <hi>as next Heir, brings his</hi> Formedon en le deſcender <hi>in the Common Pleas, where (after ſome Proceedings) upon a Demurrer in Law, Sir</hi> Jeffry <hi>could not get the Judges to proceed to Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:152672:72"/>Upon which he Petitions the King in Parliament</hi> (which no man will deny to have been in the Houſe of Peers.) <hi>They examine the Matter; And afterward order a Writ under the Great Seal containing the whole Matter to be ſent to the Judges there, willing them thereby, if the Matter ſo ſtood, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to Judgment without delay: They not doing it, an Alias is ſent; And the Judges doing nothing then neither, and Sir</hi> Jeffrey <hi>renewing his Petition; The Lords commanded the Clerk of the Parliament, Sir</hi> Thomas de Drayton, <hi>to go to Sir</hi> John Stoner, <hi>and the reſt of the Judges of the Common Pleas, and to require them, according to the Plea pleaded, to proceed to Judgment, or elſe to come into the Houſe with the whole Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, ſo as in Parliament Judgement might be given for one or the other of the Parties. The Judges come at the day, and the buſineſs was heard, and it was adjudged, That Sir</hi> Jeffrey <hi>ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover; And a Writ under the Great Seal was ſent to the Judges to give Judgment accordingly:</hi> Here then the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:152672:73"/>King in Parliament, (that is the Houſe of Peers) upon a Petition, aſſumes the Cogniſance of a Cauſe, depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Court of Common Pleas; which was ſo far from having paſſed all the formalities below (that is to ſay, an Appeal to the Kings Bench and Chancery) that it was as yet undeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in the Common Pleas. Nor did it appear unto them upon what ground it was, that the Judges gave not Judgment; So they might have anſwered Sir <hi>Jeffrey Stantons</hi> Petition with ſaying, that they would firſt ſee what the Court would determine, and what the Kings Bench afterwards; But they apply themſelves to give him relief: And yet no Votes paſt againſt that Houſe for ſo doing, as now hath been in the Caſe of <hi>Skinner</hi> againſt this.</p>
            <p>So in the Parliament of 18. <hi>E.</hi> 1. p. 16. of the <hi>Placita Parlamentaria,</hi> William de Waſthul <hi>complains of</hi> Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew del Exchequer, <hi>for coſening him upon the levying of a Fine before the Judges of the Common Pleas, by procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:152672:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>an Atturney to ſlip in other Lands unknown to</hi> Waſthul, <hi>and which be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended not to paſs in the Fine: This is returned back to thoſe Judges, becauſe the Fine had been levied before them, Et dictum eſt iiſdem Juſticiariis, quod Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordum iſtud in Rotulis ſuis faciant ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rotulare, &amp; tam ſuper Recordo iſto quam ſuper aliis ipſum</hi> Matthaeum <hi>coram eis contingentibus procedant ad Judicium &amp; debitum &amp; feſtinum faciant Juſtitiae Complementum.</hi> True! the Houſe of Lords is not ſo bound up to forms, but that it may, when it thinks good, vary, and retain a Cauſe at one time, which it will not do at any other time. Yet we ſee they were proper Judges in this Cauſe, for they order <hi>Waſthulls</hi> Complaint, and the Proceedings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them to be entred, as a Record in the Common Pleas, and thoſe Judges to proceed upon it, which, if they had not had Cogniſance of the Matter, had been all <hi>Coram non Judice,</hi> and could have ſignified nothing.</p>
            <p>And I muſt obſerve one thing, which I think will not be denyed, That
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:152672:74"/>all thoſe <hi>Placita Parlamentaria,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is ſaid to be done <hi>Coram Rege in Parlamento,</hi> is to be underſtood of the Houſe of Peers, where the King was in thoſe times commonly preſent, and alwayes underſtood to be there repreſentatively; So as his Name was ever mentioned in the Proceedings, even when his Perſon was abſent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſometimes out of the Kingdom, ſometimes detained away by ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or other occaſion; As 50. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 35. it is ſaid, <hi>The King ordains, That from thenceforth no Woman ſhould for Maintenance purſue Matters in the Kings Courts upon pain, &amp;c.</hi> And then was the King ſick at <hi>Eltham,</hi> and could not come to Parliament, as appears by <hi>n.</hi> 42. and it was only the Houſe of Peers that made that Order. So in Judgments, though in Ancient Times they were moſtly entred as given by the King, yet it was the Lords Houſe, which was <hi>Curia Regis,</hi> that gave them.</p>
            <p>For we muſt know the KING hath a double Capacity of ſitting in the Houſe of Peers, a Legiſlative
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:152672:74"/>Capacity, when he hath in himſelf a Negative Voice to what even both Houſes have concluded and done, which ſignifies nothing without his Aſſent, and his ſingle Diſſent makes it all null and void; This is in paſſing Acts of Parliament, and making of Laws; The other is a Judicial Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, when he will pleaſe to aſſiſt, and be preſent at the ordinary Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Houſe, as heretofore was uſual; which alters not the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it as it is a Court, gives it no more Power nor Juriſdiction then it had before, he being then but in a manner as Chief Judge, and not doing any thing ſingly, but according to the Plurality of Opinions; As when the Kings would in Perſon ſit in the Kings Bench, which they have in former times done, (where ſtill all is ſaid to be done <hi>Coram Rege,</hi> though now he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come there) and in Our Memory King <hi>James</hi> hath ſet in the Star Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; I think no body will ſay the Star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Chamber then, or Kings Bench be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, did or could vary from their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:152672:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>Forms and Rules of Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: No more can the Houſe of Peers alter their Proceedings, or aſſume greater Authority by reaſon of the Royal Preſence, to take Cogniſance of other Cauſes, or do any thing, which by the Cuſtome and Uſage of the Houſe, and the Law of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it could not elſe have done: But their Juriſdiction, and their way of exerciſing that Juriſdiction is ſtill one and the ſame. And therefore <hi>26. H. 6. n. 52. When the King had given a Judgment of himſelf, without the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Lords, in the Caſe of</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam de la Pool <hi>Duke of</hi> Suffolk, <hi>who ſtood impeached for Ireaſon, baniſhing him the Realm for five years; The Lords entred their Proteſtation againſt it, as not done by their Aſſent, and ſo no Act of the Houſe.</hi> And <hi>5. H.</hi> 4. <hi>n.</hi> II. The Earl of <hi>Northumberland</hi> coming into the Parliament before the King and Lords, and by Petition acknowledging to have done contrary to his Allegiance, in giving of Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and gathering of Power, for
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:152672:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>which he prayed pardon, in regard he yeelded himſelf, and came in to the King at <hi>York</hi> upon his Letters; And the King delivering this Petition to the Juſtices to be conſidered, The Lords made their Proteſtation, <hi>That the Judgment appertained only to them; And therefore as Peers of Parliament, to whom ſuch Judgement belonged, in weighing the Statutes concerning Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and concerning Liveries, they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged the Fact of the ſaid Earl to be no Treaſon nor Fellony, but only a Treſpaſs finable to the King;</hi> Whereupon the King received him into Grace, and pardoned him his Fine. All Power of Judicature in Parliament is then queſtionleſs in the Houſe of Lords, where the King alwayes is Perſonally or Virtually, and the Judgment pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from them by the Authority and in the Name of the King: For the Power of Judicature in Parliament is lodged in them, together with the King, as is declared 1. <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>n.</hi> 80. where it is ſaid, <hi>That the Commons were only Petitioners, and that all Judgments
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:152672:76"/>appertain to the King and the Lords, unleſs it were in Statutes, Grants, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidies, and ſuch like.</hi> This hath ever been the Practice, and Cuſtom, and Law of Parliament, ſince there have been Parliaments, and when this ſhall ceaſe to be, the Ancient way of Free Parliaments will ceaſe likewiſe.</p>
            <p>1. R. 2. n. 30. <hi>Sir</hi> John de Cobham <hi>ſheweth, That by the delivery of a Ring of Gold for ſeiſin to</hi> Edward <hi>the third, he had ſetled the Reverſion of ſeveral Mannors there named in the Crown, and now prayes it may ſo remain according to his Intention, divers Lords are exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, the Judges Opinions are asked, who declare it to be a good Livery and Seiſin: And ſo it is ſetled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>N.</hi> 32. William Fitzhugh, <hi>a Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finer and Citizen of</hi> London, <hi>exhibits a Bill of Complaint in the Name of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monalty of that Myſtery, againſt</hi> John Chicheſter <hi>and</hi> John Bolſham <hi>of the ſame Myſtery, for divers Oppreſſions done by them; The Lords ſend for them, examine them, they deny thoſe Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: And</hi> Fitzhugh <hi>refuſing then to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:152672:76"/>his Bill, the Lords commit him to the Tower.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>N. 35. <hi>Rober Hawley</hi> and <hi>John Shakell,</hi> are by the Lords ſent to the Tower for refuſing to bring forth a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Priſoner taken in Battel, whom they had in their keeping, and others laid claim to.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>N.</hi> 41. Alice Perrers <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Pierce, <hi>who bad been much in favour with</hi> Ed. 3. <hi>is queſtioned in the Lords Houſe, Sir</hi> Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Scroope <hi>Lord Steward of the Houſhold managing the Tryal, for that contrary to an Order made by the King and Lords,</hi> 50. Ed. 3. n. 35. <hi>That no Woman, and ſhe by Name, ſhould pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue any Matters by way of Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, upon Pain of perpetual Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and loſs of the whole Eſtate; She notwithſtanding had perſwaded King</hi> Edward <hi>to countermand Sir</hi> Nicholas Dagworth <hi>from going into</hi> Ireland, <hi>when he had been ordained by the Council to go thither for urgent buſineſs, which would have been profitable for the King and the Realm: And an other Charge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her was, for perſwading the King
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:152672:77"/>to pardon</hi> Richard Lyons, <hi>who had been Farmer of the Cuſtoms, and for abuſes and extortions had been cenſured in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to forfeit his Eſtate, and be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Priſon; ſhe got all to be remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and his Eſtate to be reſtored unto him, even that part of it which the King had given to two of his own Sons for their lives. The hearing of this Cauſe took up ſeveral dayes; Many that had been Counſellors and Officers to the late King were examined as Witneſſes. At laſt ſhe is found guilty, and Judgment of Baniſhment and loſs of Eſtate given upon her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. R. 2. n. 24. <hi>The Caſe of the Earl of</hi> Pembrock, <hi>and</hi> William le Zouch, <hi>complaining of</hi> Thomas Roos <hi>for ſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them concerning Lands in</hi> York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire, <hi>and endeavouring to get a Tryall in the Countrey, (the Record is,</hi> Deſitant D'eſtre a Liſſue du pays trop ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieuſement, <hi>his deſiring it being ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicious) ſo they pray,</hi> Que Ils partels Malueis Compaſſements &amp; Procure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments en pais ne ſoient deſheritez. <hi>That they may not looſe their Inheritance
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:152672:77"/>by ſuch wicked practiſes and procure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; The Lords upon this retain the Cauſe, appoint ſome Perſons to examine and report it:</hi> But this Preſident hath been cited before at large, ſo I do but touch it here.</p>
            <p>N. 22. <hi>Sir</hi> Philip Darcy <hi>complains, That the Prior of St.</hi> Johns <hi>of</hi> Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem <hi>ſues him in Chancery for the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of</hi> Temple-hurſt <hi>and</hi> Temple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newſom, <hi>which</hi> Ed. 3. <hi>had granted to</hi> John Darcy <hi>his Father, and produces a Deed ſhewing that the Priors Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor had paſſed the Fee of them to</hi> Ed. 2. <hi>The Lords order that Deed to be ſent to the Treaſurer and Barons of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, to examine the Kings Title, and in the mean time ſtop Proceedings in Chancery.</hi> This is more then taking Cogniſance of a Matter Originally, for they take it out of one Court, where it depended and was undeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, and ſend it to be examined in an other Court, which ſhews the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendant they had upon all other Courts.</p>
            <pb n="152" facs="tcp:152672:78"/>
            <p>4. R. 2. n. 17. <hi>Sir</hi> Ralph de Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riers <hi>had been ſeiſed by the Duke of</hi> Lancaſter <hi>upon the Marches of</hi> Scotland <hi>upon ſuſpicion of Treaſon, for holding Intelligence with the</hi> French <hi>the Kings Enemies, upon ſome Letters of his to ſeveral</hi> French <hi>Lords found and taken up by a Begger. He was brought into Parliament before the Lords, and put to his Anſwer. He firſt deſired Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, then offered the Combate againſt any that would acouſe him, both were denyed him. Then he applyed himſelf to his Anſwer; And after ſeveral dayes hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Lords ſtill remanding him to Priſon, he ſo well defended himſelf, That the Lords ſuſpected the Letters to be forged, and therefore committed the Begger, and bayled Sir</hi> Ralph, <hi>deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to his Manucaptors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. R. 2. n. 45. <hi>The Chancellor and Univerſity of</hi> Cambridg, <hi>Petition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Major Bayliff and Commonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Town, for breaking up their Treaſury, burning their Charter, and by force compelling them to make Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſes of ſome Actions they had brought
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:152672:78"/>againſt the Town, and enter into Bonds to them for great Summs. The Lords direct a Writ to iſſue out to the Maior and Bayliffs to appear in Perſon, and the Commonalty by Atturney. They appear, The Chancellor exhibits Articles againſt them. They being asked why their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhould not be ſeiſed, plead to the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, that the Court ought not to have cogniſance of them: They are told, Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be given, if they would not anſwer: Then they anſwer, and the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is heard. The Townſmen are ordered to deliver up thoſe Deeds forced from the Univerſity, which are preſently cancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: The Town Liberties are ſeiſed into the Kings hands, and part of them gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Univerſity: Some are granted back to the Town, for which they were to pay an increaſe of Rent.</hi> Note, here is a Plea to the Juriſdiction, and that Plea Overruled.</p>
            <p>8. R. 2. n. 12. <hi>The Earl of</hi> Oxford <hi>complains of</hi> Walter Sibell <hi>of</hi> London <hi>for a Slander, in having to the Duke of</hi> Lancaſter <hi>and other Noble-men accuſed him of Maintenance. The Lords hear the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:152672:79"/>buſineſs, Commit</hi> Sibell <hi>to Priſon, and give</hi> 500 <hi>Marks dammages to the Earl.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>9. R. 2. n. 13. <hi>The Caſe of the Duke of</hi> Lancaſter <hi>complaining, That Sir</hi> John Stanley <hi>had entred upon the Mannor of</hi> Latham <hi>which held of him, and had not ſued out his Livery in his Court of Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery. The Lords order him to ſue out his Livery.</hi> But this hath been already mentioned.</p>
            <p>15. R. 2. n. 16. <hi>The Prior of</hi> Holland <hi>in</hi> Lancaſhire <hi>complains of a Riot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by</hi> Henry Trebble, John Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow <hi>and others, and of an Entry made by them into the Parſonage of</hi> Whit wick <hi>in Leiceſterſhire.</hi> John Ellingham <hi>the Serjeant at Arms is ſent for them, who brings them into the Parliament: The Lords commit them to the</hi> Fleet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>N.</hi> 17. <hi>The Abbot of</hi> St. Oſeches <hi>complaineth of</hi> John Rokell <hi>for Embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery.</hi> This Caſe hath been already cited.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>N.</hi> 18. <hi>Sir</hi> William Bryan <hi>had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured a Bull directed to the two Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, to excommunicate ſome that had broken up his Houſe and carried away
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:152672:79"/>Writings. This was read in Parliament, and adjudged to be prejudicial to the King, and to be in Derogation of the Laws; for which he is committed to the</hi> Tower.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>N.</hi> 20. Thomas Harding <hi>accuſeth Sir</hi> John Sutton <hi>and Sir</hi> Richard Sut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, <hi>and layeth to their charge, that by their Conſpiracy he had been kept Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in the</hi> Fleet: <hi>Upon hearing of both Parties, for that the two Knights were known to be men of good Fame, The Lords adjudge him to the</hi> Fleet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>N.</hi> 21. John Shad well <hi>complains a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Archbiſhop of</hi> Canterbury <hi>for excommunicating him and his Neighbors wrongfully, for a Temporal Cauſe apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to the Crown and to the Laws of the Land: The Lords hear the buſineſs, find the Suggeſtions untrue, and commit him to the</hi> Fleet.</p>
            <p>1 H. 4. <hi>n.</hi> 93. <hi>Sir</hi> William Richill <hi>one of the Juſtices of the Common-Pleas (who by expreſs Order of</hi> Ri. 2. <hi>went to</hi> Calais <hi>and took the Examination and Confeſſion of the Duke of</hi> Glouceſter, <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter murdered by</hi> Hall) <hi>was brought a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:152672:80"/>into the Lords Houſe, the King pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and by Sir</hi> Walter Clopton <hi>Chief Juſtice appoſed: And anſwered ſo fully, ſhewing his ſincere dealing, that the Lords one by one declared him innocent: And Sir</hi> Walter Clopton <hi>pronounced him ſuch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4 H. 4. <hi>n.</hi> 21. <hi>The Caſe of</hi> Ponting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don <hi>and Sir</hi> Philip Courtney, <hi>where the Lords direct the Tryal, appointing what the Iſſue ſhall be; and what kind of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhall be impannelled to prevent Sir</hi> Philip<hi>'s practices in the Country: It hath been cited before at large.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. E. 4. <hi>m.</hi> 6. <hi>n.</hi> 16. <hi>The Tenants of the Mannor of</hi> Eaſt-Maine <hi>belonging to the Biſhop of</hi> Wincheſter, <hi>the King being in his Progreſs in</hi> Hampſhire <hi>in the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer-time, complained to him of their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop for raiſing new Cuſtoms among them, and not ſuffering them to enjoy their Old ones: The King bids them come to Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in Winter, and they ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved: They come, and the King recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends their buſineſs to the Lords: They commit it to certain Juſtices to examine, Upon their Report, and upon mature De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:152672:80"/>it was adjudged, That the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants were in fault, That they complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without cauſe, and they were ordered to continue their ſaid Cuſtoms and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices.</hi> Here obſerve, there was the recommendation of the King in the Caſe, juſt as now in <hi>Skinners,</hi> and this difference, that a queſtion of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom betwixt Lord and Tenants was properly determinable by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, and a Jury of the Viſenage, and this of a Treſpaſs in the <hi>Indies,</hi> to be puniſhed in Parliament, or no where: which juſtifies the Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings there.</p>
            <p>43. Eliz. <hi>the</hi> 18th <hi>of</hi> December, <hi>A Complaint was made to the Lords by the Company of Painters againſt the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Plaiſterers, for wrong done them in uſing ſome part of their Trade. Their Lordſhips referred it to the Lord Maior and Recorder of</hi> London, <hi>to be heard, examined, adjudged, and ordered by them:</hi> Which was all one as if they had done it themſelves: For it was done by their Authority and by their Order: Qui facit per alium, facit perſe.</p>
            <pb n="158" facs="tcp:152672:81"/>
            <p>18. Jac. <hi>The Lords took notice of the Proceeding of the Houſe of Commons in the Caſe of one</hi> Flood, <hi>whom they had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented before them for inſolent and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous words ſpoken by him againſt the Prince and Princeſs Palatine, examined Witneſſes, and given Judgment in the Cauſe; which they look'd upon as deeply trenching upon the Priviledges of their Houſe, all Judgments properly and ſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belonging to them. Thereupon they ſent a Meſſage to the Houſe of Commons and deſired a Conference; At which Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence the Commons confeſſed, That out of their Zeal they had cenſured</hi> Flood; <hi>But they left him now to their Lordſhips, and hoped their Lordſhips would cenſure him; In order to which they ſent up a Trunk of Writings concerning his Caſe: Then the Lords proceeded to the hearing of it, examined ſeveral Witneſſes, and heard all</hi> Flood <hi>could ſay for himſelf; which done, they adjudged him, Not to bear longer the Arms of a Gentleman, To ride with his face to the Horſe tayl, to ſtand upon the Pillory with his Ears nailed, to be whipped at a Carts tayl,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:152672:81"/>to be fined Five thouſand pounds, and to be impriſoned in</hi> Newgate <hi>during life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>21. Jac. Thomas Morley <hi>was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented before the Lords, for delivering a Scandalous Petition to the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons (as himſelf affirmed) againſt the Lord-Keeper</hi> Coventry. <hi>Upon examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it appeared, that it had not been preſented to the Houſe of Commons, only to their Committee of Grievances, &amp; that he had publiſhed very many Copies of it, even ſince his being convented before their Lordſhips, They adjudge him to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned in the</hi> Fleet, <hi>to pay</hi> 1000 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>Fine, to ſtand with his neck in the Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lory, to make his Submiſſion and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment at the Barr.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>22 Jac. Mary Brocas <hi>petitioned the Lords to be relieved for a Debt of</hi> 1000 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>due unto her by Bond from the Muſcovia Company. Upon hearing both ſides, their Lordſhips order the Company to pay the Debt, with</hi> 5 <abbr>l</abbr> per cent. <hi>Intereſt, out of the Leviations, which the ſaid Company had made among themſelves for the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Debts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſame Parliament,</hi> May 28. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:152672:82"/>Pynckney <hi>petitions the Houſe in the behalf of himſelf and other Creditors of Sir</hi> John Kennedy, <hi>to be relieved for Debts owing to them from Sir</hi> John, <hi>by the ſale of</hi> Barn-Elms, <hi>Lands in the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of his Heir</hi> John Kennedy. <hi>The Lords, upon examination of the buſineſs, find cauſe, and ſo they order it, That</hi> Barn Elms <hi>ſhould be ſold to the beſt value, and the Profits to be ſequeſtred in the mean time into indifferent hands; And that a Recognizance of</hi> 2000 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>in which</hi> Pinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney <hi>ſtood bound in Chancery ſhould be withdrawn and cancelled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſame Parliament again,</hi> Grizell Rogers <hi>Widow, petitions the Lords for the ſetling her Title to certain Lands in</hi> Heygrove <hi>in the County of</hi> Somerſet, <hi>and for quieting and ending divers Suits and Differences between her and Sir</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur Ingram, <hi>Sir</hi> William Whitmore, <hi>&amp;c. They order her Satisfaction out of particular Lands, And all Suits to ceaſe between them, And appointed Releaſes of all differences on both ſides to be drawn and ſealed.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="161" facs="tcp:152672:82"/>
            <p>4. Car. 31. Jan. <hi>The Lords Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees for Petitions make report to the Houſe of a Petition of</hi> Benjamin Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key <hi>againſt</hi> John Smith, <hi>in behalf of a Grammar-School at</hi> Wotton-Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edge <hi>in the County of</hi> Gloceſter, <hi>which School was endowed with great Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by the Widow of the Lord</hi> Berkly <hi>in</hi> Richard <hi>the</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">ds</hi> 
               <hi>time, which were now much abated and brought to an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>value by the cunning practices of the ſaid</hi> Smith. <hi>Upon which the Lords awarded a Commiſſion to iſſue out of the Chancery, to ſurvey all the ſaid Lands; And or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered alſo a ſpecial</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi>to be directed to the Warden of the</hi> Fleet (where <hi>Crokey</hi> was a Priſoner) <hi>to bring the Body of the ſaid</hi> Crokey <hi>before the Lord-Keeper, to the intent he might at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the ſaid Commiſſion; And ordered further, That if</hi> Crokey <hi>did make it appear the value of the Lands to be ſo as be ſaid, and that to be approved by the Lords Committees for Petitions, then</hi> Smith <hi>to repay to the ſaid</hi> Crokey <hi>ſuch Charges as he ſhall disburſe in the Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="162" facs="tcp:152672:83"/>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Parliament of</hi> 1640, Decemb. 16. <hi>Upon report from the Lords Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees for Petitions, That Miſtris</hi> James <hi>complained againſt Sir</hi> Edmond Saw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer <hi>for ſheltring himſelf under a Royal Protection which he had procured, by which means ſhe could not ſue him upon a Bond of</hi> 500 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>for ſo much Money bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed of her, and two years Intereſt, and ſo was debarred from helping her ſelf by any Legal courſe; The Lords ordered, that the ſaid Mris</hi> James <hi>ſhould proceed againſt the ſaid Sir</hi> Edmond Sawyer <hi>for the recovering of her Debt in any Court, where ſhe thought beſt, notwithſtanding his Protection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>December 21. <hi>The Lords Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees report a Petition of</hi> Katherine Hadley, <hi>complaining that ſhe had been kept a long time a Priſoner in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Gaol in the Old Bridewell, without any cauſe ſhewn; the Lords ordered her Releaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> 22th <hi>of</hi> Decemb. <hi>Upon a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port from the Lords Committees of Sir</hi> Robert Howard's <hi>Caſe, complaining, that he had been committed Cloſe-Priſoner
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:152672:83"/>to the</hi> Fleet <hi>by the High—Commiſſion Court, and kept there three months, till he was fain for his enlargement to enter into ſeveral Bonds with Sureties in the ſum of</hi> 3500 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>For which he deſired Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations, and his Bonds to be cancelled; The parties intereſſed were ſummoned and heard. And after due conſideration, the Lords ordered a thouſand pound dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to Sir</hi> Robert Howard, <hi>of which</hi> 500 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>to be paid by the Archbiſhop of</hi> Canterbury, 250 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>by Sir</hi> Hen. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, <hi>and</hi> 250 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>by Sir</hi> John Lambe, <hi>the Bonds to be forthwith cancelled, and delivered to Sir</hi> Robert Howard.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The 23d of</hi> Decemb. <hi>They reported the Caſe of</hi> William Dudley, <hi>that he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving arreſted the Lord</hi> Wentworth (<hi>ſon to the Earl of</hi> Cleveland) <hi>for a Debt of</hi> 400 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>entred a Caution in Mr. Juſtice</hi> Bartley's <hi>Chamber for good Bayl to be taken, yet Juſtice</hi> Bartley <hi>had releaſed the ſaid Lo.</hi> Wentworth <hi>upon ſuch Bayl, as the ſaid</hi> Dudley <hi>was utterly diſabled to recover his debt. Juſtice</hi> Bartley <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called, made no good Anſwer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. The Lords thereupon order, that
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:152672:84"/>the ſaid Juſtice</hi> Bertley <hi>ſhould forthwith aſſure unto the ſaid</hi> Dudley <hi>his Houſe and Land near</hi> Barnet, <hi>for ſecuring the ſaid Debt with Intereſt and Damages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſame day they report likewiſe the Caſe of Mris</hi> Mary Stanhope <hi>Widow, Daughter-in-law to the Earl of</hi> Cheſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field, <hi>complaining, that the ſaid Earle refuſed to aſſure unto her</hi> 40 <abbr>l</abbr> per An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num <hi>during her Widowhood, according to a former Agreement made between them, which appeared to be true by a Letter produced under the Earl's hand; And his counſel being heard, and no good cauſe ſhewn, why the Petitioner ſhould not be relieved: The Lords ordered the Earl of</hi> Cheſterfield <hi>forthwith to aſſure to the ſaid Mris</hi> Mary Stanhope, <hi>his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-in-law,</hi> 40 <abbr>l</abbr> per Annum <hi>during her Widdowhood, and to pay unto her ſuch money as was in arrear of the</hi> 40 <abbr>l</abbr> per Annum <hi>due to her for the ſpace of two years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The 30th of</hi> December, <hi>the Lords Committees for examining Abuſes in Courts of Juſtice, report the Complain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of</hi> John Turner, <hi>a Priſoner in the</hi> Gate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:152672:84"/>
               <hi>committed thither by the High-Commiſſion Court, where he had lain fourteen years, for refuſing to take the Oath</hi> Ex Officio: <hi>The Lords ordered him to be forthwith releaſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The 21th of</hi> January, <hi>the Committee for Petitions, report the Complaint of</hi> William Waters <hi>and</hi> Thomas Waters, <hi>How they had ſuffered much by an untrue and falſe Certificate, made by Dr.</hi> Clerk <hi>and Dr.</hi> Sibthorp <hi>unto the Counſel-Table, for their refuſing to pay Ship-money; whereby they were forced to pay the ſum of</hi> 34 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>for Fees: Upon which Dr.</hi> Clerk <hi>and Dr.</hi> Sibthorp <hi>were heard at large: The Lords ordered them to pay back the</hi> 34 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>to the Complainants, which they had paid for Fees, and</hi> 100 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>Damages; And to be turned out of the Commiſſion of the Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> 22th of January, <hi>the Committee for Courts of Juſtice reported the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of the Lady</hi> Frances Weld <hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>down, againſt the Archbiſhop of</hi> Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury <hi>and Mr.</hi> Dell, <hi>ſuggeſting, That ſhe had been much prejudiced by them in the recovering of a Debt of</hi> 1300 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>due
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:152672:85"/>to her upon Bond from Mr.</hi> Child: <hi>Upon hearing of all Parties, the Lords find the Archbp. and Mr.</hi> Dell <hi>free from blame, and order them to be diſcharged concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that buſineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 5th of February, <hi>the Committee reports the Complaint of</hi> Jeremy Powel, <hi>That the Biſhop of</hi> Hereford <hi>had admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Clerk to the Vicarage of</hi> Burknill <hi>in</hi> Shropſhire, <hi>though the ſaid</hi> Powel <hi>in the Right of himſelf and of</hi> Mary <hi>his Wife, had cauſed a</hi> Ne Admittas <hi>to be directed to the Biſhop. The Lords upon bearing the buſineſs, found, that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop had done contrary to Law, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ordered him to pay unto</hi> Powel, <hi>by way of Damages, the ſum of</hi> 30 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>And the ſaid</hi> Powel, <hi>as Patron, to be left in the ſame condition for tryal of his Right, as he was before the Biſhop had put a ſtop to his buſineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 9th of Febr. <hi>the Committee for Courts of Juſtice reports the Caſe of</hi> Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Bloxam, <hi>That</hi> Andrew Sande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>Clerk had procured a Sentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him in the High-Commiſſion Court, by vertue whereof the ſaid</hi> Sandeland
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:152672:85"/>
               <hi>had violently gained from him the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Rectory of</hi> Great Walding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field <hi>in the County of</hi> Suffolk. The <hi>Lords judging this proceeding of the High-Commiſſion to be moſt injurious and contrary to Law, ordered, That the Cauſe ſhould be left to a tryal at Law at the next Aſſizes for that County; That</hi> San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deland <hi>ſhould appear</hi> gratis, <hi>and plead,</hi> Not guilty, <hi>that ſo the Cauſe might come to a final Determination that Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſizes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſame day the ſame Committee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, That</hi> John Radway, William Newark, <hi>and</hi> Walter Cootes <hi>were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented</hi> Ex officio mero <hi>in the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Court of</hi> Gloceſter, <hi>and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Excommunicated for going to Church out of their own Pariſh, and upon pretence of a</hi> Significavit <hi>which was imperfect, were arreſted and caſt into Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, where they continued Eleven dayes, whereas there was no Writ juſtly taken out. The Lords Ordered that Dr.</hi> Baber <hi>Chancellor of</hi> Gloceſter <hi>ſhould pay to thoſe three perſons</hi> 40 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>for Damages, and the Underſheriffs Deputy</hi> Richard
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:152672:86"/>Byford 20. <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>upon the account of the Arreſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 23d of Febr. <hi>the ſame Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee report, That</hi> Abraham Hill, <hi>a poor aged man, was committed to Priſon in the year</hi> 1636, <hi>by</hi> Robert Buxton <hi>then Maior of</hi> Colcheſter, <hi>by verbal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand onely, without any Warrant, or Cauſe ſhewed, and continued a Priſoner ſixteen weeks, to his utter undoing: The Lords Ordered, that the ſaid</hi> Buxton <hi>ſhould pay unto him</hi> 16 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>by way of da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 5th of March, <hi>the Committee for Petitions inform the Houſe, that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint had been made before them, That</hi> Nicholas Haws <hi>Gent. an antient man, had not yet ſued out his Livery in the Court of wards, the Lords order him to do it without delay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 11th of March, <hi>the Committee for Petitions gives account to the Houſe, that according to their Lordſhips directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there had been a Tryal at the laſt Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſizes for</hi> Suffolk, <hi>between</hi> Bloxam <hi>and</hi> Sandeland, <hi>and that the Verdict had paſſed for</hi> Bloxam; <hi>whereupon the Lords
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:152672:86"/>Order, That</hi> Bloxam <hi>ſhould diſcharge the Cure as Lawful Incumbent. And that</hi> Sandeland <hi>ſhould deliver unto him the quiet Poſſeſſion of it.</hi> It is worthy Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, That the Lords, after they had referred the Deciſion of the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle for Matter of Fact, as to the forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Entry to the Common Law, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained ſtill Judges of the Cauſe, and their Judgement ſetled the Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond of</hi> April, 1641. <hi>The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee Reports, That</hi> Lambert Osbol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone <hi>Clerk, had complained of a Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in the</hi> Star-Chamber, <hi>by which he was degraded, and deprived of all his Spiritual Livings and Preferments, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Prebend of</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of</hi> Whethamſted, <hi>Fined in</hi> 5000 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>to the King, and adjudged to pay the like Sum for dammages to the Arch bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>and to be Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned; The Lords Order, That be ſhall be freed and diſcharged of his Fine, Dammages and Impriſonment, and be reſtored to his Prebendary and Parſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="170" facs="tcp:152672:87"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſixth of</hi> April, 41. <hi>The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee Reports, That the Lady</hi> Dyer <hi>had made her Complaint, That,</hi> primo Caroli, <hi>ſhe had lent Sir</hi> Richard Tichburn 400 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>upon Bond, and ſued it to a Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but Sir</hi> Robert Pye, <hi>Mr.</hi> But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, <hi>and others had extended all the Lands lyable to that Judgement at a far undervalue, to deprive her of all the benefit of it: The Lords Order, That Counſel of both ſides ſhould agree to draw up Aſſurances for ſetling the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all the Parties upon the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Extent, to be all Signed and Sealed by them, and that the Lady</hi> Dyer <hi>ſhould be firſt ſatisfied, and enjoy the Lands till then.</hi> One thing by the way is to be noted, That Sir <hi>Robert Pye</hi> was then a Member of the Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The twelfth of</hi> April, 41. <hi>The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee Reports a Complaint of Dr.</hi> Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, <hi>That Sir</hi> John Lamb <hi>had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly taken from him his Offices of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſary of</hi> Leiceſter, <hi>and of Official to the Archdeaconry there, which he injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Patent for life; That now Sir</hi>
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:152672:87"/>John Lamb <hi>took the Profits of them to himſelf, And had forced him by many Menaces and Oppreſſions to releaſe all Suits and Actions to his utter ruine and undoing, and to his Loſs and Dammage of above</hi> 1500 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>The Lords Order, That Sir</hi> John Lamb <hi>ſhould pay unto the ſaid Dr.</hi> Walker, <hi>by way of Dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, the ſum of</hi> 1500 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>to be levied upon his Lands and Chattels, ſhould be brought to the Bar as a Delinquent, and there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Reprebenſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The twelfth of</hi> June, 41. <hi>The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee Reports a Complaint of</hi> Edward Bagſhaw, <hi>his Brother</hi> Henry, <hi>and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> Mary <hi>and</hi> Margaret, <hi>againſt their Brother</hi> Thomas, <hi>concerning Portions and Annuities given them by their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Will: That all parties have been heard, and their Witneſſes. Upon hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the State of the Matter, The Lords Order</hi> Thomas <hi>to put in Security with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in four dayes for the payment of the Portions according to the Will; And to give ſecurity by Land for the paying of an Annuity of</hi> 20 <abbr>l</abbr> per annum <hi>to</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>for term of his life; That then the
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:152672:88"/>ſaid</hi> Edward <hi>ſhall releaſe by a Fine to the ſaid</hi> Thomas, <hi>all his Eſtate, Right, Title and Intereſt in the Lands and Goods of his Father deceaſed: And that a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of</hi> 1600 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>entred into by the ſaid</hi> Thomas Bagſhaw <hi>to</hi> John Gell, <abbr>
                  <hi>Eſq</hi>
               </abbr> 
               <hi>ſhall be diſcharged and made void; And that</hi> Thomas Bagſhaw <hi>ſhall make a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe to the ſaid</hi> Edward <hi>of all Debts and Demands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſixteenth of</hi> June, 41. <hi>The Lord</hi> Audley <hi>Complains by Petition, That the Lord</hi> Cottington <hi>kept from him the Mannor of</hi> Fonthill, <hi>and prayed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief therein: Upon hearing Counſel on both ſides, the Lords diſmiſſed the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The twenty third of</hi> June, 41. <hi>The Committee for Petitions, Reports, That Miſtris</hi> Walter <hi>had preferred a Petition ſetting forth, That</hi> William Walter <hi>her Husband will not permit her to cohabit and dwell with him, nor allow to her and three Children any thing for their ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port. The Lords Order her to repair to her Husband, and offer to live with him, and if he ſhall refuſe to admit her, that
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:152672:88"/>then he ſhall allow her</hi> 60 <abbr>l</abbr> per annum, <hi>for her Maintenance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> 21 th <hi>of</hi> July 41. <hi>A Petition was exhibited before the Lords by ſundry Officers and Clerks of the Court of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Pleas, ſhewing, That the diſpoſing of the Offices of Protonotaries, Phiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers, Exigenters, and other Offices of the ſaid Court, had time out of mind be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to the Chief Juſtice of that Court for the time being, but ſeveral Grants and Patents had been obtained from his Majeſty for the diſpoſing of the ſaid Offices, and therefore they prayed, That all thoſe Grants, and Letters Patents might be recalled, The Lords heard Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel upon it, and after mature deliberation declared, That the ſaid Offices do of Right belong to the diſpoſition of the Lord Chief Juſtice of the Common Pleas, And the Grants formerly made by Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents of the ſaid Offices to be Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal, and void, And Ordered the ſaid Patents to be brought into the Houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is likewiſe in the Journal Book of that Parliament, mention made of a Petition of one</hi> Thomas Smithick, <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:152672:89"/>the tenth of</hi> June, 1641. <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of wrongs ſuſtained from the Eaſt India Company, and likewiſe of a Petition from the Eaſt India Company, full of Reſpect and Submiſſion to the Houſe of Lords, and praying a longer day (then it ſeems was appointed) for hearing the Merits of the Cauſe, which the Lords granted, and Ordered all ſuch Books, Certificates, and Writings as were in the Cuſtody of the Company con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that buſineſs, ſhould be produced, and</hi> Smithick <hi>to peruſe and take Copies of them.</hi> What was more done upon this Petition of <hi>Smithicks,</hi> appears not by the Journal Book, probable they compounded the buſineſs among themſelves. But however it is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable the different Spirits of the Eaſt India Company then and of this now, The Modeſty of that, and the Carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of this ſo far differing. In thoſe times no queſtion was made of the Power of the Lords in point of their Judicature, nor no Complaint againſt their practice of it. Yet we ſee the frequency of it, in Cauſes of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:152672:89" rendition="simple:additions"/>Criminal, Civil, Mixt, between King and Subject, between Subject and Subject; no Protection, no Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge did exempt any body from their Juriſdiction.</p>
            <p>The Lords at the Conference (as they ſaid to the Gentlemen of the Houſe of Commons) were the more Copious in the enumeration of theſe later Preſidents, eſpecially thoſe of 1640, and 1641. not that they thought themſelves at all to ſtand in need of them, the antient ones before produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſhewing the uſage all along from the very firſt and beſt times, which in their Lordſhips Opinions were of much more weight, &amp; ſufficiently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing, but the Houſe of Commons having a little before at an other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference delivered it for a Maxim, <hi>That the later Preſidents were beſt,</hi> and having accordingly inſiſted upon one ſingle Preſident of the ſame Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of 1640. to Oblidge the Houſe of Lords to commit a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon upon a general Impeachment of Treaſon, without ſpecial Matter
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:152672:90" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhewn, and oppoſing that one Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident to what their Lordſhips al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged to the contrary, and made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to have been the uſage of all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times; no Record being, of any Man ever ſent to Priſon by the Houſe of Peers without a particular Crime expreſſed in the Impeachment of ſome Act done by him, before the Earl of Strafford, which was the Preſident ſtood upon. This made the Lords heap up ſo many Examples of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of their Houſe in that Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of 1640. in the point of Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature, to uſe it, as <hi>Argumentum ad heminem,</hi> and what the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons could no wayes except againſt, themſelves having declared it to be of greateſt Authority.</p>
            <p>Until <hi>Henry</hi> the Eights time, the very Houſe of Commons was to be beholding to the Houſe of Lords for their Adminiſtration of Juſtice even concerning their Members; as the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Judges and Conſervators of their Liberties and Priviledges. Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves could not before that have pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:152672:90"/>any one, that had never ſo much offended them: So far were they from exerciſing a Power of Commitment, or of inflicting any puniſhment for Crimes at large and againſt the Laws of the Land, where neither the Offence nor the Offender had particular rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to their Houſe, as in theſe later times hath been often practiſed by them. But (as I ſay) the firſt time that ever they puniſhed any, (and it was for breach of Priviledge) was in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament 34 <hi>H.</hi> 8. in the Caſe of <hi>George Ferrers,</hi> Burgeſs for <hi>Plimouth, who was arreſted and put in the</hi> Counter; <hi>The Houſe informed of it, ſent their Serjeant to demand their Member</hi> (not ſo much as to ſummon Sheriff, or Bayliff that made the Arreſt, or Party at whoſe ſuit it was made, and leſs to bring any of them as Delinquents to the Bar, as now a dayes) <hi>nor could they obtain that; But their Serjeant coming to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, found reſiſtance, the top of his Mace was broken off, his Man knocked down, and he glad to get off without the Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; So back he comes to the Houſe yet
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:152672:91"/>ſitting, and makes his Complaint; They preſently all riſe with their Speaker, come up to the Houſe of Lords, and the Speaker makes the Complaint to Sir</hi> Thomas Audley <hi>Lord Chancellor ſitting on the Wooll-ſack. The Lords judge the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to be very great, and refer the puniſhment of it to the Order of the Houſe of Commons. Then indeed they return to their Houſe, and ſend for the Sheriff of</hi> London, <hi>the Clerks of the</hi> Counter, <hi>all the Officers there that had a part in the fray with their Serjeant, one</hi> White <hi>at whoſe Sute</hi> Ferrers <hi>was Arreſted, and the Bayliffs that did Arreſt him, all to appear perſonally before them at eight of the Clock next Morning; and when they came, they ſent ſome of them to the</hi> Tower, <hi>ſome to</hi> Newgate, <hi>where they continued till they were delivered at the ſuite of the Lord Major.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We do not find that before this the Houſe of Commons committed any body, no not for the Breach of their Priviledges: nor were themſelves ſo much as Judges of the Elections of their Members, but were fain to come
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:152672:91"/>up to the Lords, and pray their aid to redreſs what was amiſs, and puniſh thoſe that had offended: All the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents ſhew it ſo to have been, and not one, no not one to the contrary.</p>
            <p>5. H. 4. n. 74. <hi>The Commons Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That all ſuch Perſons as ſhall Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt any Knight or Burgeſs of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, or any of their Servants, and know them ſo to be, do Fine at the Kings Will, and render treble Damages to the Party grieved. The Anſwer is, There is ſufficient remedy for the Cauſe;</hi> Which remedy it ſeems was, <hi>That the King and Lords would ſet them at Liberty,</hi> which was as they conceived ſufficient. For,</p>
            <p>8. H. 6. n. 57. <hi>Among the Petitions of the Commons, one is, That</hi> William Lake <hi>Servant to</hi> William Mildred <hi>Burges for</hi> London, <hi>was Arreſted and carried to the</hi> Fleet <hi>upon an Execution, and they pray he may be delivered ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Priviledge of their Houſe, It is granted, but withal, Authority is given to the Chancellor, to commiſſionate Perſons to apprehend him again after the Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="180" facs="tcp:152672:92"/>
            <p>39. H. 6. n. 9. <hi>The Commons com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain by Petition to the King and Lords, That</hi> Walter Clerck <hi>one of their Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, Burgeſs for</hi> Chippenham <hi>in</hi> Wilts, <hi>had been Outlawed, and put in Priſon, and pray, That by the Aſſent of the King and Lords he may be releaſed; Which was granted, and their Member ſet at Liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>14. E. 4. n. 55. <hi>The Commons among their Petitions bring up one of a Member of theirs</hi> William Hide <hi>Burgeſs likewiſe for</hi> Chippenham, <hi>being taken in Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oution for Debt, and a Priſoner in the Kings Bench, praying he may be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a Writ of Priviledge out of the</hi> Chancery, <hi>the which is granted, with this ſaving, That bis Creditors may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue their Execution after the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>17. E. 4. n. 36. <hi>At the Petition alſo of the Commons, the King with the Aſſent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal grants, That</hi> John <hi>at Will Burgeſs for</hi> Exceter <hi>condemned in the</hi> Exchequer <hi>during the Parliament upon eight ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Informations, at the Sute of</hi> John
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:152672:92"/>Taylor <hi>of the ſame Town, ſhall have as many Superſedeas therefore as he will, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til his coming home after the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One memorable Caſe of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture muſt not be omitted, which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned 31. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>n.</hi> 25, 26. &amp;<hi>c.</hi> Thomas Thorp <hi>Chief Baron was Speaker of the Houſe of Commons, and in an Interval of Parliament) the Parliament being upon a Prorogation,) he had been Arreſted, and carried to Priſon at the Duke of</hi> York'<hi>s Sute, who had got a Judgement againſt him in the</hi> Exchequer <hi>upon an Action of Treſpaſs, for carrying away the Dukes Goods from</hi> Durham-Houſe; <hi>The Parliament meeting, the Houſe of Commons ſend up ſome of their Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to make Complaint to the King and Lords, That their Speaker was a Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and deſire his Releaſe. The Duke of</hi> York <hi>gives the Lords an account of the buſineſs. They ask the Judges Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in the Point; The Judges Anſwer was in theſe words, It hath not been uſed before time, nor becomes it us, to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine matters concerning the High Court
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:152672:93"/>of Parliament, which is ſo high and mighty in its Nature, that it is Judge of the Law, and makes that to be Law, which is not Law, and that to be no Law, which is; And the Determination of its Priviledges belongs to the Lords in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and not to Juſtices: But to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the Uſe in Lower Courts, they ſaid, That as Writs of Superſedens of Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Parliament were brought unto them concerning any particular Member of Parliament, who had been Arreſted, ſo it were not for Treaſon, Felony, Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Peace, or for a Condemnation before Parliament, they did alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe him, that be might freely attend the Parliament: After which Anſwer made, It was by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal agreed, aſſented and concluded, That the ſaid</hi> Thorp <hi>ſhould remain in Priſon notwithſtanding his being Speaker of the Houſe of Commons, or any other Priviledge of Parliament. And they Ordered the ſame to be declared unto them, that were come from the Commons by</hi> Walter Moyle <hi>a Serjeant at Law, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was Matter of Law; but in the
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:152672:93"/>preſence of the Biſhop of</hi> Ely, <hi>and many other Lords; And then the Biſhop of</hi> Ely <hi>was to charge them in the Kings Name to chuſe an other Speaker: This was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly performed: And the Houſe of Commons did chuſe an other Speaker (Sir</hi> Thomas Charleton) <hi>in the place of</hi> Thomas Thorp, <hi>and ſent ſome Members to acquaint the Lords with it; and the Lord Chancellor anſwered,</hi> The King likes him well; It is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, That the King lay then ſick at <hi>Windſor,</hi> and yet all is done in the Kings Name, as if he had been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
            <p>Theſe Preſidents ſhew, That the Houſe of Commons did not in thoſe times exerciſe any Juriſdiction, nor themſelves lay any puniſhment upon thoſe that broke their Priviledges, and that the Sheriffs and Bayliffs of <hi>London</hi> in that Parliament of 34. <hi>H.</hi> 8. were the firſt, who felt any effects of their Juſtice in that kind. Nor after that, did they conſtantly put that Power in Execution, and for ſome time it ſeems they abſolutely waved
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:152672:94"/>it; For the very next year, the 35th of <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>One</hi> Trewinnard <hi>a Burgeſs for</hi> Cornewall <hi>had been impriſoned at the ſuite of one</hi> Skewis, <hi>and was delivered onely by a Writ of Priviledge, (But</hi> Skewis <hi>not ſent for by the Serjeant at Arms to be committed and puniſhed by the Houſe, as the uſe is now) So far from that, That the Executors of</hi> Skewis <hi>in the Trinity term of the</hi> 36th <hi>of</hi> H. 8. <hi>brought their Action of Debt againſt</hi> Chamond <hi>the Sheriff of</hi> Cornewall <hi>for the Eſcape, but were caſt in their Sute, and the Priviledge allowed, as</hi> Dyer <hi>mentions it in his Reports,</hi> p. 59. <hi>And in the</hi> 18th <hi>of Queen</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of one Mr.</hi> Hall <hi>a Member of the Houſe being Arreſted upon Complaint made to the Houſe, it was referred to a Committee to conſider of the Buſineſs, and how he ſhould be releaſed, who made their Report, That it could be only by a Writ of Priviledge, as appears by the Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of that Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And there is ſome reaſon to believe, That they never or very rarely ſent for by their Serjeant, or medled with
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:152672:94"/>the Perſons of ſuch as broke their Priviledges by arreſting or miſuſing their Servants and Attendants, till 43. <hi>Eliz.</hi> For I find in a Journal of that Parliament (which I have by me) <hi>That a Complaint being made to the Houſe, How a Servant of one Mr.</hi> Cooke, <hi>a Member of the Houſe, was arreſted, that Preſident was urged of the</hi> 34th <hi>of</hi> H. 8. <hi>And it was ſaid, that the Houſe had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Sheriffs of</hi> London <hi>and the Bayliffs, for abuſing their Serjeant, and for arreſting of</hi> Ferrers: <hi>Whereupon it was then reſolved and ordered, That the Serjeant attending the Houſe ſhould go to</hi> Newgate, <hi>and bring away both the Priſoner and his Keeper; and likewiſe command the Bayliff who made the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and the Perſon at whoſe ſuit it was made, to appear before the Houſe. This was done, the Priſoner diſcharged, and the Bayliff, and he who procured the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, brought to the Bar, and upon their humble ſumbmiſſion pardoned, with a check from the Speaker, and paying their Fees.</hi> Three Preſidents only there are, which Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> produces, of their
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:152672:95"/>exerciſing a Judicature, two of them upon their own Members for Miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, &amp; the third upon one no Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber for ſtriking a Member, this <hi>primo Mariae,</hi> the other 8. <hi>Eliz.</hi> &amp; 23. But they did not conſtantly nor fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently do that neither, that is, not judge and puniſh either their own Members for any Offence, whether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Houſe or out of the Houſe, or any other for arreſting or aſſaulting them, till after Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time. For in the 27th of her Reign, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the Journal of that Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>A Member of the Houſe having been ſerved with a Sub-poena, the Houſe ſent to the Lord Keeper, and ſignified unto him, That it was againſt their Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge. The Lord Keeper returned an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That he ſhould not ſubmit to any Opinion of the Houſe concerning their Priviledges, except thoſe Priviledges were allowed in</hi> Chancery, <hi>and would not recal the Sub-poena.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So in Matters of Elections, they were glad to pray the aid of the Houſe of Peers upon any Miſcarriage or
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:152672:95"/>Neglect of the Sheriffs; as in the 18th H. 6. n. 18. <hi>The Sheriff of</hi> Cambridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire (Gilbert Hore) <hi>had made no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of the Knights for the County: up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Complaint made to the Houſe of Peers, it was Ordered,</hi> That <hi>he ſhould go to a New Election, and make Proclamation, That no Perſon ſhould come armed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Any of the Members to be diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of their Attendance in the Houſe, come to the King and Lords for it. <hi>So did Sir</hi> Philip Courtney <hi>Knight for</hi> Devonſhire 16. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>n.</hi> 6. <hi>who being accuſed of ſome hainous Matter, comes to the King in Parliament,</hi> (for the King did then ordinarily ſit in Perſon in the Houſe of Peers) <hi>and prayes to be diſcharged his Attendance, until he was purged, which was granted; This was upon the Wedneſday, and the Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day after at the Requeſt of the Commons, he is reſtored to his place in their Houſe, and to his good Name, for that he had ſubmitted himſelf to reaſonable Arbitre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſaith the Record.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this is ſaid with great Reſpect to
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:152672:96" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Houſe of Commons, and not any wayes to impugn or queſtion their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Juriſdiction upon their Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and for the defence of their Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, but only to ſhew how things were in the beginning, and how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſive the Power of the Houſe of Peers hath ever been in their Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, reaching all Crimes, all Perſons, all Places, none exempt: And how neceſſary it is, it ſhould be ſo, That there be not a failer of Juſtice in the Land, that no Offender may eſcape unpuniſhed, and no oppreſſed Perſon go unrelieved; All other Courts ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their Bounds and Limits, which make them too narrow for ſome Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: And this truſt being in the Houſe of Peers, there is remedy in thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Caſes.</p>
            <p>But before I wind up all to a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, a word muſt be ſaid to anſwer ſome Objections, which I have met with in a Book intituled the <hi>Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners Liberty,</hi> printed in the year 1648. The firſt Objection is an Order of the Houſe of Peers with the Kings Aſſent
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:152672:96" rendition="simple:additions"/>to it 4. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 6. <hi>by which the King and Lords declare an Agreement made betwixt them, That the Lords ſhall not be held nor charged to give Judgment on others but their Peers; And that the Judgements then given ſhall not be drawn into Conſequence, to oblige the Peers in time to come, to judge other then their Peers againſt the Law of the Land:</hi> This the Author of the Book will have to be an Act of Parliament, becauſe it is ſaid to be done in full Parliament: To which I anſwer, The Record it ſelf ſhews it to be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, The Title is, <hi>Concordia ne tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur in Conſequentiam;</hi> That is, an Agreement an Accord between Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that what is done ſhall not be drawn into Conſequence, no Law to impoſe upon them, and to oblige them; And the expreſſion, That it was done in full Parliament, and ſo the Commons preſent; ſignifies no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, as to inforce what he would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer upon it. For admit that, yet it makes it not a Law, the Commons might be Witneſſes to what was done,
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:152672:97" rendition="simple:additions"/>but were no Parties; Which muſt have been to make it a Law. They muſt either have Petitioned for it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or have given their Aſſent and Approbation after; it muſt either have begun or ended in their Houſe, before it had gone to the King for his Royal Aſſent, and then it had been binding and the Law of the Land; but there was no ſuch thing here. The Occaſion of it was this, The King had prevailed with the Lords, againſt their Wills and Proteſtations to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as appears by the Record of that Parliament, <hi>n.</hi> 2. even in a Manner forced them, to condemn the Earl of <hi>March,</hi> Sir <hi>Simon de Beresford, John Matrevers, Bogo de Bayons, John De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varal, Thomas de Gourney,</hi> and <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> of <hi>Ogle,</hi> for the murther of <hi>Edward</hi> the Second, and the death of the Earl of <hi>Kent,</hi> all of them Commoners, except the Earl of <hi>March,</hi> and none of them called to anſwer, yet ſome of them in hold, and others not; Thoſe that were in hold were preſently exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, and great rewards promiſed to
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:152672:97" rendition="simple:additions"/>who ſhould bring in the reſt, quick or dead. The Lords afterwards troubled in Conſcience at what they had done, and moved with juſt indignation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt themſelves, made firſt a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation, <hi>That they would not for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be</hi> Tenus &amp; Chargez a rendre Jugement ſur autre que ſur leurs Pairs, <hi>be tyed and charged to judge any but their Peers;</hi> and this they get the King to conſent unto, and happily for the more Solemnity of the buſineſs, would have the King declare ſo much before the Commons; And their Indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, together with their Precaution not to be again neceſſitated to do the like, might carry them further to ſay, They would not be obliged to judge any but Peers againſt the Law of the Land; though it will very well bear an other Conſtruction, that it was their being in that Manner forced and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to do, what otherwiſe they would not have done, which they declared to be againſt the Law of the Land, becauſe it is againſt the Freedom of Parliaments; and not their Judging of
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:152672:98" rendition="simple:additions"/>Commoners to be againſt the Law of the Land. But admit it, thoſe Lords then thought it to be ſo, and that they ought not to judge any but their Peers; Doth that bind up the Houſe of Peers, that they may never be of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother mind? They are ſtill Maſters of their own Orders, and alter them and change them as they think good. And I look upon this Order, as no other, nor of no more force, then that made 8. <hi>E.</hi> 1. which is in the Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix to the <hi>Placita Parliamentaria,</hi> p. 442. concerning Petitions, which I have mentioned before, and which ſucceeding Parliaments would not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve. And that they did not obſerve this neither, of their not Judging Commoners, is apparently proved by the conſtant practice of the Houſe of Peers in all ſucceeding times. And one thing more would be taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of in the Proceedings of the Houſe of Peers at that time, after their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitate and Illegal Condemnation of thoſe Perſons, without ever calling them to anſwer; The Earl of <hi>March</hi>
               <pb n="193" facs="tcp:152672:98" rendition="simple:additions"/>a Peer of the Realm, was condemned and executed as well as the Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and this was looked upon as a Preſident of ill Conſequence for the Peerage, and therefore they would have a Law to prevent it, and <hi>that the Nobles of the Land ſhould not be put to anſwer but in open Parliament by their Peers,</hi> which they long endeavoured before they could obtain it: So as in 15. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 6. they adjourned the Parliament ſeverall dayes upon that point, and at laſt appointed four Earls, four Biſhops, four Barons to draw it up into form, and got it paſſed into an Act; but two years after the King got that Act to be repealed: And ſo far they likewiſe took care of Commoners in that Parliament of 15. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. as to have it enacted alſo, <hi>That no man ſhould be impeached by Commandment, without proceſs of Law.</hi> Theſe were Acts of Parliament and Laws which did bind, but the other of their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing none but Peers was a meer parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Order of the Houſe, an Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment betwixt the King &amp; them, which
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:152672:99"/>was no wayes binding to poſterity, and alterable ſtill at pleaſure by the ſame Houſe that made it.</p>
            <p>Another Battery raiſed by that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor againſt the Juriſdiction of the Houſe of Peers, is from the Statute of Appeals 1 <hi>H.</hi> 4. c. 14. And with that he would overthrow the force of that Preſident of <hi>John Hall,</hi> condemned by the Lords in that firſt year of <hi>H.</hi> 4. for the death of the Duke of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> in the 21 of <hi>R.</hi> 2. as if that power were now taken from them by that Act, and that the Commons by it had taken care, it ſhould not be ſo done by them any more, for ſo he ſaith p. 23. Which by his leave concerns nothing the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings againſt <hi>Hall,</hi> and will leſs (I may ſay) concern the preſent queſtion of the proceedings of this Houſe of Lords in the Caſe of <hi>Skinner:</hi> For that Statute provides only for Tryall of Appeals, where a private perſon next of kin is or ſhall be proſecutor, which was not in <hi>Halls</hi> Caſe, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution being in the ordinary way at the Kings ſuit: It is true, that in the
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:152672:99"/>21 of <hi>R.</hi> 2. an horrible abuſe had been in point of Appeals: Certain Lords, not by Law capable of it, taking upon them to be Appellants, and in their own Names acouſing in Parliament ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral perſons, Peers of the Realm and Commoners, of divers Treaſons and Murthers, making themſelves Judges and Parties, and condemning them to die, without, nay againſt, all forms of Law, &amp; rules of Juſtice, by w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> means many innocent men loſt both lives and Eſtates. This it is that is provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for by that Statute, and care taken it ſhall be ſo no more; not the Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry proſecution of Offenders in the Kings Name, as <hi>Halls</hi> was; Though one particular in that Tryal is confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to have been moſt Irregular and Illegal, which was examining him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelf upon Oath, but that is not material to the point in queſtion, which is, Whether the Statute of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals forbids ſuch Tryals, as aſſuredly it doth not, nor any of thoſe former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſtanced in to have paſt in the Houſe of Peers; And leaſt of all can
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:152672:100"/>it concern the late Proceedings in the buſineſs of <hi>Skinner</hi> and the Eaſt India Company, in which there is no charge either of Treaſon or Felony, where an Appeal onely can take place, to bring it within that Statute.</p>
            <p>In the ſame 23d page, an other Argument is uſed againſt this Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of the Peers, in which that Author hath certainly miſſed his Mark, for nothing could be produced, that makes more for that Juriſdiction: He ſaith That the Subject of <hi>England</hi> hath moderated Parlaments, and by expreſs words determined, <hi>that ſome things cannot be done in Parliament, as that any ſhould be impeached there of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns his Francktenement or Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and vouches for his Authority, <hi>Rot. Parl.</hi> 10. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>n.</hi> 35. where in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there is ſuch a deſire of the Houſe of Commons, <hi>That none ſhall be compelled to anſwer in Parliament concerning his Francktenement.</hi> But let him tell us, how they ſped with their deſire, if their Petition was granted, to make it a Law and binding: Far from
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:152672:100" rendition="simple:additions"/>it; The Anſwer is, <hi>Le Roy ſaduiſera,</hi> The King will adviſe, which in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Language is a flat Denyal; So then no alteration was made of what was formerly the Uſage and Power of Parliament, but all conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued as it was before; And that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they did in Parliament try and judge ſuch matters, is apparent by the deſire of the Commons, that it ſhould not be ſo hereafter; for if no ſuch thing was, their deſire, it ſhould be no more ſo, was ridiculous; but it was ſo it ſeems, and their deſire that it ſhould be altered being rejected, leaves it in the ſame ſtate it was, that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment might continue ſtill to do it.</p>
            <p>And by the Parliament in theſe Caſes is to be underſtood onely the Houſe of Peers, for there ſingly lies the Judicial Power, as is confeſſed and acknowledged by the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons themſelves, 1. <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>n.</hi> 79. (ſo it is in the Record, but in the Exact A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgment it is <hi>n.</hi> 80.) <hi>That all Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments appertain to the King and Lords, and not to them, but when out of
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:152672:101" rendition="simple:additions"/>eſpecial grace ſome are communicated unto them, and therefore they there de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, that the Records may be ſo entred, as they may not be made Parties to them;</hi> So careful they were then not to ſeem to encroach upon that Power. And whereas the Author of that Pamphlet would make a difference upon the Perſonal preſence of the King in thoſe times in the Houſe of Lords, <hi>That though they might do it then in ſome Caſes, it followed not, the Lords might do it alone the King not there,</hi> it is but a fancy of his, making a difference, where in truth there is none. I have proved it before, that the Court is the ſame, be the King preſent or abſent; The King in Perſon can judge no man, nor diſpoſe of no mans Life or Eſtate, therefore it is a Maxim, <hi>That the King can do no wrong;</hi> the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe he of himſelf and by his own particular and perſonal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority can give away no mans Right, no not any ones pretended Right, where a man hath only a poſſeſſion, though without right, the King a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:152672:101"/>
               <hi>in propria Perſona</hi> can give no Rule in it, but it muſt be tryed in one of his Courts; And his Judges and Miniſters (whom he intruſts with his Regal Power, that with which he is himſelf inveſted in his Politick Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, and which he conveys to them, making them thereby the Diſpenſers of his Royal Juſtice unto all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,) they muſt be the Perſons that do the wrong, if any be done, It is <hi>Curia Regis</hi> that doth it, and not the King, though he ſit in Court in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; And ſo the ſtile is <hi>Videtur Curioe;</hi> And the Pleas Commonly end with this Declaration of the Party, <hi>Hoc paratus ſum Verificare pro at Curia or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaverit;</hi> and when mention is of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing done contrary to the formes of proceeding, <hi>Non ſic in Curia iſta uſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatum eſt,</hi> is the expreſſion; as it is in the Preſident of the 18. <hi>E.</hi> 1. ſo much inſiſted upon by the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. So hath it been in all times the Authority of the Court, to which the Law requires obedience; When <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the third would have his Brother
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:152672:102"/>
               <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>Cornewall</hi> confirm the grant of a Mannor to one <hi>Waleran</hi> a <hi>Germain</hi> (to whom King <hi>John</hi> had given it, and which the Duke of <hi>Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall</hi> ſaid belonged to his Dutchy of <hi>Cornwall,</hi> and had therefore taken poſſeſſion of it) his Anſwer was, <hi>That he was willing Curioe Regioe ſubire Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicium &amp; Magnatum Regni,</hi> that was to ſay, the Judgment of his Peers in Parliament: and when the King ſaid angrily to him, He ſhould then quit the Kingdom, it he would not deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver up the Mannor; his reply (as <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> Records it) was, <hi>Quod nec Walerano Jus ſuum redderet, nec ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Judicio Parium fourum e Regno exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret;</hi> He would neither quit his Right nor the Kingdom, but by the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Peers: Such difference was then made betwixt the Kings Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Command, and an Order of the Houſe of Peers in diſpoſing of mens Rights, which makes it very apparent, That the Kings Perſonal preſence could not add any thing to, or make any alteration in, the Juriſdiction of
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:152672:102" rendition="simple:additions"/>any Court. But enough of this; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially conſidering what is ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore upon the ſame Subject.</p>
            <p>Some other Evaſions I find in that Book to elude the Lords Judicature, and take off the force of ſome Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents which have been cited in main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of it, which I think are but evaſions, and work no great effect. As that of the Baniſhment of <hi>Alice Perrers</hi> or <hi>Pierce,</hi> which that Author will prove to have riſen from the Commons, and to have been at their Petition; becauſe <hi>Walſingham</hi> a Cloi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered Monk ſaith ſo, contrary to the Record in the Tower, where he finds no ſuch thing, where certainly it would not have been omitted, had it been ſo, that being ſo eſſential a part of a Tranſaction of Parlament, that it could not have been left out by the Clerk in the Journal Book; And whereas to fortifie <hi>Walſingham</hi>'s Teſtimony, he ſaith he then lived, as if he had been <hi>Teſtis Ocularis,</hi> I doubt much if he was then born, or ſo young he muſt have been, that he could little take
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:152672:103"/>notice of the paſſages of the time, for <hi>Baloeus</hi> in his Book <hi>De Scriptoribus Britanicis,</hi> ſaith he flouriſhed in the year 1440. under <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth; when he died we know not, but had he died then, or ſoon after, he muſt have been ſixty three years old, if ſo be he was in the World when <hi>Alice Pierce</hi> was baniſhed; for the Judgement of <hi>Alice Pierce</hi> was the firſt year of <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> the ſecond, which was in 1377. So as what he writes could be but by hearſay. Which is obſerved by me, onely to ſhew what weak proofs that Author brings to make good his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions, and ſhews the badneſs of his Cauſe; Not that I think it at all mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial to the point in queſtion, whether or no it was at the requeſt of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, that <hi>Alice Pierce</hi> was judged by the Lords, which would not at all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince what he would infer upon it, that the Houſe of Lords hath not of it ſelf Cogniſance of the Cauſe of a Commoner, nor can judge him for an Offence, whether Capital or of a leſſer Nature, but that the Houſe of
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:152672:103"/>Commons, making it their deſire, qualifies them for it: Which is a ſtrong Argument of the contrary, and proves that the Houſe of Commons doth thereby acknowledge their Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: For ridiculous it were to think, That any Act of that Houſe could create a new Power in the Houſe of Lords, which it had not in it ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and which afterwards muſt ceaſe, till it pleaſe the Houſe of Commons to give again a new life and being to it: As if the Houſe of Lords were but a Property, which cannot move of it ſelf, to have the Verſe ſaid of it, <hi>Ducitur ut nervis alienis mobile lignum.</hi> I am ſure it hath not been ſo hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, nor do I think the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons will own that Authors Opinion. And ſo the Judgment of <hi>Hall</hi> for the death of the Duke of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> that too forſooth muſt be at the requeſt of the Commons, and ſo be an Act of Parliament, and the proof for it is, that at the end of the Roll they thank the King for his juſt Judgment. But if the Gentleman would have peruſed
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:152672:104" rendition="simple:additions"/>the whole Roll, he would eaſily have been ſatisfied, that the thanks of the Commons related not to <hi>Halls</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, but to the proceedings of the King and Houſe of Peers againſt Sir <hi>William le Scroop,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Green,</hi> and Sir <hi>John Buſſy,</hi> who had been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive for <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, and were looked upon as principal Authors of the Miſcarriage of his Reign: For at the requeſt of the Commons, the Lords confirmed a Judgment former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given againſt them in ſome of the Kings Courts, (not in Parliament) and the King declaring, That though he took the forfeiture of their Eſtates ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Sentence given upon them, yet he underſtood not, there ſhould be by it any Infringement of the Statute, which ſaid, <hi>That no mans Eſtate ſhould be forfeited after his death, who had not been convicted whilſt living,</hi> for theſe perſons he ſaid had been ſo convicted; Whereupon the Commons thanked the King for his righteous Judgment, and thanked God for gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them ſuch a King: This had no
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:152672:104"/>relation at all to the buſineſs of <hi>Hall;</hi> And in the Record it is an Article by it ſelf of what had paſſed in Parliament another day. So for the proceeding againſt <hi>Gomeniz</hi> and <hi>Weſton,</hi> that too muſt be at the requeſt of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and conſequently an Act of Parliament; Whereas the Commons had onely in general deſired, that all ſuch as had delivered up any of the Kings Forts and Caſtles unduely, might be called to account for it in that Parliament, and be puniſhed for it according to their demerit by the Judgment of the Lords, who thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on commanded the Lievtenant of the Tower to bring before them thoſe two, who were already in hold for their ſeveral Facts in that kind, whom they tryed and condemned, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded likewiſe againſt ſeveral others, as <hi>Creſſingham, Spikeſworth, Trevit,</hi> and many more guilty of the ſame Crime, whom they convented before them; and Sentenced, ſome to death, ſome to other puniſhments according to the Quality of their Offence: Now,
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:152672:105"/>I do ask if in common ſence it can be conſtrued, that the Commons were at all Parties in the proſecution of theſe ſeveral Offenders: But admit, they had particularly impeached every one of them (which is more, then to deſire ſuch a Delinquent may be brought to his Tryal, and that the Lords would do Juſtice on him as they find Cauſe, and much more, then onely to deſign the Crime, and leave it to the Lords to find out the Perſons; For in an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment they examine the matter, and firſt find themſelves the Party to be guilty, and then they follow it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and prove him ſo, before the Lords) Doth this at all give them any part in the Judgment? or muſt it not neceſſarily be underſtood, that the Judicature is naturally and conſtantly lodged with the Lords, and the Houſe of Commons part then is onely to bring the Offender before the Lords to be tryed? This very Record of the Proceedings in the Lords Houſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Gomeniz</hi> and <hi>Weſton</hi> ſhews it ſo to be, and proves the Judicature of
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:152672:105"/>the Houſe of Peers as ſtrongly as can be; It runs thus, <hi>Item par la ou ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plié eſt par les Communes, que tous ceux qunt rendus &amp; perdus Chatels ou Villes par dela par uray defaut des Capitaines, puiſſent eſtre a Reſponſe a Ceſt Parlement &amp; ſelon leur deſert fortement punis par agard des Seigneurs &amp; Baronage, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievant le malueis enſample qils ont donnez as autres qui ſont Gardeins de villes &amp; Chatels, Commandé eſt a Sire Alein de Buxhall Coneſtable del Tour de Londres qe y face venir deuant les Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neurs en Parlement a Weſtminſter le Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dredy</hi> 27 <hi>Jour de Novembre lán ſuſdit Jehan ſire de Gomeniz &amp; William de Weſton,</hi> &amp;c. Item, <hi>Whereas it is prayed by the Commons that all thoſe, who have delivered up and loſt Caſtles and Towns on the other ſide of the Sea by their own default, being Captains of them, may be put to their anſwer at this Parliament, and according to their deſert be ſeverely puniſhed by the award of the Lords and Baronage, for the eſchewing of the evil example, which they have given to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Guardians of Towns and Caſtles;
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:152672:106"/>Command is given to Sir</hi> Allen de Bux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall <hi>Conſtable of the</hi> Tower <hi>of</hi> London, <hi>to bring before the Lords in Parliament at</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>upon Friday the</hi> 27th <hi>of</hi> November <hi>of the aforeſaid year,</hi> John <hi>Lord of</hi> Gomeniz, <hi>and</hi> William <hi>of</hi> We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here the Commons deſire that all ſuch may be ſeverely puniſhed by the award of the Lords and Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage; So it is their Award and their Judgment muſt puniſh, and this by the Commons confeſſion; And you may obſerve further, that the Commons do not make any mention of any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſon, but the Lords they command Sir <hi>Allein de Buxhall</hi> to bring <hi>Gomeniz</hi> and <hi>Weſton</hi> before them ſuch a day; But it is eaſie to trace the Author of the Pamphlet, where he was led out of the way, and that was by an other Pamphlet of the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the Baronage, which goes under Mr. <hi>Seldens</hi> Name, but hath as many miſtakes in it as leaves, and there indeed it is ſaid <hi>p. 15.</hi> That at the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the Commons, that all thoſe who have rendred Caſtles, be
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:152672:106" rendition="simple:additions"/>put to their Anſwer, and that <hi>Allen Buxhall,</hi> Conſtable of the Tower, do bring before the Lords ſuch a day, <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meniz</hi> and <hi>Weſton,</hi> to anſwer the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles which there ſhall be preferred for the ſaid Cauſe, they were ſo brought, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But the Record it ſelf you ſee is otherwiſe, which that Pamphleter it ſeems never read. And for what he further would infer, to make that and all other Judgements at the proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Commons (admit they had been ſo, which theſe were not) Acts of Parliament, is a Fancy ſo ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, as it is not worth the anſwering, which makes no difference betwixt an Act of Attainder, that paſſeth both Houſes, and afterwards hath the Kings Aſſent, (as all other Laws have, which is an effect of the Legiſlative Power, in which either Houſe hath an equal Vote) and a proceeding before the Lords againſt a Criminous Perſon in a Judicial way, wherein the Commons have nothing to do, as to the judging of him.</p>
            <pb n="210" facs="tcp:152672:107" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>But one thing more in that Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let I cannot let paſs, which is in <hi>p.</hi> 12. The words are theſe, <hi>viz. For the Kings giving Judgment in Parliament with the Lords Aſſent, I do confeſs Judgements there ought to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and punctually entred, as given Par noſtre Seigneur le Roy que eſt Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verain. Juge en tous Cas, &amp; par les Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neurs Spirituels &amp; Temporels ouel Aſſent des Communes de la Terre, ou a leur Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, &amp; Nenny par les Seigneurs Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porels Seulement;</hi> That is, <hi>As given by our Lord the King, who is Sovereign Judge in all Cauſes, and by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, with the aſſent of the Commons of the Land, or upon their Petition, and not by the Lords Temporal alone.</hi> And for this he quotes in the Margent, <hi>Rot. Part. apud Leiceſter,</hi> II. 16. which he delivers ſo Magiſterially, as any man would ſwear he had good Authority for what he ſaid, and that his old French was ſome old Oracle of Parliament: And I muſt confeſs upon the firſt reading of this I was at a ſtand, finding here ſuch a poſitive Precept,
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:152672:107" rendition="simple:additions"/>contrary to what I had ſtill believed, both in the Affirmative <hi>(it muſt be by the Kings and Lords, with the Aſſent of the Commons)</hi> and Negative <hi>(not by the Lords alone.)</hi> But when I came to examine this Aſſertion by the Record, I found there was a foul miſtake, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther purpoſely or ignorantly I judge not: For what was delivered by Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, to bolſter up his Clients pretenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, is there produced, as the Rule of the Court; And an Error aſſigned to reverſe a former Judgment, which is but the Allegation of a Lawyer, that draws up his Clients Plea, is made an Argument to controul and condemn a conſtant uſage of the Houſe of Peers, It was in the Caſe of the Earl of <hi>Salisbury, Who brought a Writ of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in the Parliament</hi> 2. H. 5. <hi>to reverſe the Judgment given</hi> 2. H. 4. n. 30. <hi>by the Lords Temporal alone with the Kings Aſſent, by which Judgment the Earls of</hi> Kent, Huntington <hi>and</hi> Salisbury, <hi>and ſome others, who had been ſome ſlain, ſome taken in actual Rebellion by other the Kings Subjects, and by them put to
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:152672:108" rendition="simple:additions"/>death without form of Law, were decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red attainted of Treaſon, and their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates forfeited; For the reverſal where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of</hi> Thomas <hi>the Son Earl of</hi> Salisbury, <hi>amongſt the Errors aſſigns this for one, as a principal one, that it was given by the Lords Temporal alone with the King, whereas it ſhould have been by the King, Lords Spiritual and Temporal, with the Aſſent of the Commons, or at their Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> And what follows upon this? In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed if the Judgment had been rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, though perhaps upon ſome other Error, (for ſeveral others were aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) there might have been ſome co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour for the Gentlemans Aſſertion, and the Inference he would make up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it: But ſo far from it, that the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment formerly given by the Lords Temporal alone, with the Kings Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, is fully ratified and confirmed: Which is as ſtrong an Argument to evince and prove the Right of Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature lodged in that Houſe as is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</p>
            <p>And ſo I ſhall leave that Pamphle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and now conclude, only adding
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:152672:108"/>this as mine own ſenſe and wiſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Lords exerciſing this Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature, and in truth what hath been my Obſervation of their Lordſhips own Intention and Reſolution, which themſelves have ſtill declared and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed in their execution of it; which is this.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That though they have an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Right to ſuch an univerſal un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited Power; of taking cogniſance of all Manner of Cauſes of what na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſoever, and of the Judging and Determining them, if no particular Law do otherwiſe diſpoſe of thoſe Caſes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That their Anceſtors have ſo exerciſed this Power in all times Ancient and Modern, which conveys down that Right to them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Maxim, <hi>uſus &amp; Conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etudo eſt Lex Parlamenti,</hi> what hath been alwayes uſed by Parliaments is the Law of Parliaments.</p>
            <pb n="214" facs="tcp:152672:109"/>
            <p>Thirdly, That this Houſe of Lords hath ever been careful not to entertain any buſineſs, which was determinable in Inferior Courts, ſo as charged with doing it, they may well take up the Pſalmiſts complaint, and ſay, <hi>They have laid to our charge things that we knew not, and would have us reſtore what we took not away;</hi> Though if the Lords had now taken upon them to exerciſe ſuch an univerſal Power of Judicature, they had medled but with their own, that which belongs to them, and had done no man wrong, had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven no juſt cauſe of complaint, they had but troden in their Anceſtors ſteps, continued that in the Houſe of Peers, which it hath ever been poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of. And would it not be a ſhame for them to leave their Poſterity in a lower and more curtalled condition then their Predeceſſors left them, to give up a Right and a Priviledge o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theirs, which (as hath been ſhewed) i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo neceſſary to the Publick Juſtic<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Kingdom? But they have no<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> done that, which is ſaid of them: An<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="215" facs="tcp:152672:109"/>there is no colour for any complaint. Why then quarrel with them? Why at this time ſtir a queſtion which lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep, and for ought we know had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver awaked, not had elſe ever been ſtirred? Is this a time to divide, to cauſe needleſs differences? Were it not more deſirable, nay more neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to reconcile affections, to unite en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, and to conjoyn the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and Power, and Authority of the two Houſes of Parliament, for compoſing the differences which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready are, rather then to create new, and eſpecially when no cauſe is given for it? For it may be truly ſaid, Here is not <hi>Cauſa litigandi,</hi> if there be not <hi>Animus litigandi.</hi> Let it be calmly and coolely conſidered, what the Lords have done, if they have given any cauſe of difference, if this Apple of Diſſention grew with them, which hath been maliciouſly caſt in by ſome of the Eaſt India Company, and too readily taken up by thoſe whom they had ſurpriſed and abuſed by miſinfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations. Their Lordſhips have now
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:152672:110"/>only done Right to a poor man, that was oppreſſed to ruine by potent Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, who had done the wrong in a Forreign Countrey, and ſo were no wayes puniſhable for it here in the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Courſe of Law, nor the poor man any wayes relievable, (for no part of his Caſe, as hath been ſhewed, was within the Compaſs of the Common Law: Their new deviſe of a Fiction, which is in truth meerly a Fiction, in the whole of it, without any real foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in Law, Reaſon, or good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience as being grounded upon a falſhood, and yet this Fiction (I ſay) ſuch as it is, not applicable to Treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) ſo as here had been an abſolute Failer of Juſtice, if the Lords had not undertaken it; And they undertaking it alſo, not of themſelves, as making it their own Act, but upon the Kings ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Recommendation, when his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and Counſel had in vain ſpent ſome years in endeavouring to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade thoſe ſevere Adverſaries of this poor man, to make him ſome reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Reparation, and they would not.</p>
            <pb n="217" facs="tcp:152672:110"/>
            <p>Fourthly, And notwithſtanding all this, that their Lordſhips ſhould be quarrelled with, decried, miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by Offenders, whom they had before them; and that, even before they had determined any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them: yet the Petition of thoſe Offenders full of Falſities, not onely to be received, which (under Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and with great reſpect be it ſpoken of them who did receive it) was a Manifeſt Breach of Priviledge, but to be believed, and Votes to be paſſed thereupon, <hi>That the Lords had done that, which was not agreeable to Law, and which tended to deprive the Subject of the benefit of the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, Though theſe things might well provoke their Lordſhips to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate themſelves, not only by aſſerting their Right to ſo great and extenſive a Power, (which they have done upon good grounds, and with evincing Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaments) but even employing and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing it in its full latitude; And the ſame Maxim would juſtifie them in
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:152672:111"/>their ſo doing, which the Poet brought to juſtifie <hi>Caeſar</hi> in his vaſt underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, when the Senate by denying him his juſt demands, gave him the occaſion and the boldneſs to make himſelf Maſter of all, take that which was denied him and all the reſt, which happily he had elſe never attempted, the Maxim is, <hi>Omnia dat qui juſta ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat:</hi> So quarrelling with the Lords now upon ſo unjuſt a ground, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying them ſuch an apparent Right as they had to give Relief to <hi>Skinner,</hi> would plead their excuſe to all the World, if they ſhould extend their Power as far, as their Anceſtors ever did.</p>
            <p>But we will hope better things from them, and that (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>their Moderation ſhall appear to all men,</hi> and that no ill uſage will make them depart from their reſolution of not interpoſing their Power, where the Law can give a remedy, nor enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining any Cauſe, which is properly determinable in Inferior Courts, For
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:152672:111"/>that certainly, however it might be Lawful, would not be expedient, and good men will onely do that which is expedient, as being that which is moſt acceptable to God, and moſt benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to men, which Parliaments will I hope ever do, It ſhall be my Prayer they may, to which I am ſure all good people will ſay Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
